Actuarial Science (CBA)

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Actuarial Science (CBA)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (28 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Susan Vagts

DESCRIPTION

Interim Director and Associate Professor of Practice: Vagts

Professor: Ramsay

Associate Professor: Mashayekhi

Assistant Professor: Shi

An actuary is a mathematically-oriented business person who will most likely be a manager or supervisor at some point in his/her career. Thus, a course of study culminating in a bachelor of science degree in business administration with a major in actuarial science is an excellent educational background for prospective actuaries. Additional information is available at www.BeAnActuary.org.

The actuarial science program is designed to prepare students for the current industry demands. Because the demands change on a regular basis, often times, the number of hours, the sequencing of courses, and the specific requirements change for this major. Students should continue to consult with the department for the appropriate selection and listing of course requirements.

The actuarial science program is proud to have been named one of the first Centers of Actuarial Excellence by the Society of Actuaries.

All actuarial science students are encouraged to visit the actuarial science program’s website (http://cba.unl.edu/academics/actuarial/) and an actuarial science program faculty adviser for more information about the program, including the Actuarial Science Club, sequencing of courses, scholarship opportunities, and the requirements for achieving professional actuarial designations.

In addition, because of the mathematical orientation for this program, actuarial science majors are required to make some modifications to the degree program requirements. These requirements (with a reminder that all required course work must be taken for a grade) are noted below.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 28 hours of course work for the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade. Actuarial science majors must take MATH 106, MATH 107, and MATH 208, as well as CSCE 101 & CSCE 101L.
These hours have been built into the College Degree Requirements as part of the Non-Business Requirements (NBR).
ACTS 399/499 may not count toward the major or minor in actuarial science.
Other College Degree Requirement changes for actuarial science majors includes:
ACTS majors must take STAT 380 in place of ECON 215 for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will also take STAT 462 & STAT 463 Introduction to Mathematical Statistics I & II for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will take FINA 461 Advanced Finance in place of FINA 361 for the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirements; the prerequisite of FINA 361 (for FINA 363 and FINA 461) is satisfied with completion of ACTS 440.
12 hours of 300/400-level elective course work is NOT required for actuarial science majors.
As part of the college elective requirements, all students complete ONE business elective course for the program. ACTS majors are WAIVED from this specific requirement; however, all ACTS majors must take an IBCR course and thus, this can be done to meet the business elective requirement. The department suggests ECON 321 or MNGT 428 as part of NBR 6–ACE 9 which then double counts for both the NBR 6 and IBCR requirement. An alternative option is to take FINA 450 International Financial Management to meet the IBCR (FINA 450 can double count towards a Finance major or Finance minor).

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in actuarial science will complete 28 hours of actuarial science course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M):

ACTS 430 Actuarial Applications of Applied Statistics

ACTS 440 Interest Theory

ACTS 470 Life Contingencies I

ACTS 471 Life Contingencies II

ACTS 473 Introduction to Risk Theory

ACTS 475 Actuarial Applications in Practice

FINA 307 Principles of Individual Risk Management & Insurance or FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

Choose one of the following:

ACTS 410 Intro to Credibility, Smoothing of Data & Simulation

ACTS 425 Survival Models

ACTS 450 Stochastic Processes for Actuaries

ACTS 474 Introduction to Property/Casualty Actuarial Science

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities

In addition to the 28 hours for the major, ACTS majors are also encouraged to take:

ACTS 441 Introduction to Financial Economics, ACTS 474 Introduction to Property Casualty Actuarial Science
Actuarial science problem labs as appropriate
MATH 314 Linear Algebra, MATH 221 Differential Equations
At least one of FINA 412, FINA 420, FINA 438, or ECON 413

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, actuarial science majors may double major in finance. The finance department allows double counting of courses for students choosing to obtain a double major in actuarial science and finance.

Actuarial Science and Finance Double Majors

1. Take the Core Finance Requirements.

2. Choose ONE of the four options available. Students may select only ONE option to complete.

a. If choosing the General Finance Option, double majors must take FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis, and cannot take FINA 307 as a finance elective

i. Also, consider choosing FINA 450 as one of the 400-level options to meet the requirement for the major as well as a requirement for the IBCR.

b. For all other options within the finance major, the required and elective finance courses are the same as those of a student obtaining just the finance major.

Finance Minor

Actuarial students may double count their finance courses towards a finance minor. They will follow the regular minor found in the finance section of the Bulletin. The courses used might include:

FINA 307 or FINA 338

FINA 363

FINA 365/ECON 365

FINA 450 or FINA 467 or FINA 412 or FINA 420 or FINA 438

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Actuarial Science Minor

To fulfill the requirements for an actuarial science minor, students must complete:

Twelve (12) graded hours of actuarial science course work; ACTS 440, ACTS 441, ACTS 470, and ACTS 474 are suggested.
No "Pass/No Pass"
ACTS 399 may not be used toward the minor (or major).
The college requires that 75% of the minor be earned on campus.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

OTHER

Actuarial Science Major

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).

Substitutions When Changing Majors

If ACTS students change to a different major in the College of Business Administration, the following substitutions may be made.

ACTS 440 for FINA 361

STAT 380 for ECON 215

Advertising & Public Relations

COLLEGE: Journalism & Mass Communications

MAJOR: Advertising & Public Relations

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Journalism

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Michael Goff

DESCRIPTION

Professors: Brown, Mitchell, Shipley

Associate Professors: Hachtmann, Struthers

Assistant Professors: Jones, Kiambi, Lauerman, Wagler, Wang

Professors of Practice: Goff, James, Larsen

Assistant Professor of Practice: Tidball

The advertising and public relations major prepares students for careers in a wide variety of communication-related areas. Recent graduates have taken jobs in more than 20 states and several other countries in diverse careers such as retail and corporate advertising and marketing, media sales, brand management, media planning, account management, research, public relations, media relations, special event planning, mobile and digital communications, copywriting and layout and design.

The advertising and public relations faculty believes that a successful career must be built upon a solid foundation, an education that combines theory and practice. To achieve that end, the major offers courses in copywriting, layout, media planning, graphics, campaign development, research, management, and strategic communications. The curriculum is designed to emphasize strategy, planning and implementation in creative problem solving.

Much emphasis is placed on individual relationships between faculty and students, an interaction vital to a student’s creative development. An adviser also helps each student tailor an academic plan to meet his or her interests and needs.

In advertising and public relations classes, students often work with actual clients who present real-life problems. This experience gives students a professional perspective on problem solving in many sectors including nonprofit, retail, small business and community organizations as well as large corporations. Students are encouraged to augment their academic experience with internships.

The faculty, with many professional contacts both locally and nationwide, actively help students find jobs within the state and throughout the country. Students interested in majoring in advertising and public relations should contact the college office in 147 Andersen Hall, 402-472-3041.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The major is 39 hours in advertising and public relations.

The courses required for a major in advertising and public relations are as follows:

ADPR 251, ADPR 283, JOMC 101, JOMC 486, JOMC 487 and one of the following:

JOMC 160 or JOMC 161

Additionally, all ADPR majors take one of the following three: ADPR 429, ADPR 439, or ADPR 489, as well as 18 hours from approved electives for the major.

The 18 elective hours below comprise four optional areas of emphasis, including account services, creative/interactive, public relations or sports communication. Students also may select the elective courses from multiple areas of emphasis to provide a broad background. Among the 18 elective hours, students may select courses from JOUR, JOMC or BRDC; however, at least 9 of the 18 elective hours must be chosen from JOUR 201, JOUR 202, ADPR 207 or ADPR elective options numbered 300 or higher.

The account services emphasis includes the following: ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 360, ADPR 434, ADPR 481, and ADPR 484.

The creative/interactive emphasis options include the following: ADPR 323, ADPR 329, ADPR 333, ADPR 339, ADPR 433, ADPR 447, ADPR 458, ADPR 459, ADPR 483, and ADPR 484.

The public relations emphasis options include the following: ADPR 207, ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 417, ADPR 450, ADPR 451; JOUR 201 and JOUR 202.

The sports communication emphasis options include the following: JOMC 101; JOMC 150, JOUR 202; ADPR 450 and ADPR 451.

If approved by the Advertising and Public Relations sequence head, all areas of emphasis may further include the following: ADPR 491 or JOUR 491; ADPR 495 and ADPR 499H.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major. However, the second major in the college will not take the place of a concentration or any of the 72 hours required outside the college.

Graduating seniors also must complete JOMC 98, Senior Assessment. Typically, JOMC 98 is taken in the last semester. However, seniors who have completed all courses for the major may take it in the term preceding graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Internship policy

Students may be able to earn credit for internships under certain circumstances. Please go to the college website and find the Internship Policy under the Student Services tab.

Credit in special experiences

Students may earn up to 6 credit hours toward the degree in some student experiences: Jacht, National Student Advertising Competition, photojournalism reports, depth reports and others. Students may repeat the same course again for additional credit hours, but those credits will not count toward the degree inside or outside the major. Talk with an academic adviser for further information or specific questions.

Aerospace Studies Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Aerospace Studies Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Lt. Col. Christopher Bohn

DESCRIPTION

Department of Aerospace Studies: Lt Colonel Christopher Bohn, U.S. Air Force, Professor of Aerospace Studies, 209 Military and Naval Science Building

Air Force ROTC

The preparation of future Air Force officers is provided through the Air Force ROTC (AFROTC) program. Enrollment is open to any student attending the University on a full-time basis. The curriculum provides the individual with a firm understanding of the concepts of aerospace power and the Air Force mission, organization and operations.

Enrollment in AFROTC is voluntary and accomplished through the fall and spring registration periods. Scholarships are available on a competitive basis. Approximately fifty percent of the students hold scholarships.

General Program

The Air Force ROTC program consists of the General Military Course (GMC) during the freshman and sophomore years and the Professional Officer Course (POC) for the remaining years. All GMC cadets must complete a four-week field training session during the summer between their sophomore and junior years to enter the POC. Field training is a competitively selected process, and all students wishing to pursue a commission through AFROTC must attend field training.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Minor in Aerospace Studies (Joint Military Studies)

The minor in aerospace studies is offered to any student completing the courses of study listed below. The minor not only prepares cadets for active duty service but provides any student the opportunity to study one of our country’s major instruments of power, the United States Military. In addition to studying Air Force organizations, missions and operations, the student will gain a broad perspective of the military in general by studying the history of all Department of Defense Services, thus emphasizing our country’s focus on Joint Military Operations.

Course Requirements (18 cr)

1. AERO 331, AERO 332, AERO 441, AERO 442 (total 12 cr)

2. 3 cr from the following: MNGT 320, MNGT 360, MNGT 361, MNGT 411, MNGT 414, MNGT 464, or MNGT 466

3. 3 cr from the following: HIST 303, HIST 304; GEOG 272; POLS 160, POLS 260, POLS 360, POLS 363, POLS 462

Active Duty Obligation

There is no active duty obligation for enrolling in any AFROTC courses, unless a student wishes to become an Active Duty Air Force Officer or accepts an Air Force scholarship. Students who complete the Air Force ROTC program and receive a commission, incur a four-year active duty commitment. Flying officers serve additional commitments from the time they complete their training.

Agribusiness (CBA)

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Agribusiness (CBA)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (31 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

DESCRIPTION

Director: TBA

UNL’s agribusiness program is nationally recognized for its innovation and quality. The program is designed to meet the agribusiness industry’s needs for professionals and entrepreneurs who have the educational background to become successful decision-makers in the rapidly changing agribusiness world. Agribusiness students interact with agribusiness professionals through learning and work-related opportunities, both in and out of the classroom.

Majoring in the agribusiness program prepares students for many agribusiness careers, such as:

Agribusiness Management

Finance and Lending

Real Estate Management and Investment

Commodity Trade and Analysis

Grain Merchandising

Market Planning and Analysis

International Marketing

Entrepreneurship and New Business Development

Sales Management

Information Technology and Analysis

Production Management

Food Marketing and Industry Organization

The agribusiness major also prepares students for graduate study in agribusiness, business administration, and agricultural economics.

The agribusiness major is a joint program between the College of Business Administration and the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources. It prepares students for careers in this dynamic and constantly changing field. It is the first program of this kind in the U.S. and is designed to meet the agribusiness industry’s need for employees with training in both business and agriculture.

Agribusiness majors take a blend of courses in business and agriculture that gives the student a balance between the decision-making framework of business and the technical aspects of modern agriculture and food systems. This means emphasis is placed on business and agriculture, making it an attractive degree for agribusiness employers and a very marketable degree for agribusiness students. The program also allows the student to build expertise in their area of interest by taking College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources courses in a specific area.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
Agribusiness majors may elect to fulfill the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirement of MNGT 350/MIST 350 with MRKT 350.
Students interested in agronomy or chemical sales are recommended to take CHEM 109.
Agribusiness majors through the College of Business Administration may not count AECN 141 Introduction to the Economics of Agriculture toward the degree unless transferring in from another college.
Double counting options: There are several agriculture courses offered through the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources that may be used to fulfill both requirements for Non-Business Requirements (NBR) for the College as well as for the agribusiness major:
NBR 3 (ACE 4) – AGRI 115, AGRO 131, ENTO 115, MSYM 109, NRES 108, PLPT 110 may be taken to fulfill the science requirement (NBR 3–ACE 4) as well as a requirement for the major.
NBR 6 (ACE 9) – AECN 346, AECN 367, AECN 420, AECN 425, AGRI 282, ENSC 110, HORT 200, may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) as well as a requirement for the major.
In instances where double counting occurs, course work selected for the first major that is also double counted for NBR may not, in turn, also be used to satisfy the College electives of 300/400-level requirement nor may NBR course work double counting for the major be double counted for any minor in which these courses could be used to fulfill minor requirements. In other words, students may choose to have the NBR approved course work double count for the first major or minor (not both) and only in the instance of the double count with the minor may the hours also count for the 300/400-level College electives.
18 hours of the 24 hours required in production, non-production, and elective hours must be taken at the 200 level or above.
Most course work for the major is offered out of the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR).

Specific Major Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 31 hours of course work for the major.

AECN 201 Farm & Ranch Management (4 hours)

MRKT 225 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship in Food Products Marketing or MRKT 325 Marketing of Agricultural Commodities (3 hours each)

Minimum of 6 hours of PRODUCTION course work from the following departments:

Agriculture (AGRI) (not AGRI 042) (May opt to take AGRI 115 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major; and/or AGRI 282 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Agronomy (AGRO) (May opt to take AGRO 131 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Animal Science (ASCI)

Energy Science (ENSC) (May opt to take ENSC 110 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Entomology (ENTO) (May opt to take ENTO 115 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Food Science & Technology (FDST)

Horticulture (HORT) (May opt to take HORT 200 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Mechanical Systems Management (MSYM) (May opt to take MSYM 109 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Natural Resources & Environmental Economics (NRES) (May opt to take NRES 108 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Plant Pathology (PLPT) (May opt to take PLPT 110 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Veterinary and Biomedical Sciences (VBMS)

MINIMUM of 9 hours of NON-PRODUCTION course work from the following departments:

Agricultural Economics (AECN) (May opt to take AECN 346, AECN 367, AECN 420, AECN 425 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Agricultural Education (ALEC)

The following courses may not be selected to fulfill this requirement: AECN 141, AECN 201, AECN 225/EAEP 225/MRKT 225, AECN 325/MRKT 325 (depending on which one was selected for above requirement).

MINIMUM of 9 hours of ELECTIVE course work beyond those selected for any of the above may be selected from the following College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources departments:

Agricultural Economics (AECN) (not AECN 141, AECN 201) (May opt to take AECN 346, AECN 367, AECN 420, AECN 425 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Agriculture (AGRI) (not AGRI 042) (May opt to take AGRI 115 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major or AGRI 282 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Agricultural Education

Agronomy (AGRO) (May opt to take AGRO 131 for ACE 4 and major.)

Animal Science (ASCI)

Biochemistry (BIOC)

Energy Science (ENSC) (May opt to take ENSC 110 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Entomology (ENTO) (May opt to take ENTO 115 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Food Science and Technology (FDST)

Horticulture (HORT) (May opt to take HORT 200 to fulfill both ACE 9 and major.)

Mechanized Systems Management (MSYM) (May opt to take MSYM 109 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Natural Resources and Environmental Economics (NRES) (May opt to take NRES 108 to fulfill both ACE 4 and major.)

Plant Pathology (PLPT) (May opt to take PLPT 110 to fulfill ACE 4 and major.)

Range (RNGE)

SOIL (SOIL)

Veterinary and Biomedical Sciences (VBMS)

Water Science (WATS)

Eighteen of the 24 hours (6 hours production, 9 hours non-production, and 9 hours College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources electives) must be completed at the 200 level or above. Courses and descriptions appear under the individual departmental majors.

Students should consult with their adviser for the appropriate selection of courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

OTHER

The program requires and enforces that specific prerequisite requirements be completed by the first class meeting. Concurrent registration in a class that is a prerequisite for another class is NOT allowed. Transfer credit assumes that the prerequisites have been transferred to UNL and appear on the transcript.
For the International Business Course Requirement (IBCR), most agribusiness majors will take MRKT 453 (providing 6 hours of marketing are done), counting it to fulfill both the IBCR and one of the 300/400-level requirements for the college ELECTIVES requirement. However, for students interested in other areas, the other IBCR courses will work as well.
Students should refer to the Non-Business Requirement (NBR) section for options to complete course work to double count for NBR 3–ACE 4 and/or NBR 6–ACE 9 requirements as well as course work for the major. Please work closely with an adviser.
12 hours of ELECTIVES for the College (beyond the major) must be done at 300/400-level.
If course work for the agribusiness major (BCA-M) exceeds 21 hours at the 300/400-level, a student may appeal (see the agribusiness adviser in CBA 310) to double count the additional hours toward the 300/400-level requirement.
This double counting option will work as long as these hours have not already been double counted as part of the major and NBR requirements.
60 hours of business course work must be completed for the degree. Given the unique nature of the agribusiness major and program, required course work for the degree, as well as course work for the major, is considered to be ‘business’ related and thus counted toward meeting this college requirement.
In all instances of ‘double counting,’ the course will count for 3 hours of credit. Students must still meet the minimum 120 hour requirement of course work to graduate.

Agricultural Education

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Agricultural Education

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Agricultural Education

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation, 2.75 for graduation with teaching option

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes-Environmental Communication, Leadership & Communication, Leadership & Entrepreneurship

CHIEF ADVISER: Lloyd Bell (teaching), Gina Matkin (agricultural leadership)

DESCRIPTION

Head: Mark Balschweid, Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication; 300 Agriculture Hall

Professors: Bell, Husmann, Terry

Associate Professor: Matkin

Assistant Professors: Cannon, Kang, Hastings, McElravy

Assistant Professors of Practice: Garbacz, Kreifels

A degree in agricultural education is designed to prepare students with the necessary communication and interpersonal skills, leadership training, and knowledge of technical agriculture to be a teacher of agricultural education at the secondary or postsecondary level, or accept employment in agribusiness leading to positions in training and/or development. The degree provides good preparation for work in agricultural extension, positions in foreign service, and agricultural educators in business and industry. Many students graduate with a dual degree in agricultural education and another degree in the College. Agricultural education students may elect to follow the teaching options or the leadership option.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Students desiring to be admitted to the Teacher Education program in the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication should apply as early as possible after the completion of at least 42 credit hours (at least one year before they plan to student teach). Student teaching is conducted off campus through university-approved agreements with cooperating secondary schools. Plans for student teaching must be made early.

To be admitted into the student teaching program candidates must have: 1) a minimum scholastic grade point average of 2.75 including no grades lower than “C” within the endorsement area, and no grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses, 2) passing scores within the Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), 3) 1,000 hours of verified work experience within the agriculture, food, natural resources (AFNR) career cluster, or 300 hours of supervised employment in the AFNR career cluster under the direction of a UNL academic unit, 4) three written letters of recommendation; one of which must be a character reference. Student Teaching (ALEC 431) is available as Pass/No Pass only. Meet with your adviser to plan for your student teaching experience.

Other Admission Requirements

Teaching Certificate

Successful completion of the teaching endorsement requirements, along with a recommendation by the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication, warrants recommendation for a Nebraska Secondary Teaching Certificate by the Nebraska Department of Education, with an endorsement to teach secondary agricultural education (7-12). The choice is available to students to complete course work qualifying for subject endorsement in biology.

Students in other agricultural degree programs may qualify based upon meeting the teaching certificate requirements.

Criminal History/Background Check

Effective August 2012, individuals enrolled in any UNL teacher education course requiring a practicum experience in schools or other institutions must have successfully completed a background review prior to any practicum visitations. Two successful reviews will be required during your teacher preparation program; one prior to your initial practicum experience, and a second prior to your student teaching field experience. Background reviews must be completed through One Source, The Background Check Company. See your adviser or practicum course instructor for necessary details to request and complete a background review.

Nebraska State Department of Education Policy Pertaining to Students with Felony or Misdemeanor Convictions

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with felony convictions or misdemeanor convictions involving abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval by the Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the Department of Agricultural Education will require each student to affirm under oath that he/she does not have any convictions in the above-named areas prior to each field placement. If a student does have any felony or misdemeanor convictions, he/she is required to meet with Dr. Tom Wandzilak, Certification Officer, Student Services Center, 104 Henzlik Hall, 402-472-8626, as soon as possible. Students with questions pertaining to convictions should contact Dr. Wandzilak.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Teaching Option

College Integrative Courses 15

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

ALEC 431 Student Teaching (ACE 10) (Capstone Course) (P/NP only) 12

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) 5-6

Select from:

MATH 106 Calculus I (5 cr)

MATH 102 Trigonometry (2 cr) or MATH 103 (If MATH 103 is taken, only 2 credit hours can be counted toward this requirement.) or MATH 104 Applied Calculus (3 cr) or MATH 203 Contemporary Mathematics (3 cr) and STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (ACE 3) or EDPS 459 Statistical Methods (3 cr)

Communications 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Oral Communication 3

Select from: COMM 209 or COMM 286

Communication/Interpersonal Skills: ALEC 102 (ACE 2) 3

Natural Sciences (ACE 4) 12-13

CASNR Approved Life Sciences 4

Select one course from:

AGRO 131 & AGRO 132 Plant Science & Agronomic Plant Science Lab

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab

BIOS 109 General Botany

BIOS 112 & BIOS 112L Introduction to Zoology & Lab

ENTO 115 Insect Biology & ENTO 116 Insect Identification

FDST 131 & FDST 131L The Science of Food & Lab

HORT 131 & HORT 133 Plant Science & Horticultural Plant Science Lab

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I (formerly BIOS 102)

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I 4

NOTE: Students pursuing combined agriculture-biology endorsement must complete CHEM 109.

PHYS 141, PHYS 151, PHYS 211 or MSYM 109 4-5

Economics 3

AECN 141 Introduction to the Economics of Agriculture (ACE 6) 3

Humanities and Social Sciences 15

EDPS 457 Learning & Motivation Principles for Secondary Teaching or EDPS 362 Learning in the Classroom 3

SOCI 217 Nationality & Race Relations or TEAC 330 Multicultural
Education (ACE 9) 3

Humanities and Social Sciences electives 9

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, and 8.

Agricultural and Natural Resource Sciences (Endorsement Area) 36

A minimum of 15 hours completed at the 200 level or above, and a minimum of 9 hours completed at the 300 level or above. Students must have a course in four CASNR departments or program areas. A course may be used to fulfill more than one category; however, the hours will only count once toward the 36-hour agricultural science requirement.

NOTE: No grades lower than “C” within the endorsement area.

Research and Applied Technology 3

Select from: AGRI 115, AGRO 315, AGRO 431, FDST 131

Policy 3

Select from: AECN 265, AECN 276, AECN 346, AECN 376, NRES 323, POLS 235, POLS 236

Management 9

Select from: AECN 201, AECN 325, ASCI 250, ASCI 320, ASCI 330, ASCI 450, ASCI 451, ASCI 452, ASCI 453, ASCI 454, ASCI 455, ASCI 457, AGRO 204, AGRO 240, AGRO 405, HORT 325

Production 3

Select from: ASCI 100, ASCI 150, HORT 131 and HORT 133, HORT 159, HORT 221, HORT 325, HORT 327, HORT 350

Natural Resources 6

Select from: AECN 265, AGRO 153, AGRO 366, BIOS 232, ENTO 109, NRES 211, NRES 220, NRES 311

Mechanized Systems (courses available through SCC-Lincoln or SCC-Milford) 9

NOTE: Meet with your adviser to plan for your Mechanized Systems classes.

Select from: MSYM 245 (UNL), AUTT 1003, WELD 1060 & 1070, WELD 1080 & 1090, CNST 1100, CNST 1200

Food System 3

Select from: AECN 225, ASCI 210, FDST 101 or FDST 131

Leadership and Education (Professional Education Courses) 20

NOTE: No grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses.

ALEC 134 Agricultural Education, Journalism, & Leadership Careers 2

ALEC 135 Early Field Experience in Agricultural Leadership, Education & Communication 1

ALEC 234 Planning Leadership & Experience Programs 3

ALEC 308 Lab Instruction & Management 3

ALEC 405 Methods of Instruction for Secondary Agriscience Education 3

ALEC 405L Methods of Instruction Laboratory Education 1

ALEC 413 Program Development 3

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

SPED 401B Accommodating Exceptional Learners in the Secondary School Classroom or SPED 434 Introduction to Special Vocational Needs 3

Free Electives 3-5

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

Biology Endorsement Requirements

If the student desires to qualify for both an endorsement in agricultural education and a subject endorsement in biology, the following course work should be integrated into the teaching option.

Supporting Laboratory Based Courses (12 hours)

Chemistry: CHEM 109 4

Physics: PHYS 141, PHYS 151, PHYS 211 or MSYM 109 4-5

Earth Science: AGRO 153/HORT 153/SOIL 153 Soil Resources 4

Biology Courses (24 hours)

Select at least one of the suggested courses from each of the following categories. A course may be used more than once toward fulfilling the content requirement, however a minimum of 24 different hours is required. At least 12 hours must be taken at the 200 level or higher. Other course work may be negotiated with your academic adviser.

Botany

BIOS 109 General Botany 4

AGRO 131 & AGRO 132 Plant Science & Agronomic Lab 4

AGRO 204 Resource-Efficient Crop Management 3

AGRO 240/RNGE 240 Forage Crop & Range Management 4

HORT 131 & HORT 133 Plant Science & Horticultural Plant Science Lab 4

Cell Biology/Biochemistry

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab or BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab 4

Ecology

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

NRES 211 Introduction to Conservation Biology 3

NRES 311 Wildlife Ecology & Management 3

Evolution

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

Genetics

AGRO 315 Genetics 4

Human Biology

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab 4

Microbiology

FDST 372/NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation 3

Zoology

ASCI 240 Anatomy & Physiology of Domestic Animals 4

NOTE: To be eligible for the biology endorsement, a student must maintain a minimum grade point average of 2.75 in the above course work or its equivalency.

Integrated Laboratory Management

ALEC 308 Laboratory Instruction & Management 3

Science Methods Instruction

TEAC 451V Learning & Teaching Principles & Practices 3

TEAC 397 Professional Practicum Experience III parallel with TEAC 451V 1

Student Teaching

Students seeking a dual endorsement will be required to complete their student teaching experience in a school where they will spend teaching time in both biology and agriculture.

Horticulture Education Endorsement Requirements

If the student desires to add a subject endorsement in horticulture education to their teaching certification, the following course work should be completed.

Horticulture Education (Grades 7-12) 33

ALEC 400 Overview to Program Planning or ALEC 413 Program Development 3

HORT 131/AGRO 131 Plant Science 3

HORT 133 Horticultural Plant Science Lab 1

HORT 153/AGRO 153/SOIL 153 Soil Resources 4

HORT 212/LARC 212/NRES 212 Landscape Plants I or HORT 213/LARC 213/NRES 213 Landscape Plants II 3

HORT 221 Plant Propagation 3

HORT 227/AGRO 227/PGAM 227/TLMT 227 Introductory Turfgrass Management 3

HORT 228/AGRO 228/PGAM 228/TLMT 228 Introduction to Landscape Management 3

HORT 261 Floral Design I 3

HORT 325 Greenhouse Practices & Management 4

HORT 395/AGRO 395/TLMT 395 Career Experience 3

Skilled and Technical Sciences 2+2 Teaching Option

The following is a 2+2 program for students interested in obtaining certification in Skilled and Technical Sciences (STS). This certification will allow an individual to teach Skilled and Technical Sciences in a Nebraska secondary school (grades 7-12). Completion of the 60 credit hour requirement in the Skilled and Technical Sciences 2 + 2 Teaching Option at UNL, along with the completion of an associate of applied science within a post-secondary institution with a 2 + 2 agreement, will allow a student to complete a BS degree in agricultural education from UNL.

The program is an agreement between the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR) and community college systems in Nebraska. The 2+2 program requires a student to complete the first two years at a community college and earn an associate of applied science degree before transferring to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln (UNL).

The transfer policy in CASNR will be in effect for all students interested in the STS 2+2 program. This 2+2 program is for the STS teaching program and will be the only program available for students to become certified at UNL. Students transferring into other UNL programs other than the STS program must follow the requirements set forth through the departments within the specific colleges.

The prerequisite for entry into the STS certification program at UNL is the completion of the Skilled and Technical Sciences Program at a community college with a 2 + 2 Skilled and Technical Sciences Agreement. Students who transfer into UNL from other programs within the community college system will not be eligible for entry into the 2+2 program in STS at UNL.

To be admitted into the student teaching program candidates must have: 1) a minimum scholastic grade point average of 2.75 including no grades lower than “C” within the endorsement area, and no grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses; 2) passing scores within the Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST); 3) 1,000 hours of verified work experience within the Skilled and Technical Sciences (STS) career cluster, or 300 hours of supervised employment in the STS career cluster under the direction of a UNL academic unit; and 4) three written letters of recommendation; one of which must be a character reference. Student Teaching (ALEC 431) is available as Pass/No Pass only. Meet with your adviser to plan for your student teaching experience.

Teaching Certificate. Successful completion of the teaching endorsement requirements, along with a recommendation by the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication, warrants recommendation for a Nebraska Secondary Teaching Certificate by the Department of Education, with an endorsement to teach skilled and technical sciences (7-12).

STS Teaching Option

Students who meet entry requirements in the STS Teaching Option will have completed a variety of course work from their community college. Many of the courses within the community college system have direct equivalencies with our ACE program at UNL. Following a comprehensive transfer analysis, students will be provided an accurate degree audit of the remaining ACE courses needed at UNL along with the professional program in Agricultural Education. The minimum requirements of CASNR reflect the common core of courses that apply to students pursuing degrees in the college. Students should work with an adviser to satisfy ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 10 requirements. ACE requirements 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, and 9 will be completed through their academic programs within the community college system since it is a requirement for an associate of applied science degree at their institutions.

ACE Requirements 9

Students should work with an adviser to select one course each in ACE outcomes 5, 7, and 8.

Leadership and Education (Professional Education Courses) 42

NOTE: No grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses.

ALEC 135 Early Field Experience in Agricultural Leadership, Education & Communication 1

ALEC 308 Lab Instruction & Management 3

ALEC 405 Methods of Instruction for Secondary Agriscience Education 3

ALEC 405L Methods of Instruction Lab Education 1

ALEC 413 Program Development 3

ALEC 424 Foundations of Career & Technical Education 3

ALEC 431 Student Teaching (ACE 10) 12

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

ALEC 496 Independent Study in Leadership Education (SkillsUSA/PDP) 3

EDPS 209 Strategies for Academic Success 3

EDPS 457 Learning and Motivation Principles for Secondary Teaching or EDPS 362 Learning in the Classroom 3

SPED 401B Accommodating Exceptional Learners in the Secondary School Classroom or SPED 434 Introduction to Special Vocational Needs 3

TEAC 259 Instructional Technology 3

Free Electives 9

Program Credit Requirements 51

STS Credit Requirements for BS Degree in Agricultural Education 60

Maximum Credits for Transfer into UNL 60

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

Agricultural Leadership Option

The Agricultural Leadership Option is recommended for those interested in pursuing a career in the agricultural industry in the areas of leadership development, commodity board advocacy, executive development, youth and leadership development, extension, consulting/training, organizational development, human resources, public policy, rural and community development.

College Integrative Courses 8

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

ALEC 495A Internship in Leadership Development (ACE 10) (Capstone Course) 5

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) 5-6

Select from:

MATH 106 Calculus I (5 cr)

MATH 102 Trigonometry (2 cr) or MATH 103 (If MATH 103 is taken, only 2 credit hours can be counted toward this requirement.) or MATH 104 Applied Calculus (3 cr) or MATH 203 Contemporary Mathematics (3 cr) and STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (ACE 3) or EDPS 459 Statistical Methods (3 cr)

Communications 9

Written Communication 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 200, JGEN 300 (ACE 1)

Oral Communication 3

Select from: COMM 209 or COMM 286

Communication/Interpersonal Skills: ALEC 102 (ACE 2) 3

Natural Sciences 8-9

Select 2 of 3 Natural Sciences courses (ACE 4)

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (4 cr)

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I (ACE 4) (4 cr) or CHEM 109 General Chemistry (4 cr)

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151 or MSYM 109 (4-5 cr)

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 12

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

ACE Courses 9

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, and 9.

Minor 12-20

NOTE: An approved minor in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources other than the leadership and communication or leadership and entrepreneurship minor is required or the Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management minor or the Child, Youth & Family Studies minor offered throught the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Major Requirements 33

ALEC 134 Agricultural Education, Journalism, & Leadership Careers 2

ALEC 202 Leadership Development in Small Groups & Teams 3

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations 3

ALEC 305 Presentation Strategies for Agricultural Audiences 3

ALEC 388/AECN 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources 3 (ACE 8)

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership 3

ALEC 410/NRES 413 Environmental Leadership 3

ALEC 414 Classic Figures in Leadership 3

ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities 3

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation 3

ALEC 428/NRES 428 Leadership in Public Organizations 3

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

Free Electives 23-33

Must include one CASNR 3-credit 200-level or higher course from a department other than ALEC or the minor department.

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Students in the teaching option of Agricultural Education need to be aware that CASNR has a 24-credit hour limitation established by the Faculty Senate. Please plan accordingly and review your status with your academic adviser every academic term.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Leadership and Communication Minor

An 18-hour minor in leadership and communication is available through the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication. Combining a leadership and communication minor with any CASNR degree strengthens students’ “employability” base by making them competent technical professionals who are also strong leaders and effective communicators. The 18-hour minor is comprised of upper and lower division courses as follows:

Complete at least three courses from the following list 9

ALEC 102 Interpersonal Skills for Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 202 Leadership Development in Small Groups & Teams (3 cr)

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations (3 cr)

ALEC 305 Presentation Strategies for Agricultural Audiences (3 cr)

The remaining courses are selected from the following list 9

*ALEC 337 Instructional Internship in Leadership Development (3 cr)

ALEC 388/AECN 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources (3 cr)

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 410/NRES 413 Environmental Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 414 Classic Figures in Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities (3 cr)

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation (3 cr)

**ALEC 480 Dynamics of Agricultural Environmental Journalism (3 cr)

***AERO 331 Air Force Leadership Studies I (3 cr)

***AERO 332 Air Force Leadership Studies II (3 cr)

* For students having completed ALEC 102 and who have been selected as teaching assistants.

** Open to students enrolled in the agricultural journalism major only.

*** May be substituted for Air Force ROTC students only.

Leadership and Entrepreneurship Minor

An 18-hour minor in leadership and entrepreneurship is available through a joint program offered by the Departments of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication and the Engler Agribusiness Entrepreneurship Program. This minor is intended for those who are interested in gaining additional professional skills in leadership and entrepreneurship. The 18-hour minor is comprised of theory based and applied courses as well as a final capstone course.

Leadership Courses 6

Select one theory-based course from the following: 3

ALEC 202 Leadership Development in Small Groups & Teams (3 cr)

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations (3 cr)

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation (3 cr)

ALEC 488 Leadership, Power, & Influence (3 cr)

Select one application course from the following: 3

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership (3 cr)

*ALEC 410/NRES 413 Environmental Leadership (3 cr)

*ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities (3 cr)

* Note that Junior standing is required for these two courses.

Entrepreneurship Courses 6

Select one foundational course from the following: 3-4

EAEP 101 Introductory Seminar on Opportunities in Entrepreneurship (1 cr) & EAEP 388/AGRO 388/HORT 388/ENTR 388 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship (3 cr), or

MNGT 121/ENTR 121 Introduction to Entrepreneurial Management (3 cr)

Select one application course from the following: 3

AECN 275/AGRO 275/EAEP 275/ENTR 275/HORT 275 Agribusiness Entrepreneurial Finance (3 cr)

EAEP 488/AGRO 488/ENTR 488/HORT 488 Business Management for Agricultural Enterprises (3 cr)

ENTR 321/MNGT 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations (3 cr)

ENTR 421/MNGT 421 Initiating & Managing Entrepreneurial Growth (3 cr)

EAEP 225/AECN 225/MRKT 225 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship in Food Products Marketing (3 cr)

Experiential Learning in Leadership and/or Entrepreneurship

Select one course from the following: 3

AGRI 310 Study Tours in International Agriculture (3 cr)

ALEC 102 Interpersonal Skills for Leadership (with 20-hour service learning project) (3 cr)

ALEC 153 Chancellor’s Leadership Class (3 cr)

ALEC 165 Pepsi Service Scholars (3 cr)

ALEC 337 Instructional Internship in Leadership Development (credit received for being a Teaching Assistant) (3 cr)

ENTR 322/MNGT 322 Family Business (3 cr)

ENTR 422A/MNGT 422A/822A Small Business Owner or ENTR 422/MNGT 422 Managing Rapid Growth & Change in Organizations (3 cr)

MNGT 423/ENTR 423 Business Plan Development & Decision Making (3 cr)

Internship in Leadership and/or Entrepreneurship 3

ALEC 496 Independent Study in Leadership Education (Field Experience) (3 cr)

EAEP 395 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship Internship (3 cr)

Students who wish to minor in Leadership and Communication must first meet with a Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication (ALEC) faculty member from the leadership program. Students who wish to minor in Leadership and Entrepreneurship must meet with either an ALEC or Engler Agribusiness Entrepreneurship Program faculty member. A completed Declaration of Minor form, filled out with the assistance of the faculty member, should be signed by the student’s academic adviser and turned into the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources Dean’s office.

Anthropology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Anthropology

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Martha McCollough

DESCRIPTION

Chair: LuAnn Wandsnider, 810 Oldfather Hall

Professor: Hames, Wandsnider

Associate Professors: Athanassopoulos, Awakuni-Swetland, McCollough, Willis

Assistant Professor: Osborne

Lecturers: Beyene, Douglass, Hammerl

Adjunct Faculty: Bozell, Connor, Hunt, Hartley, Leite, Lynott

Undergraduate Advisor: Dr. Martha McCollough, 402-472-2441, mmccollough1@unl.edu

Courses in anthropology are designed to acquaint the student with the range of human behavior and emphasize archaeology, physical anthropology, cultural anthropology, applied anthropology, and Omaha language and culture.

The Department of Anthropology participates in the programs in African American and African Studies, Asian Studies, Ethnic Studies, Environmental Studies, Great Plains Studies, Global Studies, Latino and Latin American Studies, Native American Studies, and Women’s and Gender Studies.

Recommendations. Because of the broad and interdisciplinary nature of anthropology, we recommend that majors select additional courses outside the department to enhance their appreciation of and improve their skills in related disciplines. The student’s adviser will make specific course recommendations in keeping with individual needs and interests.

Graduate Work. The Department of Anthropology offers graduate work leading to the master of arts degree. A description of the program appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Graduate Advisor: Dr. Effie Athanassopoulos, 402-472-0172, eathanassopoulos1@unl.edu

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Anthropology (33 hours)

Hours

Foundation Courses 10

ANTH 212 Introduction to Cultural Anthropology 3

ANTH 232 Introduction to Prehistory 3

ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L Introduction to Physical Anthropology & Lab 4

Advanced Anthropology Courses 9

Archaeology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 431 Historical Archaeology: Current Topics (3 hrs)

ANTH 432 History & Theory of Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 433 North American Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 438 Topics in Old World Prehistory (3 hrs)

Biological Anthropology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 422 Medical Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 442 Human Variation (3 hrs)

ANTH 430 Nutritional Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 448 Human Growth & Development (3 hrs)

Cultural Anthropology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 412 Social Structure (3 hrs)

ANTH 417 History of Anthropological Theory (3 hrs)

ANTH 473 Ecological Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 474 Applied & Development Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 477 Hunters-Gatherers (3 hrs)

Research Methods 3-4

Select one course from:

ANTH 290 Fieldwork (3 hrs)

ANTH 482 Research Methods in Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 484 Quantitative Methods in Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 486 Community-Based Research & Evaluation (3 hrs)

ANTH 487A-E Analysis of Archaeological Materials (3 hrs)

ANTH 490 Advanced Field Work (3 hrs)

ANTH 491 Landscape Archaeology (3 hrs)

Electives from 9-10

Select one course from: 100-, 200-, 300-, or 400- series

Fieldwork is recommended. Only 6 credits total of ANTH 290 and ANTH 490 may count toward the major. Only 3 credits of ANTH 291 or ANTH 491 may count toward the major. ANTH 104A, ANTH 105A, ANTH 204A, ANTH 205A, ANTH 210, and ANTH 210A cannot be applied toward the anthropology major.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its program, majors will, as they complete an ACE 10 course in their junior or senior year:

1. Participate in a focus group discussion of programmatic strengths and weaknesses.

2. Complete an exit survey, submitted anonymously.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Graduate Work. Students contemplating graduate work should work closely with adviser to design course of study.

Minor Requirements

A minor may be chosen from any minor offered by the College of Arts and Sciences.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

No course may be taken Pass/No Pass.

Course Level Requirement

At least 12 hours in courses numbered in the 300 and 400 series. May be satisfied by advanced anthropology courses or electives.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Requires 18 hours of anthropology including ANTH 110; at least one of the 200-level core courses in anthropology (ANTH 212 Introduction to Cultural Anthropology, ANTH 232 Introduction to Archaeology, or ANTH 242 Introduction to Physical Anthropology); and, at least one 300- or 400-level anthropology course. Up to 6 hours of field study (ANTH 290, ANTH 291, ANTH 490, ANTH 491) and 6 hours of advanced Native language (ANTH 204, ANTH 205, ANTH 210) courses may apply. Excluded courses: ANTH 104, ANTH 105, ANTH 130.

Arabic Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Arabic Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 12

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Abla Hasan

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Evelyn Jacobson, 1111 Oldfather Hall

Vice Chair: Radha Balasubramanian

Professors: Carr, Hayden-Roy, E. Jacobson, Pereira, Stump

Associate Professors: Balasubramanian, Brantner, González, González-Allende, Guevara, Kalisa, Lorenzo, Mejias-Bikandi, Saskova-Pierce, Shirer

Assistant Professors: Amano, Enkin, Hasan, Kingsbury-Brunetto, Peterson, Velázquez

Emeriti Professors: Fouletier-Smith, M. Jacobson, Martinez, Nickel, Turner, Wilhelmsen

The Department of Modern Languages and Literatures offers courses in Arabic, German, Japanese, the Romance Language group (French, Spanish), and the Slavic group (Czech, Russian). Whenever possible, the courses are conducted in the language that is studied. The aim of instruction is reading, writing, aural and oral proficiency, and an understanding of the life, literature, and culture of the country. Lectures and films in the language studied are offered during the school year for the benefit of the students in the department. Language laboratories supplement class work.

Placement

Incoming students who wish to enter the University’s language program in French, Spanish, and German are required to take the Computer Assisted Placement Examination (CAPE). The results of the placement exam, together with training in a secondary school university, or other prior second language environments, will assist students in finding the level at which they will have the greatest opportunity for success. The examination results will be used in combination with advising to determine appropriate placement in the sequence of courses offered within the department’s curriculum. CAPE is administered in the language laboratory (302 Burnett Hall). Those students exempted from this requirement are expected to enroll in a first semester elementary course (101). Students qualifying for this exemption are defined as follows:

1. Students with no previous second language exposure whatsoever.

2. Students whose second language exposure amounts to one year or less at the U.S. high school level.

3. Students who wish to begin study of a new language other than those previously studied.

For other languages, placement is generally determined by the following criteria for students who come to the University with:

1. 1 semester of a language in high school should take 101 (same language or a new one);

2. 2 or 3 semesters in high school should take 102 (same language);

3. 4 or 5 semesters in high school should take 201;

4. 6 semesters in high school should take 202;

5. 8 semesters or more in high school should take 203.

The department participates in the following interdisciplinary study programs: Institute for Ethnic Studies, Global Studies, Jewish Studies, Latin American Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Women’s and Gender Studies.

Students may receive full credit at the University of Nebraska for education abroad programs in many countries, among these are Costa Rica, France, Germany, Spain, Russia, Japan, and the Czech Republic. See http://educationabroad.unl.edu for a guide to these programs.

Auditing. Audits are allowed in 101 in French, German and Spanish only upon recommendation of the Modern Language Placement Advisers. Otherwise no audits are allowed in 100- and 200-level classes.

Literature in Translation

The Department offers the following literature in translation courses for which no knowledge of a foreign language is necessary. Check the Schedule of Classes to determine which are being taught in any given semester:

MODL 234D Major Themes in World Literature

MODL 298, MODL 398 Special Topics

FREN 282 and GERM 282 Literature in Translation

SPAN 264 and SPAN 265 Spanish-American Literature in Translation I & II

MODL 442/GERM 442/842 Survey of Medieval German Literature in Translation

JAPN 331 Introduction to Japanese Film

JAPN 483 Japanese Literature in Translation

RUSS 482 and RUSS 483 Russian Literature in Translation I & II

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered in French, German, and Spanish. For details, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

12 hours of courses numbered 300 or above:

6 hours from 300 level ARAB courses.
6 additional hours. These 3 hours may be from 300 or above course in a related area in a different department as approved by the undergraduate advisor. Any 300 or above course or independent study course in a related topic can count if approved by the undergraduate advisor.

Specific courses in other departments that may be used to fulfill this requirement are:

HIST 434/834 Palestine & the Arab-Israeli Conflict (JUDS 434)

MODL 300 or above course as approved by the undergraduate advisor

POLS 477/877 Israel & the Middle East (JUDS 477)

RELG 318 Islam in the Modern World

WMNS 408/808 Cross-cultural Mentoring I (ANTH 408/NUTR 408) (cases should be from an Arabic background)

WMNS 409/809 Cross-cultural Mentoring II (ANTH 409/NUTR 409)

Architectural Engineering (Omaha)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Architectural Engineering (Omaha)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Architectural Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 128

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Christine Warren

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Eddy M. Rojas

Program Coordinator: Ece Erdogmus

Professors: Goedert, Merkel, Wang, Waters

Associate Professors: Alahmad, Erdogmus, Li, Morcous, Schwer, Tiller

Assistant Professors: Lau, Norton, Pedersen, Yu

Website: http://engineering.unl.edu/durhamschool/academics/ArchitecturalEngineering.shtml

Architectural Engineering (AE) is a program of the Charles W. Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction. This degree program can only be completed on the Omaha campus. The AE undergraduate program is a four-year program requiring 128 credit hours. A one-year master of architectural engineering (MAE) program of 36 credits is also offered.

The educational objective of the program is to produce graduates who:

Practice architectural engineering as licensed professionals in the following areas of building design:

building structural systems
building mechanical systems
building acoustics
building lighting systems
building electrical systems

Apply the fundamental principles of science, engineering, and mathematics to the analysis of architectural engineering problems
Design solutions to architectural engineering problems under realistic condeitions that include:

identifying relevant issues
formulating solutions
evaluating and selecting a solution
communicating the final design

Architectural engineering (AE) is the engineering design of buildings. Students will have the option to specialize in either the design of building structural systems, building mechanical systems and acoustics or building lighting and electrical systems. The first three years are common to all three fields of specialization, and include the same math and science courses common to all engineering programs. Students will take an introductory course in AE in their first semester. This course exposes the students to the materials and systems that make up a modern building. It will also provide a preview of the work they can expect to do after graduation. This first AE course helps the student to decide if this is the career path he/she wishes to pursue.

In the second semester, the AE student begins the first of a four-course sequence of courses in architecture. The purpose of these courses is to familiarize the engineering student with the thought and design process of architects and to develop an appreciation of the architectural features of buildings. This exposure to architecture is an important part of the student’s education. It develops creativity and gives the AE graduates a unique ability to work effectively with their professional colleagues in architecture.

The intent of the AE program is to develop both breadth and depth. This is done by requiring the students to have a good understanding of all the systems that make up a building while also giving them a specialized education in their chosen option areas. The breadth is provided in the 5th and 6th semesters, with all students taking courses in each of the three areas of specialization. The depth is provided in the 7th and 8th semesters, as the program splits into the three option areas.

A one-year master of architectural engineering degree follows the four-year undergraduate program. This fifth year continues the specialized education in each of the three option areas, and provides an introduction to some of the professional practice topics that architectural engineers will need later in their careers.

The year of the AE program features a MAE design project. The project requires the student to practice all the design skills and understanding of building systems developed throughout the program. Students in teams will complete a significant building design in a manner that closely simulates professional practice. Industry and faculty members will serve as consultants to the students.

Architectural Engineering is accredited by the EAC-ABET, Inc. The accreditation is attached to the one-year master of architectural engineering degree.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Students must complete at least 42 credit hours in the AE program before applying for admission to the degree program in AE. Transfer students must have all transfer hours accepted before applying for admission. The number admitted will depend on the availability of space, faculty, and other academic resources. Admission will be based on academic performance in a set of 42 credit hours of courses taken in the AE program. Students will not be permitted to register for more than 61 credit hours of courses listed in the AE curriculum until they have been accepted into the degree program in AE.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Please visit our website for the latest information on the Architectural Engineering requirements for the bachelor of science program. http://engineering.unl.edu/durhamschool/academics/ArchitecturalEngineering.shtml

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Because of rapid technical developments, the AE curriculum will be continually reviewed and upgraded. Currently enrolled students are expected to modify their programs to take advantage of such revisions. Students who do not maintain continuous progress toward the degree through enrollment in applicable course work will be considered as new students upon re-entering the program and will be subject to the requirements of the undergraduate catalog current at the time of their re-entry.

AE students must pass any course offered by the AE program (those with an AE or CIVE prefix) with a grade of “C-” or higher to obtain credit toward graduation for that course. All courses that are prerequisites for AE or CE courses must be passed with a grade of “C-” or higher to obtain entry into the subsequent course.

The AE program follows the UNL ACE general education requirements. Because of the specific needs of the program, most of these courses are specified in the curriculum.

Please contact Christine Warren, student services coordinator, at cwarren2@unl.edu or 402-554-3918, if you are interested in more information about this program.

Architecture

COLLEGE: Architecture

MAJOR: Architecture

DEGREE OFFERED: The professional program in architecture consists of two components: the three-year Bachelor of Science in Design (BSD-Architecture) and the subsequent two-year Master of Architecture (MArch).

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 for BSD; 58 additional for the MArch

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Leslie Gonzalez & Stephanie Kuenning (pre-architecture); assigned faculty (architecture)

DESCRIPTION

Program Director: Jeffrey Day, 232 Architecture Hall

Professors: Day, Drummond (dean emeritus), Handa, Hoistad, Kuska, Laging, Scholz

Associate Professors: Ford, Hardy, Hemsath, Hind, Krug

Assistant Professors: Karle, Kelly, Olshavsky

Professors Emeritus: Borner, Corkill, Duncan, Ertl, Gibbs, Moore, Potter, Puderbaugh, Sawyers, Steward (dean emeritus)

Chief Advisers: Pre-Architecture: Leslie Brehm (lbrehm2@unl.edu) and Stephanie Kuenning (skuenning2@unl.edu); Architecture: Assigned faculty

The primary responsibility of the architectural profession is the design of meaningful, productive environments for human occupation and use. Architects, therefore, must be able to understand the needs and desires of the people who will inhabit and use their creations and then effectively synthesize the complex structural, mechanical, constructional components, and cultural references that go into the design of a building. As designers, they must possess creative and aesthetic skills as well as technical knowledge, collaborative ability, and problem-solving agility.

The architecture program seeks to increase students’ desire to learn and to develop a capacity for design-thinking and sound, critical judgment while simultaneously developing their creative potential. Specifically, the curriculum provides the background and means for the student to:

1. Analyze and understand society’s needs and desires,

2. Translate these needs and desires into a physical form and spatial organization,

3. Contribute creatively to the building construction industry,

4. Search out new problems and contribute to environmental knowledge through design-research,

5. Initiate and review developments in technology and society, and

6. Participate in the community that makes decisions affecting the physical environment.

Architecture is a six-year course of study divided into a pre-professional common first year (d.ONE) and a professional program of study. Students choosing to study architecture first enter the College as majors in pre-architecture. After completing a one year introductory design curriculum common to all undergraduates in the College of Architecture, students apply for admission into the architecture program’s professional program. The professional program in architecture consists of two components: the three-year bachelor of science in design (BSD-Architecture) and the subsequent two-year master of architecture (MArch).

Students in good standing at the completion of the BSD-Architecture are admitted to the MArch program without application.

In the United States, most state registration boards require a degree from an accredited professional degree program as a prerequisite for licensure. The National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB), which is the sole agency authorized to accredit U.S. professional degree programs in architecture, recognizes three types of degrees: the bachelor of architecture, the master of architecture and the doctor of architecture. A program may be granted a 6-year, 3-year, or 2-year term of accreditation, depending on the extent of its conformance with established educational standards.

Masters degree programs may consist of an undergraduate degree and a professional graduate degree, that, when earned sequentially, constitute an accredited professional education. However, the undergraduate degree is not, by itself, recognized as an accredited degree.

The bachelor of science in design is a para-professional degree and a necessary component of the professional program which culminates with the master of architecture degree. The master of architecture degree is the first professional degree. The professional master of architecture degree is fully accredited by the National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB).

In addition to the normal two-year professional program, applicants with degrees from other fields may be eligible to enter the three year master of architecture program with deficiencies. These deficiencies are evaluated by the program director on an individual basis after admission resulting from a review of the applicant’s transcripts and other pertinent professionally-related materials by the Student Affairs Committee. Students in this three year program are required to complete 27 to 50 hours of selected undergraduate courses (a minimum of one additional year) prior to pursuing the professional program. Applicants with deficiencies exceeding 50 credit hours are not admitted.

For those who would like to pursue scholarship and research in architecture, the architecture program also offers a 36 credit hour, scholarly-nonprofessional master of science in architecture degree for students with a bachelors degree in architecture or a related discipline.

The Master of Architecture Professional Program

General

The professional program in architecture is a six-year course of study that includes a one-year pre-professional segment, a three-year core segment culminating in the award of the bachelor of science in design (BSD) and culminates in the final two-year exploratory segment which results in the receipt of the professional master of architecture degree (MArch).

Although the bachelor of science in design degree is an integral part of the five-year professional program in architecture, it should be clearly understood that the undergraduate BSD is not a professional degree and is not accredited by the National Architectural Accrediting Board. Most state registration boards will not acknowledge any degree unless accompanied by an accredited professional degree.

The accredited, first professional degree awarded by the College of Architecture is the master of architecture degree which is awarded at the successful conclusion of the professional program in architecture. This is the only accredited professional architecture program in the state of Nebraska.

Upon successful completion of the one-year pre-architecture program, students who have been admitted to the second year may enroll in the curriculum that leads to the BSD degree and the MArch degree.

The professional program in architecture is structured to develop highly competent professional architects capable of performing effectively in an evolving discipline.

d.ONE: The Common First Year

The Common First Year (d.ONE) engages and prepares students for exciting futures in all design fields within the College of Architecture.

The Common First Year (d.ONE) curriculum offered by the College of Architecture, introduces students to design through courses in three areas: Technique (drawing and computer applications), Design Discipline (an introduction to the related design disciplines and design history), and Design Practice (design Thinking and design Making). In addition, students take University courses in math, English, communications, and a general education elective. Design Thinking and Design Making are sequential hands-on courses where students learn to work in teams to address problems and promote innovation. At the same time, they learn the foundational skills in composition, craft, presentation, and idea generation necessary for all design fields.

At the end of the Common First Year, students have gained an understanding of the broad range of design and are eligible to apply to any of the design programs in the College—Architecture, Landscape Architecture, Interior Design, and Industrial Design (pending program approval).

ADMISSION

Admission to the Architecture Program

After completion of the first year of pre-architecture studies, either within the College of Architecture or at another institution, students may apply for admission to the architecture program.

Pre-architecture students should apply for admission to the professional program in architecture. Successful applicants will have their major changed from pre-architecture to BSD-Architecture option.

Available teaching resources and space capacities limit enrollment to the second year of architectural studies; therefore enrollment limits are established each semester.

Required courses must be completed before advancing to the next year of study.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the architecture program, applicants must:

Be enrolled in the College of Architecture
Be in good scholastic standing
Have completed the one year pre-architecture program of study.

Second Year Admission Process

1. An application for admission may be completed by filling out the online application. The program receives applications once a year on March 1.

2. Applicants must submit a portfolio conforming to the defined criteria for the program applied for by the date posted at the completion of the spring semester.

3. Any applicant who has previously applied for admission and has not been accepted or who fails to enroll in the professional program in architecture after an acceptance must reapply in the regular manner. Students may apply for admission to the architecture program only three times.

Evaluation

The Student Affairs Committee of the program will carefully evaluate the applications for admission. The committee considers three elements in their evaluation; cumulative grade point average, a weighted grade point average, and the portfolio of student work. The weighted grade point average gives additional value to the applicant’s achievement in the required DSGN prefix course or transfer equivalents in the pre-professional curriculum.

Selection

Admission to the architecture program will be awarded to applicants who show the greatest professional potential and have demonstrated scholastic achievement. The Student Affairs Committee reserves the right to not fill all available spaces in the professional program in architecture if it determines that the remaining applicants have not performed at an acceptable level.

Admission to the 2-Year Master of Architecture Program

Students having completed the BSD-Architecture may continue their studies culminating in the MArch without re-application provided they exhibit a cumulative grade point average of B (3.0) and a studio GPA of B (3.0). Students must submit an intent form with a brief statement of purpose. A portfolio is not required. Students wishing to be eligible for fellowship and assistantships must submit the form by February 1.

Students from outside the program must apply to gain admission to the 2-year MArch degree program. Applications are available in October from the department office and are reviewed once a year in February. The Graduate Record Examination (GRE) is not required.

All applications for admission are subject to approval of the Student Affairs Committee. Enrollment shall be limited by the teaching resources and space capacities of the department. An enrollment quota is established prior to each admissions cycle.

Students in the professional program are governed by the rules, procedures and policies established in the architecture program. These are published in the Student Guide or by official notification by the faculty.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the 2-Year professional program in architecture, applicants must:

Have a 4-year degree from an accreditation-leading architecture program
Present a portfolio of design work
Be in good scholastic standing
Have a B average or its equivalent in past academic programs

The Student Affairs Committee of the architecture program requires a minimum TOEFL score of 550 or 213 computer-based or Internet-based score of 79-80 for all international student applicants whose first language is not English.

Evaluation

A portfolio of an applicant’s recent design work will be evaluated by the Student Affairs Committee of the architecture program and is considered to be a very important part of the application review process, along with the applicant’s educational profile, letters of recommendation, transcripts, and application form.

Selection

The limited number of spaces available each semester will be awarded to applicants who have displayed the highest abilities in a combination of scholastic achievement, design capability, and professional potential. Strong applicants with significant deficiencies may be admitted to the 3-year MArch program.

The Admissions Committee reserves the right to reject applicants who, in its opinion, have not reached an acceptable level of design proficiency.

Admission to the 3-Year Master of Architecture Program

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the 3-year MArch program, applicants must:

Have a four-year bachelor degree in any field
Have a B (3.0) cumulative grade point average in past academic programs

The Student Affairs Committee requires a minimum TOEFL score of 550 or 213 computer-based or Internet-based score of 79-80 for all international student applicants whose first language is not English.

Evaluation

The Student Affairs Committee evaluates the candidate’s past academic record, three letters of recommendation, a statement of educational goals and the information requested on the application form. A portfolio is not required for candidates applying for the three year masters degree program, however, providing evidence of past achievements and/or creative activity is helpful to the committee in its evaluation.

Selection

The limited number of spaces available each semester will be awarded to applicants who have displayed the highest abilities in a combination of scholastic achievement and professional potential.

Deficiencies

The Student Affairs Committee and/or the Program Chair reserve the right to require additional course work be done to correct perceived deficiencies in the candidates educational background. Examples of common deficiencies include college calculus, basic design, and computer applications. Courses fulfilling these requirements are available at the University of Nebraska and may be taken in the summer preceding the first year of the program.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Pre-Architecture Curriculum

The pre-architecture curriculum begins with d.ONE, a basic design first year common to all undergraduate majors in the College of Architecture. This common first year introduces students to the fundamentals of design thinking and design making. The pre-architecture program is followed by three years of architectural instruction leading to a bachelor of science in design. After receipt of the bachelors degree, students may declare intentions to continue for an additional two years of study, leading to a professional master of architecture degree. The professional master of architecture degree is accredited by the National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB).

The College of Architecture, and all six years of the architecture program, are located at UNL. However, we do offer the option to complete the first year of the program at UNO. After successfully completing the prescribed pre-architecture program at UNO, students may transfer to UNL and apply for admission to the second year of study in the Architecture Program.

For more information about courses at UNO, or transferring from UNO to UNL, please contact us.

PRE-ARCHITECTURE: Common First Year, First Semester

DSGN 101 Introduction to Design 2

DSGN 110 Design Thinking (ACE 7) 3

DSGN 120 Design Drawing 3

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 Composition Elective (ACE 1) 3

ACE 6 Elective 3

Total 14

PRE-ARCHITECTURE: Common First Year, Second Semester

DSGN 111 Design Making 4

DSGN 123 Computer Applications in Design 3

DSGN 140 History of Design (ACE 5) 3

MATH 104 Applied Calculus 3

Communication Elective: COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (ACE 2) 3

Total 16

ARCHITECTURE: Second Year, First Semester

ARCH 241 Architecture History & Theory II (ACE 7) 3

ARCH 210 Architectural Design Studio: Representation 5

ARCH 231 Structural Fundamentals 3

PHYS 151 Elements of Physics (ACE 4) 4

Total15

ARCHITECTURE: Second Year, Second Semester

ARCH 262 Building Organization 3

ARCH 211 Architectural Design Studio: Ideation 5

ARCH 232 Materials and Assemblies 3

ARCH 222 BIM for Design - Introduction to BIM 1

Technique 1

ACE 6, 8, or 9 3

Total16

ARCHITECTURE: Third Year, First Semester

ARCH 240 Architecture History & Theory I (ACE 5) 3

ARCH 310 Fundamentals of Achitectural Design (ACE 10) 5

ARCH 3XX Structural Mechanics 3

ACE 6, 8, or 9 3

Open Elective 3

Total17

ARCHITECTURE: Third Year, Second Semester

ARCH 360 Site Context Issues 3

ARCH 311 Architectural Design: Ecological Context (ACE 10) 5

ARCH 3XX Structural Optimization 3

Open Elective 3

Total14

ARCHITECTURE: Fourth Year, First Semester

ARCH 461 Urbanism (LARC 461) 3

ARCH 410 Architctural Design: Tectonics (ACE 10) 5

ARCH 333 Building Environmental Technical Systems I (CNST 305) 3

Open Elective 3

Total14

ARCHITECTURE: Fourth Year, Second Semester

ARCH 341 Architectural Theory 3

ARCH 411 Architectural Design: Urbanism Studio (ACE 10) 5

ARCH 430 Technological Integration 3

Open Elective 3

Total14

Total for Graduation120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, DSGN, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

GPA Requirements

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Second, Third and Fourth Year, Architecture

Students in the second year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average of 2.6. Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to meet two parallel academic standards. First the student must maintain a semester grade point average of 2.6 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation. Further, students whose GPA for the academic year is between 2.6 and 3.0 are required to submit their studio work for review by the Student Affairs Committee for determination of continuance in the program or repetition of the year’s studio sequence.

Fifth and Sixth Year, Architecture

Students in the MArch program are required to maintain a semester grade point average of 3.0 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Art History

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Art History

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Christy Aggens

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Peter Pinnell, 120 Richards Hall

Professors: Hoff, Mamiya, Stewart

Associate Professors: Bolland, Katz

Assistant Professor of Practice: Vigneault

A diverse and experienced faculty of art historians help art history scholars explore the history of the visual arts from ancient to modern art and the theoretical and critical literature associated with the cultures producing a given art style. Students attain proficiency in the practice of art and knowledge of the history of art in addition to general college education with about one-fourth of the course work in the Department of Art and Art History.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical & Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Library 110 1

Art History Major Requirements 33

Minor(s) 18-24

Electives 26-38

Total hours required for graduation 120

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Any student who meets college admission requirements may declare a major in art history.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Hours

AHIS 101 Introduction to Art History & Criticism I 3

AHIS 102 Introduction to Art History & Criticism II 3

AHIS 400 Art History Capstone Experience (offered spring semester only) 3

Art History electives (including a minimum of 12 credits of courses numbered above 299) 24

Minor Requirements

Students are required to complete one Plan A or two or more Plan B minors.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade.
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 15 credits in the major (including AHIS 400) must be in courses numbered 299 or above.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules

No more than 6 hours of independent study courses (AHIS 390, AHIS 392, AHIS 395, AHIS 490, AHIS 492, AHIS 495, AHIS 499H) may count toward the major in the BA degree.
At least 18 credit hours of the required art history courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A minor in art history—18 credits

AHIS 101 Introduction to Art History & Criticism I 3

AHIS 102 Introduction to Art History & Criticism II 3

Art History electives (including at least 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 12

Plan B minor in art history—12 credits

AHIS 101 Introduction to Art History & Criticism I 3

AHIS 102 Introduction to Art History & Criticism II 3

Art History electives 6

Up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass may be taken in the Plan A minor or each of two Plan B minors.

Athletic Training

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Athletic Training

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Vicki Fisher

DESCRIPTION

Athletic training is the art and science of treating athletic injuries. The Commission on Accreditation of Athletic Training Education (CAATE) develops and maintains guidelines for colleges and universities to provide an education for athletic training and verifies that those standards have been met. The University of Nebraska–Lincoln athletic training program is currently granted accreditation status by the CAATE. The underlying philosophy of this program is the same as with all other components of the University of Nebraska athletic medicine program.

The athletic training education program is dedicated to providing students with educational programming that is recognized as excellent. It is dedicated to providing students with opportunities to have clinical experiences with teams noted for excellence, in facilities noted for excellence. It is also expected that students will display excellence in academic and clinical settings, and will adhere to the highest standards as put forth in the National Athletic Trainers Association Code of Professional Ethics. The University of Nebraska athletic training education program is dedicated to the continual assessment of our program and our students in order to maintain our standards.

The athletic training education program is housed in the Department of Nutrition and Health Sciences. Completion of the entire program constitutes a major field of study. Students completing the course of study are eligible to sit for the National Athletic Trainers Association Board of Certification Examination.

Students are required to earn a B- or higher in ATHT 145 in order to continue in the program. All other ATHT courses must be a C+ or higher and must average at least 3.0 to remain in good standing in the program and graduate. The minimum grade requirements for other courses vary. Students are strongly encouraged to contact the advising center for a complete program description.

Admission to the athletic training education program is competitive. Included in athletic training education are six semesters of required clinical internship.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 32

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 330 or EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) (C or higher required) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Course) (C+ or higher required) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. 3

ACE 10. ATHT 445 (Professional Requirement) 3

Professional Requirements 45

ATHT 145, ATHT 146, ATHT 245, ATHT 246, ATHT 249, ATHT 446 (3 hrs ea) 18

ATHT 345 and ATHT 346 (4 hrs ea) 8

ATHT 247, ATHT 248, ATHT 347, ATHT 348, ATHT 447, ATHT 448 (1 hr ea) 6

NUTR 100, NUTR 250, NUTR 384, NUTR 484 (3 hrs ea) (C+ or higher required) 12

NUTR 150 1

Supporting Courses 27-31

MATH 102 or MATH 103 or MATH 106 (C or higher required) 2-5

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L (C or higher required) 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L (C or higher required) 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L (C+ or higher required) 4

BIOS 214 (C+ or higher required) 5

CHEM 110 4

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151 4-5

Electives 12-16

Total Hours 120

ADMISSION

Before a student is admitted to the athletic training education program, they must undergo a period of observation in the training rooms at the University of Nebraska. This period serves two purposes. First, it allows the student to make an informed decision about whether they wish to pursue athletic training as a career. Second, it allows the staff athletic trainers to observe the students work habits and social skills. The ability to work long and sometimes tedious hours and the ability to work well with people is absolutely necessary to be a successful athletic trainer.

Observation lasts for one year, and is tied to the completion of ATHT 145 and ATHT 146. During the first few weeks of the fall semester, the student will be assigned to a rotation between the various sports and training rooms at the University of Nebraska. The student will be asked to observe approximately five hours per week with the various athletic trainers at UNL. During these rotations, the student is expected to finish weekly assignments, which reflect the knowledge and abilities that are expected of an introductory student in athletic training. If a student does not complete the course of study or does not complete ATHT 145 and ATHT 146 with a grade of B- or better, they will be asked to repeat the observational period.

During the spring semester, the students interested in continuing the athletic training curriculum will apply to the director of athletic training for admittance to ATHT 247. Applications will be considered based on the following criteria:

Completion of ATHT 145 and ATHT 146 with a grade of B- or better.
A cumulative grade point average of 2.75 or better.
Evaluations provided by the staff athletic trainers supervising the students during their observational experiences.
Completion of an application provided by the director of athletic training education, along with an interview with the admissions committee.

There are a maximum number of students that may be admitted to the curriculum. Therefore, this application process is competitive. Candidates will be evaluated by the entire athletic training staff, and will be selected based on the work and academic criteria outlined above.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for pre-school and school age youth, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. In addition, the Department of Health and Human Services has created its own set of standards that apply to all individuals working in any capacity with pre-school children who are not yet in kindergarten. To comply with these two sets of standards, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Biochemistry (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Biochemistry (ASC)

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Britta Osborne

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Paul Black, N200 Beadle Center

Professors: Becker, Cahoon, DiRusso, Markwell, Spreitzer, Weeks, Wood

Associate Professors: Adamec, Bailey, Barycki, Lee, Simpson, Stone, Wilson

Assistant Professors: Basset, Buan, Fomenko, Hall, Harris, Khalimonchuk, Markham

Professor of Practice: Madhavan

Assistant Professor of Practice: Zhang

The Department of Biochemistry offers studies leading to either a bachelor of science (BS) or to a combined bachelors and masters degree (BS and MS) in biochemistry. The training offered is suitable for a professional career in biochemistry, which may lead to employment in various industries involved in the manufacture or processing of chemicals, foods, feeds, and pharmaceuticals; or federal agencies such as the Food and Drug Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Public Health Service, and Environmental Protection Agency. The program is also suitable as preparation for graduate studies leading to academic careers in biochemistry and professional careers in medicine, dentistry, veterinary medicine, pharmacy, and health-related fields.

The combined bachelors and masters degree in biochemistry is especially tailored for highly motivated undergraduate students with superior ability who seek additional training to further their career goals. This research thesis-based program is designed to provide opportunities to students to carry out and interpret contemporary research.

Graduate Work. Advanced degrees of master of science and doctor of philosophy are available through the Center for Biological Chemistry. For details, consult the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Laboratory Fee and Deposit. Students who enroll in laboratory courses in the Department of Biochemistry may be required to pay a small nonrefundable cash fee to defray the cost of materials consumed in the course and a deposit to cover the cost of replacing or repairing equipment the student may damage in the laboratory.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Biochemistry 12

BIOC 101 Career Opportunities in Biochemistry 1

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism 4

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication 2

BIOC 433 Biochemistry Lab 2

BIOC 435 Advanced Topics in Biochemistry (ACE 10) 3

Natural Sciences 45-49

LIFE 120 Fundamentals of Biology I 3

LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I Lab 1

BIOS 206 General Genetics or AGRO 315 Genetics 4

BIOS 312 Microbiology 3

BIOS 313 Molecular Microbiology Lab (2 cr) or BIOS 314 Microbiology Lab (1 cr) 1-2

CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 General Chemistry I & II & CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (12 cr) or CHEM 113 & CHEM 114 Fundamental Chemistry I & II & CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (11 cr) 11-12

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 or CHEM 261 & CHEM 263 Organic Chemistry I & Lab 4-5

CHEM 252 & CHEM 254 or CHEM 262 & CHEM 264 Organic Chemistry II & Lab 4-5

CHEM 471 or CHEM 481 Physical Chemistry 4

PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 Elementary General Physics I & II (10 cr) or PHYS 211 & PHYS 212 General Physics I & II & PHYS 221 & PHYS 222 General Physics Lab I & II (10 cr) 10

Mathematics and Statistics 9

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

Minimum Credit Hours for Graduation 120

Within the same subject matter area, students may request a more advanced course be substituted for a required course.

Advanced Placement and International Baccalaureate Credit. Students who earned AP or IB credit for general chemistry in high school are still required to complete a freshman-level chemistry sequence at an accredited post-secondary institution. These students are encouraged, but not required, to take CHEM 113/CHEM 114 rather than CHEM 109/CHEM 110. High school dual enrollment credit is not included in this policy.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, selected courses are assessed and majors are required to participate in an exit interview in their senior year. The interview will be conducted in the BIOC 435 course and results of participation in the interview will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass. Students in biochemistry may not take any of the courses required for the biochemistry degree program Pass/No Pass except for courses involving independent study, research, and seminars.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

A minimum of 18 credit hours of course work to include the following courses:

Hours

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism 4

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication 2

BIOS 206 General Genetics or AGRO 315 Genetics 4

BIOS 312 Microbiology 3

BIOS 313 Molecular Microbiology Lab (2 cr) or BIOS 314 Microbiology Lab (1 cr) 1-2

CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II or CHEM 262 Organic Chemistry 3

CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II

Lab (1 cr) or CHEM 264 Organic Chemistry Lab (2 cr) 1-2

Biochemistry (CASNR)

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Biochemistry (CASNR)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Biological Chemistry

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Britta Osborne

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Paul Black, N200 Beadle Center

Professors: Becker, Cahoon, DiRusso, Markwell, Spreitzer, Staswick, Weeks, Wood

Associate Professors: Adamec, Bailey, Barycki, Lee, Simpson, Stone, Wilson

Assistant Professors: Basset, Buan, Fomenko, Hall, Harris, Khalimonchuk, Markham

Professor of Practice: Madhavan

Assistant Professor of Practice: Zhang

Coordinator for Undergraduate Research: Madhavan

The Department of Biochemistry offers studies leading to a bachelor of science (BS) or a combined bachelors and masters degree (BS and MS) in biochemistry. The training offered is suitable for a professional career in biochemistry which may lead to employment in various industries involved in the manufacture or processing of chemicals, foods, feeds, and pharmaceuticals; or federal agencies such as the Food and Drug Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Public Health Service, and Environmental Protection Agency. The program is also suitable as preparation for graduate studies leading to academic careers in biochemistry and for professional careers in medicine, dentistry, veterinary medicine and health-related fields.

The combined bachelors and masters degree in biochemistry is especially tailored for highly motivated undergraduate students with superior ability who seek additional training to further their career goals. This research thesis-based program is designed to provide opportunities to students to carry out and interpret contemporary research.

Graduate Work. Advanced degrees of master of science and doctor of philosophy are available through the Center for Biological Chemistry. For details, consult the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Laboratory Fee and Deposit. Students who enroll in laboratory courses in the Department of Biochemistry may be required to pay a small nonrefundable cash fee to defray the cost of materials consumed in the course and a deposit to cover the cost of replacing or repairing equipment the student may damage in the laboratory.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Hours

Biochemistry Core 15

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

BIOC 101 Career Opportunities in Biochemistry 1

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism 4

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication 2

BIOC 433 Biochemistry Lab 2

BIOC 435 Advanced Topics in Biochemistry (ACE 10) 3

Natural Sciences 45-49

LIFE 120 Fundamentals of Biology I (ACE 4) 3

LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I Lab (ACE 4) 1

BIOS 206 General Genetics or AGRO 315 Genetics 4

BIOS 312 Microbiology 3

BIOS 313 Molecular Microbiology Lab (2 cr) or BIOS 314 Microbiology Lab (1 cr) 1-2

Select one sequence from: 11-12

CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 General Chemistry I & II (4 cr ea) & CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (4 cr) (12 cr)

CHEM 113 Fundamental Chemistry I (4 cr) & CHEM 114 Fundamental Chemistry II (3 cr) & CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (4 cr) (11 cr)

Select one sequence from: 4-5

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab (4 cr)

CHEM 261 & CHEM 263 Organic Chemistry & Lab (5 cr)

Select one sequence from: 4-5

CHEM 252 & CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II & Lab (4 cr)

CHEM 262 & CHEM 264 Organic Chemistry & Lab (5 cr)

CHEM 471 Physical Chemistry or CHEM 481 Physical Chemistry I 4

Select one sequence from: 10

PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 Elementary General Physics I & II (5 cr ea) (10 cr)

PHYS 211 & PHYS 212 General Physics I & II (4 cr ea) and PHYS 221 & PHYS 222 General Physics Lab I & II (1 cr ea) (10 cr)

Mathematics and Statistics 9

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (ACE 3) 5

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

Communications 6

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 120, JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Communication and Interpersonal Skills (ACE 2) 3

Select from: ALEC 102; COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 286; JGEN 300

Economics, Humanities, and Social Sciences 15

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Free Electives 26-30

Minimum Credit Hours for Graduation 120

Within the same subject matter area, students may request a more advanced course be substituted for a required course.

Advanced Placement and International Baccalaureate Credit. Students who earned AP or IB credit for general chemistry in high school are still required to complete a freshman-level chemistry sequence at an accredited post-secondary institution. These students are encouraged, but not required, to take CHEM 113/CHEM 114 rather than CHEM 109/CHEM 110. High school dual enrollment credit is not included in this policy.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass. Students in biochemistry may not take any of the courses required for the biochemistry degree program Pass/No Pass except for courses involving independent study, research, and seminars.

Minimum Grade Requirement. No transfer or UNL C- and D grades can be applied toward requirements in the biochemistry major or a minor.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

A minimum of 18 credit hours of course work to include the following courses:

Hours

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism 4

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication 2

BIOS 206 General Genetics or AGRO 315 Genetics 4

BIOS 312 Microbiology 3

BIOS 313 Molecular Microbiology Lab (2 cr) or BIOS 314 Microbiology Lab (1 cr) 1-2

CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II or CHEM 262 Organic Chemistry 3

CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II Lab (1 cr) or CHEM 264 Organic Chemistry Lab (2 cr) 1-2

Biological Sciences

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Biological Sciences

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Wendy O'Connor and Erin Sayer

DESCRIPTION

Director: Valery E. Forbes, 348 Manter Hall

Vice Director: John C. Osterman, 348 Manter Hall

Professors: Avramova, Basolo, Blum, Cerutti, Christensen, Forbes, Fritz, Gardner, Gibson, Harshman, Kamil, Knops, Mackenzie, Morris, Nickerson, Wagner, Wood, Zera, L. Zhang

Associate Professors: P. Angeletti, Atkin, Bachman, Brassil, Chia, Elthon, Hebets, Li, Montooth, E. Moriyama, H. Moriyama, Osterman, Pilson, Storz, Tenhumberg

Assistant Professors: Brown, Couch, DeLong, Meiklejohn, Riekhof, Russo, Smith, Weber, Yu, C. Zhang

Professor of Practice: Glider, Woodman

Lecturers: A. Angeletti, Herman

The School of Biological Sciences offers educational opportunities in various areas of biology leading toward either the Bachelor of Science or the Bachelor of Arts degree. Study in the biological sciences prepares students for a variety of careers requiring knowledge of biological processes, such as teaching; environmental resource management and assessment; production and sales of biological materials; research in governmental, industrial, and academic laboratories; as well as preparation for careers in medicine, dentistry, and health-related professions.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of Master of Science, and Doctor of Philosophy are offered. For details, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab
LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab
BIOS 205 Genetics, Molecular & Cellular Biology Lab
BIOS 206 General Genetics
BIOS 207 Ecology & Evolution

Specific Major Requirements

An additional 18 hours of elective courses in biological sciences.

At least 10 hours must be at the 300 level or above, with at least 3 hours at the 400 level. Students concerned about their preparation for college-level biology should consult their adviser.

Additionally, biological sciences majors are strongly urged to attend the Cedar Point Biological Station for at least one summer session. Majors are also encouraged to do a research project with a faculty member.

No more than 8 hours may be from courses whose home department is other than biological sciences.

The following courses will NOT count toward the biological sciences major: BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L, BIOS 150, BIOS 160, BIOS 203, BIOS 220, BIOS 222, BIOS 232 or BIOS 280. BIOS 395 Internship is offered Pass/No Pass only and therefore may not be used in the major.

No minor is required, but biological sciences majors must complete the following ancillary courses in addition to the 36 hours in the major:

Biochemistry: BIOC 321 or BIOC 431
Chemistry: CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 or CHEM 113 & CHEM 114
Organic Chemistry: CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 or CHEM 255 & CHEM 257 or CHEM 261 & CHEM 263
Mathematics: MATH 106 and one of the following: MATH 107 or CSCE 155T or an approved statistics course (choose from STAT 218, EDPS 459, PSYC 350, ECON 215, STAT 380)
Physics: PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 or PHYS 211 & PHYS 212

Program Assessment. To assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its program, after significantly completing the course work, all majors will be required in their senior year to register for BIOS 99 and complete selected assessment activities.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a students GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

No biological science course, except BIOS 310, used to fulfill the 36 hours for the major (and 18 hours for the minor) may be taken Pass/No Pass.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours, comprised of the five-course core: LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L, BIOS 205, BIOS 206, and BIOS 207

Broadcasting

COLLEGE: Journalism & Mass Communications

MAJOR: Broadcasting

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Journalism

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes-only for meteorology majors and environmental studies majors with a meteorology emphasis

CHIEF ADVISER: Michael Goff

DESCRIPTION

Professors: Hull (emeritus), Lee, Mayeux (emeritus), Renaud, Walklin

Associate Professors: Alloway, Creighton, McCoy, Spann (emeritus)

Professor of Practice: Christensen

Assistant Professor of Practice: Peon-Casanova

The broadcasting major offers courses leading to a wide variety of careers in the broadcasting and telecommunications industry. Building on a solid base of instruction in radio, television, mobile and online journalism, the major has broadened its curriculum in response to advancing technology and new electronic media. Broadcasting offers courses in news gathering and dissemination, sports reporting, videography, sales, management, programming and other specializations including the use of audio and video on the Internet and the World Wide Web. Courses are designed to develop both a comprehensive understanding of theoretical principles and professional skills. Most courses involve extensive practical laboratory work in addition to classroom lectures and discussions.

Many of the broadcasting faculty members have extensive industry experience at media organizations such as ABC News, WBNS-TV (CBS) in Columbus, Ohio, KMTV, Omaha, Nebraska and Nebraska Educational Television. The faculty continues to be connected to the industry, and its members are actively involved in professional media organizations. Students, likewise, are encouraged to further their professional goals through participation in student organizations such as the Alpha Epsilon Rho national broadcasting society, the Society of Professional Journalists, Northwest Broadcast News Association, Radio, Television News Directors Association, the Radio Television Digital News Association and the American Copy Editors Association.

KRNU and KRNU2, are professionally managed radio stations, and an integral part of the instructional program. With studios in Andersen Hall, KRNU operates year-round and serves an audience of potentially 250,000 persons in the Lincoln area, plus a global audience via the Internet. KRNU2 operates on the Internet only. Student-produced programs aired on these stations have won many awards in competition with other student groups as well as with commercial stations. Students are successful in the Broadcast Education Association national student competition, Society of Professional Journalists and the Northwest Broadcast News Association

Students have also had success in the national Hearst competition, including the national winner in the 2013 feature category in television news, second place television news overall in 2012, third place radio news overall and the broadcast television news national winner in 2006. In addition, several students have placed in the top five in both radio and television.

And broadcasting students have achieved success in producing documentary films. Broadcasting students received a Bronze Oscar in the student documentary category for their 2003 production of “Cuba: An Illogical Temple.” Students also finished in the top seven in the student academy awards for a documentary comparing the Tsunami in Sri Lanka to hurricane Katrina in New Orleans. A third documentary, "Breaking Down Barriers," compared the challenges facing Turkish immigrants living in Germany with Hispanic immigrants living in the U.S. It won the prestigious Robert F. Kennedy award for human rights in 2008.

In addition, students may work and take classes in the studios of the Nebraska Educational Television Network, one of the premier ETV facilities in the nation.

Students also produce Star City News, a bi-weekly television news broadcast, and Fast Forward, a bi-weekly entertainment program, which are distributed throughout Lincoln via cable television.

Broadcasting faculty assist students in acquiring internships and professional work experience prior to graduation. Last year more than 100 media-related internships and professional part-time jobs were held by broadcasting majors including internships at CNN in New York working with Anderson Cooper, at ESPN and VH1. Graduates are working for major media organizations throughout the nation.

Students wishing to major in broadcasting should contact the college office in 147 Andersen Hall.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The broadcasting major is 39 hours with 18-21 of the hours selected to develop emphasis in either news or production.

Those completing either a news emphasis or a production emphasis take all of the following: JOMC 101, JOMC 160, JOMC 486, and JOMC 487.

Those who choose a news emphasis additionally complete JOUR 202, JOUR 304; BRDC 369, BRDC 370, BRDC 472 and 9 hours of electives chosen from advertising and public relations, broadcasting or journalism.

Those who pursue a production emphasis additionally complete JOMC 161, BRDC 227, BRDC 228, BRDC 359, BRDC 360, BRDC 462 and 6 hours of electives selected from advertising and public relations, broadcasting or journalism.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major; however, the second major in the college will not take the place of a concentration or any of the 72 hours required outside the college.

Graduating seniors also must complete JOMC 98, Senior Assessment. Typically, JOMC 98 is taken in the last semester; however, seniors who have completed all courses for the major may take it two semesters preceding graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Internship Policy

Students may be able to earn credit for internships under certain circumstances. Please go to the college website and find the Internship Policy under the Student Services tab.

Credit in Special Experiences

Students may earn up to six credit hours toward the degree in some courses: Jacht, National Student Advertising Competition, photojournalism reports, depth reports and others. Students may repeat the same course again for additional credit hours, but those credits will not count toward the degree inside or outside the major. Talk with an academic adviser for further information or specific questions.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

A broadcasting minor (18 hours) is available only for meteorology majors and environmental studies majors with a meteorology emphasis. These students complete both JOMC 162 and JOMC 163 or only JOMC 160 and all of the following: JOUR 202, BRDC 369, BRDC 370 and BRDC 472.

Business Administration

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Business Administration

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (24 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes-for non business students only

CHIEF ADVISER: D'vee Buss

DESCRIPTION

The business administration major is designed for students who wish to obtain a broad education in business administration rather than specializing in a specific area within the College. For the student who has an educational goal that bridges two or more areas of business, the general business administration major permits the design of a tailor-made program to fit that goal.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 24 hours of course work for the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

No departmental 399/499 courses may count toward the business administration major.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in business administration are to complete 24 hours of 300/400-level business course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M) to be selected from course work offered by:

Accounting
Economics
Finance
Management or Supply Chain
Marketing

As part of the 24 hour requirement:

Course work must be from the 300/400-level with the course work selected from the following approved list.
A MINIMUM of 3 hours from each of five departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 6 hours from each of three departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 9 hours must be taken at the 400 level.
Departmental 499s (unless an honors thesis) may NOT be used toward the major.

Course work for the major must be selected from the following courses.

Accounting:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II

Any 400-level accounting course work

Economics:

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics

ECON 321 Intro to International Economics

Any 400-level economics course work

Finance:

FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

FINA 365/ECON 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

Any 400-level finance or actuarial science course work

Management:

MNGT 321/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations

MNGT 361 Human Resource Management

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communication, & Teams

SCMS 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models

Any 400-level management or supply chain management course work

Marketing:

MRKT 346/SCMS 346 Marketing Channels Management

MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy

MRKT 345 Market Research

MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems

MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics

Any 400-level marketing course work

Additional Restrictions:

Students who earn BSAD 491 (6 hrs) from the Senshu (Japan) study abroad program may substitute 6 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in two of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA China study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA CIMBA (Italy) study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in any upper-level course work offered by the departments requires completion of appropriate prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

General Business Minor—Plan A Only

The minor consists of the following 18 hours:

ACCT 200 Accounting for Business Decisions (3 hrs)

ECON 200 Economic Essentials & Issues (3 hrs)

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society (3 hrs)

FINA 300 Financial Decision Making (3 hrs)

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations (3 hrs)

MRKT 300 Contemporary Marketing (3 hrs)

Please note the following information.

This minor is available to all other colleges at UNL.
Only nonbusiness students can complete this minor.
Courses in the minor can’t be used towards a degree in business
Prerequisites are enforced.
No more than one course may be transferred into the minor. The number of courses is calculated on the course replaced. If ACCT 201 and ACCT 202 are used to replace ACCT 200, it is one course
Students with previous credit in business should see their college adviser for further information.
Credit cannot be earned in both: ACCT 201 or 202 and ACCT 200; BLAW 371 or 372 and BLAW 300; ECON 211 or 212 and ECON 200; FINA 361 and FINA 300; MRKT 341 and MRKT 300.

OTHER

All students enrolling in CBA courses are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include junior standing, as well as expected completion of the BCF and BCI for enrollment in most 300 or 400-level business courses. This includes the required course work in information systems, communications, mathematics and statistics, accounting, and economics as well as marketing, finance, production, MIS, human resources, and business law prior to enrolling in course work for their major.

Business Administration majors are not eligible to add an International Business minor.

Chemical Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Chemical Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Chemical Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 131-132

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER:

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Hendrik Viljoen

Professors: Cornelius, Larsen, Noureddini, Saraf, Subramanian, Timm, Velander, Viljoen

Associate Professors: Demirel, Van Cott

Assistant Professor: Kidambi

Lecturer: Flodman

The mission of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln chemical and biomolecular engineering program is to provide qualified students with a foundation in engineering sciences and engineering design methods to prepare them for successful professional careers and to contribute to the needs of society.

In pursuit of the program’s mission, the Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering has established the Educational Objectives given below:

The graduate of the University of Nebraska Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering:

Performs as a chemical engineer.

Contributes with satisfying progress toward the level at which he or she chooses to engage in professional practice in industry, academics, allied or alternate fields.

Pursues a career as a practicing engineer in diverse fields such as chemical process industries, biochemical technology, pharmaceuticals, petroleum, energy, polymers/advanced materials, food processing, medicine/medical research, environment or safety; pursues an academic career to teach, research and serve the community.

Applies engineering and scientific principles.

Uses engineering and economic analyses, modern engineering tools and techniques with existing practical constraints and limitations to create solutions that are economical and sustainable.

Interacts successfully with a wide range of people.

Exercises care and responsibility in broad and diverse interpersonal interactions by effectively listening, speaking, writing and presenting.

Incorporates safety, ethics, and environmental protection in all engineering practices.

Understands the importance of safety, health, and environmental protection in all engineering practices. Upholds the American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE) Code of Ethics and advises colleagues and the public on consequences presenting adverse effects on health, safety and the environment.

Accepts responsibility for life-long learning.

Continues professional growth and development throughout his or her career by participating in professional societies such as AIChE, industrial training, continuing education and professional development courses.

The Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering offers a course of study designed for students who plan careers in a wide variety of industries, ranging from the chemical and process industries to biotechnology, electronics, and the environment. Students receive training in the basic subjects of mathematics, English, and physics in common with other students in engineering, but in addition receive extensive training in chemistry. In various courses the emphasis is placed on the fundamental principles of fluid mechanics, heat transfer, mass transfer, separation processes, thermodynamics, kinetics, and process dynamics, as well as process economics and design of chemical processes.

The instructional laboratories provide opportunities for students to operate experimental equipment, to test the theories and correlations developed in the classroom, and to design their own experimental equipment for the solution of special problems.

Graduates are qualified to undertake work in research, design, development, production, maintenance, and technical sales in a wide variety of industries including chemicals, petroleum, petrochemicals, rubber, plastics, agricultural chemicals, food, biotechnology, pharmaceuticals, paper, fabrics, aircraft, automotive, electronics, energy conversion, and environmental pollution prevention and control.

The Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering is located in Othmer Hall. A state-of-the-art unit operations laboratory, used to give hands-on chemical process experience, is located there. Laboratory equipment is provided for the study of fluid mechanics, heat transfer, mass transfer, staged operations, process control, thermodynamics, reaction kinetics, and polymerization. The department operates its own microcomputer facility. Additional research equipment is available for independent and graduate study in several areas.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Any student in the chemical and biomolecular engineering program whose grade point average in required chemical and biomolecular engineering courses is less than 2.4 will be admitted to the required courses of the following year only with the special permission of the department.

First Semester

CHEM 113 Fundamental Chemistry I* 4

CHME 113 Introduction to Chemical Engineering I 2

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

ACE Electives 1 6

Total 17

Second Semester

CHEM 114 Fundamental Chemistry II* 3

CHME 114 Introduction to Chemical Engineering II 2

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering & Science Focus 3

MATH 107 Calculus II 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

Total 16

* The sequence CHEM 109, CHEM 110 is an acceptable alternative to CHEM 113, CHEM 114.

Third Semester

CHEM 261 Organic Chemistry 3

CHEM 263A Organic Chemistry Lab 1

CHME 202 Mass & Energy Balances 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 208 Calculus III 4

MECH 223 Engineering Statics 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 18

Fourth Semester

CHEM 262 Organic Chemistry 3

CHEM 264A Organic Chemistry Lab 1

CHME 223 Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics I 3

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering I 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

Total 16

Fifth Semester

CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis 4

CHME 323 Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics II 3

CHME 331 Equilibrium Stage Operations 3

CHME 332 Transport Operations I 3

ACE Elective 1 3

Total 16

Sixth Semester

Advanced Chemistry 3-4

Select from: CHEM 421, CHEM 431, CHEM 441, CHEM 471, or CHEM 481

CHME 312 Chemical Engineering Computation 3

CHME 330 Chemical Engineering Lab I 3

CHME 333 Transport Operations II 3

Oral Communication Elective 3

Choose from ALEC 102, JGEN 300, or COMM 286 (SLO 2).

Total 15-16

Seventh Semester

CHME 442 Chemical Reactor Engineering & Design 3

CHME 452 Chemical Engineering Processing Economics & Optimization 3

CHME 462 Automatic Process Control 3

Technical Electives 2 6

ACE Elective 1 3

Total 18

Eighth Semester

CHME 430 Chemical Engineering Lab II 4

CHME 453 Chemical Engineering Process Design 3

CHME 460 Automatic Process Control Lab 1

ENGR 400 Professional Ethics & Social Responsibility 1

Technical Elective 2 3

ACE Elective 1 3

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required 131-132

1 Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

2 The 9 hours of technical electives must include at least 3 credit hours of engineering science. All must be approved by the adviser.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Special emphasis options available in the Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering include:

biotechnology/bioengineering
environmental engineering
materials engineering
mathematics and statistics

Technical Electives

The purpose of technical electives is to provide the student with an opportunity to gain new knowledge in an area of engineering or science beyond the basic undergraduate chemical engineering program. The technical electives may be in engineering design, engineering science, physical science, life science, and/or math.

A minimum of 9 credit hours of technical electives are required. This must include at least 3 credit hours of engineering science.
All technical electives must be approved by a departmental academic adviser prior to registration for the course.
Students are expected to complete their technical elective requirements during their junior and senior years with corresponding level of courses.
With the pre-approval of the student’s academic adviser, a maximum of 3 credit hours of CHME 499 Senior Problems or CHME 499H Honors Thesis may be applied toward the technical electives requirement.
Introductory 100-level courses are not accepted as technical electives.
Advanced Placement (AP) high school classes are not allowed as technical electives.
Courses lacking a quantitative physical science foundation such as accounting, marketing, economics, or law are normally not acceptable as technical electives.
Students are strongly encouraged to select their technical electives from the following list. Course(s) may be taken outside of this list with approval of a departmental academic adviser prior to registration for the course.

Biotechnology/Bioengineering/Chemistry

CHEM 431/831 Biomolecules & Metabolism (BIOC 431, BIOS 431/831) (4 cr)

CHEM 432/832 Gene Expression & Replication (BIOC 432, BIOS 432/832) (2 cr)

CHEM 441 Inorganic Chemistry (3 cr)

CHEM 471 Physical Chemistry (4 cr)

CHEM 481 Physical Chemistry I (4 cr)

CHEM 482 Physical Chemistry II (4 cr)

CHEM 486/886 Advanced Topics in Biophysical Chemistry (BIOC 486, BIOS 486/886) (3 cr)

CHME 473/873 Biochemical Engineering (3 cr)

CHME 474/874 Advanced Biochemical Engineering (2-6 cr)

BIOS 312 Microbiology (3 cr)

BIOS 206 General Genetics (4 cr)

Environmental Engineering

BSEN 455/855 or CIVE 455/855 Nonpoint Source Pollution Control Engineering (3 cr)

CHME 489 Air Pollution, Assessment & Control (3 cr) (See CHME 492 for course description.)

CIVE 326 Introduction to Environmental Engineering (BSEN 326) (3 cr)

CIVE 327 Environmental Engineering Lab (BSEN 327) (1 cr)

CIVE 421/821 Hazardous Waste Management & Treatment (3 cr)

CIVE 422/822 Pollution Prevention: Principles & Practices (BSEN 422/822) (3 cr)

CIVE 424/824 Solid Waste Management Engineering (3 cr)

CHEM 421/821 Analytical Chemistry (3 cr)

CHEM 423/823 Analytical Chemistry Lab (2 cr)

ENVR 489 Environmental Studies Seminar (1 cr)

Materials Engineering

CHME 482/882 Polymers (3 cr)

MATL 360 Elements of Materials Science [ES] (4 cr)

MATL 460 Mechanical Aspects of Materials (3 cr)

MATL 462/862 X-Ray Diffraction (3 cr)

MATL 469/869 Physical Materials Systems (3 cr)

MATL 471/871 Electron Microscopy of Materials (3 cr)

MATL 473/873 Corrosion (3 cr)

MECH 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies (3 cr)

MECH 381 Elements of Computer-aided Design (3 cr)

PHYS 422/822 Introduction to Physics & Chemistry of Solids (ELEC 422/822) (3 cr)

Mathematics and Statistics

MATH 314/814 Linear Algebra (Matrix Theory) (3 cr)

MATH 322/822 Advanced Calculus (3 cr)

MATH 324/824 Introduction to Partial Differential Equations (3 cr)

STAT 380 Statistics & Applications (MATH 380) (3 cr)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

GPA Requirements

Any student in the chemical and biomolecular engineering program whose grade point average in required chemical and biomolecular engineering courses is less than 2.4 will need special permission of the department to be admitted to the required CHME courses the following year.

OTHER

University Honors Program

For those students who have been admitted to the University Honors Program, junior- and senior-level chemical and biomolecular engineering classes are available as honors-designated classes (i.e., CHME xxxH) on a “contract basis” between the student and the instructor with approval by the department faculty. The requirement of an honors thesis research project is fulfilled by completion of a minimum of 3 credits of CHME 499H (Honors Thesis) under the direction of a department faculty member. Additional information on the University Honors Program, including admission requirements, can be found in the Honors Program section.

Chemistry

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Chemistry

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Craig Eckhardt

DESCRIPTION

Chair: David Berkowitz, 551 Hamilton Hall

Vice Chair: Marjorie Langell

Professors: Berkowitz, DiMagno, Du, Dussault, Eckhardt, Hage, Harbison, Langell, Parkhurst, Powers, Rajca, Redepenning, Takacs, Zeng

Associate Professors: Cheung, Griep, Lai, Li

Assistant Professors: Dodds, Guo, Morin, Sinitskii, C. Stains, M. Stains, Zhang

Professors of Practice: Kautz, Malina

Chemistry deals with the analysis, structure, properties, and synthesis of matter ranging in size from single atoms to biologically-active small molecules to DNA and proteins. A degree in chemistry prepares students for many career options: industry (research, analysis, production), teaching, graduate studies, or professional schools. Chemistry is also a valuable second major for students completing degrees in a number of science, math, or engineering disciplines. The bachelor of science (BS) is recommended for students planning graduate studies or professional careers in chemistry and is also an excellent choice for pre-medicine. The bachelor of arts (BA) program is designed for students needing undergraduate training in chemistry as preparation for professional careers outside of chemistry and fits easily into pre-medical, pre-pharmacy, pre-health, and pre-law degree programs. A degree with a chemistry emphasis is available to students enrolled in the Environmental Studies program (consult that entry for details). The chemistry department hosts a Web page with other information (scholarships, etc.) relating to the undergraduate programs at http://chem.unl.edu/undergrad/.

Laboratory Fee and Deposit. Students who enroll in chemistry laboratory courses pay a special fee to defray the cost of materials and equipment. The special fee is applied to tuition in the amounts given in the Schedule of Classes.

Breakage Costs. Glassware and equipment that are lost or damaged by the student are charged to the students N-card.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of science and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details, consult the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Bachelor of Science in Chemistry Required Program of Study

Chemistry (46-49 cr); Math (13 cr); and Physics (8-12 cr)

CHEM 101 Career Opportunities in Chemistry

CHEM 113, CHEM 114, CHEM 221 (Fundamental Chemistry & Quantities Analysis)

ACE Student Learning Outcome 4 is met by any one of the following: CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, or CHEM 113

CHEM 261, CHEM 262, CHEM 263 (2 cr), CHEM 264 (2 cr) (Organic Chemistry)

CHEM 431, CHEM 433 (Biochemistry)

CHEM 481, CHEM 482, CHEM 484 (Physical Chemistry)

CHEM 399 (at least 2 cr) (Undergraduate Research)

And

Either CHEM 421 & CHEM 423 (Analytical Chemistry) or CHEM 441 & CHEM 443 (Inorganic Chemistry) or both.

ACE Student Learning Outcome 10 is met by both combinations of CHEM 421 & CHEM 423 and CHEM 441 & CHEM 443

MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208

PHYS 211, PHYS 212 (with recommendations of PHYS 213 & PHYS 222)

Bachelor of Arts in Chemistry Required Program of Study

Chemistry (35-36 cr); Math (9-10 cr); and Physics (8-10 cr)

CHEM 101 Career Opportunities in Chemistry

CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 221 (General Chemistry & Quantitative Analysis)

ACE Student Learning Outcome 4 is met by any one of the following: CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, or CHEM 113

CHEM 251, CHEM 252, CHEM 253, CHEM 254 (Organic Chemistry)

CHEM 471 (or CHEM 481) (Physical Chemistry)

And

At least two of the following combinations:

CHEM 421 & CHEM 423 (Analytical); CHEM 431 & CHEM 433 (Biological); CHEM 441 & CHEM 443 (Inorganic)

ACE Student Learning Outcome 10 is met by both combinations of CHEM 421 & CHEM 423 and CHEM 441 & CHEM 443

MATH 106, MATH 107 (or MATH 238)

PHYS 141 and PHYS 142

NOTE: It is possible to transfer between the BS and BA programs despite the different sets of courses, but the student should visit the chemistry adviser to work out the details.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required in their senior year:

1. To take a standardized chemistry exam during their final year in the program. It will be administered during the middle of the spring semester at a time that is mutually agreeable to all graduating seniors.

2. To participate in an exit interview with a designated faculty member.

3. To submit a copy of the report written for CHEM 399 to the departmental office for evaluation.

The Vice-Chair will inform students of the scheduling and format of assessment activities.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a students GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students majoring in chemistry may not take chemistry courses Pass/No Pass except for CHEM 396 and/or CHEM 399. Chemistry majors may take up to 6 hours in minor courses Pass/No Pass subject to approval of the department granting the minor.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The Plan A chemistry minor is for students with only one minor. The program of study is: completion of a freshman chemistry sequence (CHEM 109, CHEM 110, and CHEM 221 or CHEM 113, CHEM 114, and CHEM 221) plus an additional 12 hours of chemistry excluding CHEM 131, CHEM 195, CHEM 396, and CHEM 399.

The Plan B chemistry minor is for students with two or more minors. The program of study is: completion of a freshman chemistry sequence (CHEM 109, CHEM 110, and CHEM 221 or CHEM 113, CHEM 114, and CHEM 221) plus an additional 8 hours of chemistry excluding CHEM 131, CHEM 195, CHEM 396, and CHEM 399.

Child Development/Early Childhood Education

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Child Development/Early Childhood Education

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Val Wiemeyer

DESCRIPTION

These students are prepared to work effectively with children in a variety of settings such as childcare programs, nonprofit organizations, and family childcare.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the teacher education curriculum and must be successfully completed. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Criminal History Background Check Requirement” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements (or majors) are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30-34

ACE 1. ENGL 101, ENGL 150,ENGL 151, ENGL 254 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 2. ALEC 102, COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, or COMM 286 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 3. ECON 215, EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 203, MATH 208; or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 4. ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 113; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; GEOG 155; GEOL 101, GEOL 103; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; METR 100; NRES 108; PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 151 & PHYS 153, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262; or TMFD 206 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (CYAF Professional Core) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. CYAF 495 (CYAF Professional Core) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 497A (Education Core) 3

Supporting Courses 1

LIBR 110 1

CYAF Core Requirements 15

CYAF 222, CYAF 333, CYAF 380, CYAF 382, CYAF 488 (3 hrs ea) 15

Education Core Requirements 39-40

CYAF 210, CYAF 271, CYAF 374, CYAF 474 (3 hrs ea) 12

CYAF 270 2

CYAF 210L, CYAF 270L, CYAF 271L, CYAF 374L, (1 hr ea) 4

CYAF 497A (3 hrs are met in ACE 10) 9

NUTR 100 3

Select one course: 3

EDPS 462, SLPA 150, SPED 201, SPED 303, SPED 480 or PSYC 380

Select two courses: 6-7

CYAF 371 & CYAF 371L or CYAF 383 or CYAF 384

Concentration Area (Choose one concentration) 12

Program Management (12 hrs)

CYAF 477 (3 hrs)

Select one course: EDAD 421, ALEC 202, or ALEC 302 (3 hrs)

Select two courses: ACCT 202, ECON 210, MNGT 121, MNGT 320, MNGT 321, or ENTR 291 (6 hrs)

Nature Education (12 hrs)

CYAF 384 (3 hrs)

Select three courses: ANTH 473, CYAF 493, BIOS 232, ENTO 115 & ENTO 116, ENTO 109, HORT 200, LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, NRES 220 & NRES 222, SOCI 446, or ENVR 201 (9 hrs)

Infants and Toddlers (13 hrs)

CYAF 371 (3 hrs)

CYAF 371L (1 hr)

CYAF 497I (6 hrs)

SPED 463 (3 hrs)

Pre-Graduate School/Research (12 hrs)

CYAF 498 (3-6 hrs) (Suggested: UCARE proposal)

Select two courses: EDPS 459, EDPS 470, PSYC 350, PSYC 450, SOCI 205, SOCI 206, SOCI 407 (6 hrs) (Research Methods)

Select one course from: PSYC 270, PSYC 470, Nature Education electives (see above) (3 hrs)

Suggested: UCARE proposal

Electives 18-23

Total Hours 120

NOTE: Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses. All CYAF courses must be taken for a grade (not Pass/No Pass).

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for pre-school or school aged youth, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. In addition, the Department of Health and Human Services has created its own set of standards that apply to all individuals working in any capacity with pre-school children who are not yet in kindergarten. To comply with these two sets of standards, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. This must be completed before one’s first field experience. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process, culminating experience, or internship. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed. Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student’s future in the College and one’s ability to find success in the profession of education. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after either background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one’s criminal history can lead to removal from the program. A student’s ability to continue to participate in any teacher education program in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and/or the Nebraska Department of Education standards as they apply to working with pre-school and school age youth.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action including possible removal from the program. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Child, Youth & Family Studies Minor

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Child, Youth & Family Studies Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER:

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Child, Youth and Family Studies Minor (18 hrs)

CYAF 160 (3 hrs)
CYAF 280 (3 hrs)
Four courses in the Department, two of which must be at the 300 level or above.

Grade Rules

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses.

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for pre-school or school aged youth, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. In addition, the Department of Health and Human Services has created its own set of standards that apply to all individuals working in any capacity with pre-school children who are not yet in kindergarten. To comply with these two sets of standards, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. This must be completed before one’s first field experience. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process, culminating experience, or internship. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed. Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student’s future in the College and one’s ability to find success in the profession of education. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after either background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one’s criminal history can lead to removal from the program. A student’s ability to continue to participate in any teacher education program in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and/or the Nebraska Department of Education standards as they apply to working with pre-school and school age youth.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action including possible removal from the program. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Civil Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Civil Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 130

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE:

CHIEF ADVISER: Karen Schurr

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Daniel Linzell

Professors: Dahab, Dvorak, Linzell, Rilett, Tuan, Zhang

Associate Professors: Admiraal, Bartelt-Hunt, Guo, Jones, Khattak, Kim, Krause, Moussavi, Rohde, Stansbury, Szerszen

Assistant Professors: Kilic, X. Li, Y. Li, Sharma, Steelman, Wood

The Department of Civil Engineering offers a complete undergraduate program to students on the Lincoln and Omaha campuses of the University of Nebraska. Curriculum requirements are nearly identical on both campuses. The goal is to prepare students for entry into the civil engineering profession immediately after graduation or to pursue graduate-level work.

The general educational objectives of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln civil engineering undergraduate program are to prepare our graduates to:

APPLY their solid foundation in civil engineering toward the practice, advanced-degree education and a broad range of career choices;
PERFORM technical analysis or design of a complex system, component or process as acting representatives of governmental agencies, private consulting engineering firms, research organizations or industry;
EXPLAIN engineering concepts accurately and effectively to inform technical and non-technical audiences using appropriate verbal, written, virtual and graphical means;
APPLY basic project management and business concepts and processes;
ENGAGE in lifelong learning to foster technical growth, ethical conduct, and the practice of professional communication, teamwork and leadership skills; and
OBTAIN licensure in a profession such as civil engineering.

As a professional discipline, civil engineering is closely related to the total human environment. In all professional endeavors, the civil engineer must consider ecological effects as well as the social, economic, and political needs of people. The civil engineer designs systems to control and manage our water resources to provide electric power, agricultural irrigation, flood control, recreation, water supplies and wastewater treatment systems for our urban and industrial needs.

The civil engineer plans, designs, and constructs our transportation systems including highways, railroads, waterways, and airports to connect rural, urban, and industrial areas. The civil engineer also designs and constructs housing and facilities for recreational, industrial, and commercial complexes, which comprise the urban environment. It is the responsibility of civil engineering to minimize air, water, and land pollution and protect the environment.

Instructional emphasis is placed on fundamental engineering principles derived from mathematics, chemistry, physics, and engineering science. These subjects provide a sound background for the subsequent introductory courses in environmental, geotechnical, structural, transportation, and water resources engineering. Students are introduced to design concepts in the freshman year. Design is incorporated throughout the curriculum that culminates in two senior-level courses, CIVE 385 Professional Practice and Management in Civil Engineering and CIVE 489 Senior Design Project.

Instructional laboratories in environmental engineering, hydraulics, geotechnical engineering, structures, and surveying provide each student with an opportunity to learn, through individual participation, the operation of the testing equipment used to establish engineering design criteria and to monitor and model engineering facilities such as water and wastewater treatment plants, river control systems, and structural systems.

Some students may desire to obtain a degree in construction management in addition to the degree in civil engineering. Because some civil engineering courses require prerequisites beyond those required for similar construction management courses, students should obtain the civil engineering degree first. Advising will be done by a civil engineering faculty member familiar with the construction management curriculum. After completing the civil engineering degree, the student will move to the construction management department to complete requirements for the second undergraduate degree in construction management.

The Departments of Civil Engineering and Architecture have a joint program awarding licensing degrees in both fields of study. A bachelors degree in civil engineering and masters degree in architecture are awarded, after approximately seven years of study. The departments work with individual students in tailoring a joint degree program. More information can be obtained from either department office.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Professional Admission Requirements

Criteria for Professional Admission to the Civil Engineering Degree Program

Pre-professionally admitted College of Engineering students majoring in civil engineering must have their academic records reviewed for professional admission to the Civil Engineering Degree Program during the fall, spring or summer immediately following the term in which:

·         at least 43 credits applicable to the degree have been earned, and

·         PHYS 211, MECH 223, MECH 325 and MECH 373 have been completed with “C” letter grades or better.

It is likely a student may need to complete four full semesters of credits applying to the Program before these requirements are able to be completed.

To be considered for professional admission, the following College of Engineering general criteria must be met:

·         Completion of at least 12 credits (one semester) after admission to the College of Engineering,

·         Cumulative grade point average of 2.5 or greater, and

·         No more than two declined admission requests to other engineering majors.

Professional admission approval to the Civil Engineering Degree Program requires the following Departmental specific criteria must also be achieved:

·         Earn a “C” letter grade or better in PHYS 211, MECH 223, MECH 325 and MECH 373, and

·         Earn a “C” letter grade or better in ALL math, science and engineering courses required for the Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering degree ifthe cumulative grade point average is less than 2.700.

Students approved for professional admission to the Program are then allowed to take 400-level civil engineering courses to complete their degree.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree of Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campuses)

Students must have completed the equivalent of the fourth semester before admission to the civil engineering program. Transfer students must have all transfer hours accepted before being considered for the degree program.

First Semester Hours

CIVE 112 Introduction to Civil Engineering 1

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering & Science Focus 3

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Chemistry Elective 4

Chemistry elective must be CHEM 111, CHEM 113, or both CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 (8 hrs).

Total 16

Second Semester Hours

CIVE 130 Computer-aided Design 2

MECH 130 is an acceptable substitute.

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 16

Third Semester Hours

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

MECH 223 Engineering Statics 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

CHEM 221 is an acceptable substitute.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

CIVE 361 Highway Engineering 3

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations for Engineers 3

MECH 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

MECH 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

Total 15

Fifth Semester Hours

CIVE 310 Fluid Mechanics 3

CIVE 319 Hydraulics Lab 1

CIVE 326 Introduction to Environmental Engineering 3

CIVE 327 Environmental Engineering Lab 1

CIVE 341 Introduction to Structural Engineering 4

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications or IMSE 321 Engineering Statistics &
Data Analysis 3

Total 15

Sixth Semester Hours

CIVE 334 Introduction to Geotechnical Engineering 4

CIVE 352 Introduction to Water Resources Engineering 3

CIVE 378 Materials of Construction 3

CIVE 385 Professional Practice & Management 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 16

Seventh Semester Hours

Technical Elective 3

A description of allowable technical elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Design Electives 6

A full list of approved elective courses is available from the department.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Science Elective 4

Approved science elective courses include BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L, CHEM 251 & CHEM 253, and GEOL 101.

CIVE 498 Special Topics 1

A list of allowable alternative courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Total 17

Eighth Semester Hours

CIVE 489 Senior Design Project 3

Technical Electives 9

A description of allowable technical elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Design Elective 3

A full list of approved elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Professional Development Elective 3

A full list of approved professional development elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Total 18

Total Credit Hours Required 130

Design Electives

CIVE 419 Flow Systems Design (3 cr)

CIVE 425 Process Design in Water Supply & Wastewater Treatment (3 cr)

CIVE 426 Design of Water Treatment Facilities (3 cr)

CIVE 427 Design of Wastewater Treatment & Disposal Facilities (3 cr)

CIVE 436 Foundation Engineering (3 cr)

CIVE 440 Reinforced Concrete Design I (3 cr)

CIVE 441 Steel Design I (3 cr)

CIVE 452 Water Resources Development (3 cr)

CIVE 462 Highway Design (3 cr)

CIVE 463 Traffic Engineering (3 cr)

Classics & Religious Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Classics & Religious Studies

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes - Classics; Religious Studies

CHIEF ADVISER: Yaroslav Komarovski (Religious Studies); Thomas Rinkevich (Classics)

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Stephen G. Burnett, 237 Andrews Hall

Professors: Burnett, S. Crawford, Lahey, Turner

Associate Professors: Athanassopoulos (anthropology), Duncan, Gorman, Komarovski, Rinkevich, Wood

Assistant Professor: Murray

Senior Lecturer: D. Crawford

Assistant Professor of Practice: Lippman

The courses and majors in the Department of Classics and Religious Studies have been designed to meet the needs of three categories of students:

1. Those who wish to pursue the subjects for general educational purposes;

2. Those who plan to major and do graduate work in classics or religious studies;

3. Those who want to become high school Latin teachers.

Any student who studies classics and religious studies will acquire the basic elements of a liberal education and a beneficial background for study in professional schools.

The Major in Classics and Religious Studies

The classics and religious studies major offers a wide range of courses in the civilization, religions and culture of the ancient Mediterranean world, as well as ancient and modern religions broadly conceived. It is an interdisciplinary major with two areas of emphasis, one in Classics and one in Religious Studies. Depending on your chosen emphasis, this major is designed to provide you with an excellent background to pursue graduate work in classical languages and literature, classical archaeology, ancient history, religious studies, literary scholarship, and other humane disciplines. In addition, the broad and humane education offered by the major serves as excellent preparation for careers in law, medicine, journalism, ministry, business and education.

The Major in Classical Languages

This major is intended primarily for those interested in graduate study of the Greco-Roman world. As competency in both Greek and Latin is requisite for graduate study, students must take courses in both languages to complete the major. This major is also appropriate for students who wish to undertake advanced study in related fields such as linguistics, or to teach high school Latin.

Education Abroad. Advanced undergraduates are encouraged to further their education abroad. Students may choose from among several established programs that cover a full academic year, semester, or summer. Most ancient studies programs offer a variety of courses in classics, ancient and modern languages, and history. In addition, students are introduced to the archaeology and art of the culture by frequent trips to sites and museums. These programs include, but are not limited to the American School of Classical Studies at Athens, College Year in Athens, the Intercollegiate Center for Classical Studies in Rome, and The Hebrew University in Jerusalem.

Also, UNL faculty frequently offer archaeological study tours to Greece, Italy, Turkey and Egypt during the summers. The department administers the Clarence A. Forbes Fellowship for education abroad. Further information on education abroad scholarships and programs may be found at http://educationabroad.unl.edu.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Select 3 hrs from:

CLAS 180 Classical Mythology (3 cr)

CLAS 121 Classical Antiquity in Popular Culture (AHIS 121) (3 cr)

CLAS 141 Spectacle & Entertainment in the Roman World (3 cr)

Select 3 hrs from:

RELG 108 World Religions (3 cr)

RELG 118 Introduction to Hinduism, Buddhism, & Daoism (3 cr)

RELG 150 Explaining Religion (3 cr)

RELG 181 Judaism, Christianity, & Islam (3 cr)

Specific Major Requirements

An emphasis in either Classics or Religious Studies is required (described below). Nine hours must be taken at the 300 level or above. No more than 6 hours of independent study may count toward the major.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required from time to time to complete written exit surveys and to compile portfolios of selected work in major courses. All such work will be assessed in ways that assure student anonymity. The Classics and Religious Studies undergraduate advisers will inform students of the scheduling and format of assessment activities.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Emphasis in Classics

In addition to the core courses, 24 hours of courses with the prefix CLAS, GREK or LATN (language courses above the 199 level), or courses which are crosslisted with CLAS. Related courses offered by other departments may count toward the major. See degree audit or academic adviser in Classics for approved courses.

Emphasis in Religious Studies

In addition to the core courses, 24 hours of courses with the prefix RELG. Of the 24 hours, at least 6 hours at the 200 level, 6 hours at the 300 level and 3 hours at the 400 level Religious Studies (RELG) courses, or cross-listed Religious Studies courses. Related courses offered by other departments may count toward the major. See degree audit or academic adviser in Religious Studies for approved courses. The student may count up to 6 hours above the 199 level in Greek, Latin, Hebrew or Arabic toward the Religious Studies major. Students also have the opportunity, through a cooperative agreement, to take selected courses at Nebraska Wesleyan University in ethics, theology and world religions. These courses are identified with a “w” as part of the course number.

Minor Requirements

A minor is required and may be any minor approved by the College.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Departmental permission to take major or minor courses for Pass/No Pass credit must be obtained. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Minor in Classics

A minimum of 18 hours of courses with the prefix CLAS, GREK or LATN (language courses above the 199 level) or which are cross-listed with CLAS. At least 6 hours must be above 299.

Minor in Religious Studies

A minimum of 18 hours of courses with the prefix RELG, including at least 3 hours at the 100 level, 3 hours at the 200 level, and 3 hours at the 300 or 400 level. The student may count up to 3 hours above the 199 level in Greek, Latin, Hebrew or Arabic toward the Religious Studies minor.

Coaching Minor

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

PROGRAM: Coaching (Minor only)

DEGREE: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 15

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

This minor is not available for students seeking teacher certification; a supplemental endorsement in coaching is available for students in teacher education.

Course Requirements

ATHT 235 (3 hrs)

ATHC 494 (3 hrs)

Select three from the following: ATHC 311, ATHC 312, ATHC 317, ATHC 318 (6 hrs)

Contact: Dr. Tom Wandzilak, twandzilak1@unl.edu, 402-472-8626.

OTHER

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Communication Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Communication Studies

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Karen Lee, Kristen Carr

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Dawn O. Braithwaite, 433 Oldfather

Director of Forensics: Aaron Duncan

Professors: Braithwaite, Krone, R. Lee, Seiler

Associate Professors: Kellas, Soliz

Assistant Professors: Pfister, Woods

Assistant Professor of Practice: K. Lee

Communication studies is a social science and humanistic field of study, research, and application. The mission of the Department of Communication Studies is to examine human symbolic activity as it shapes and is shaped by relationships, institutions, and societies. This work concerns how, why, and with what effects people communicate through verbal and nonverbal messages. Through research, teaching, and service, the Department devotes particular attention to understanding the ways in which communication erodes and sustains collaboration within and among local, national, and global communities.

Communication competencies are among those most highly desired in professional, personal, organizational, and civic arenas. Additionally, a major in Communication Studies goes beyond learning communication skills by fostering a world view that demonstrates a commitment to communication, collaboration, and community. Communication Studies majors go on to careers in sales, marketing, human resources, customer service, nonprofit management, event planning, fund raising, public relations, management, and government, to name just a few. Majors also go on to graduate school and law school.

University Debate and Forensics

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln offers a nationally recognized debate and forensics program of participation in campus and intercollegiate debate, public speaking, and interpretation events. The program gives students the opportunity to compete at the local, state, regional, and national level. No previous debate or speech experience is required. All students who are in good standing may take part in intercollegiate debate and forensics.

Graduate Work. Graduate programs leading to the master of arts and doctor of philosophy degrees are offered in the department. A master of arts specialization in marketing, communication studies, and advertising is also offered by the department. A detailed description of these programs appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

All prospective majors must consult and register with a departmental chief adviser. Majors are expected to meet regularly with their adviser. An approved program of study must be filed at the time students declare the major or within the first 12 hours of course work in the major. In order to graduate with a communication studies major, students must have an approved program of study. The minimum number of hours for a major in communication studies is 36. The 36-hour requirement must include the following:

1. Majors must complete one of the following: COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 212, COMM 220, COMM 286, or COMM 295.

2. Majors must complete both COMM 101 and COMM 201. These courses should be completed within the first twelve hours in communication studies of a student’s program.

3. Majors must complete two of three 200-level foundational courses which include COMM 283. See major adviser for additional eligible course options.

4. Majors must complete COMM 495.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to complete an assessment of the major. This assessment will be implemented in the communication studies capstone course: COMM 495.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA, but could prevent or delay graduation if the assessment is not completed as required.

Minor Requirements

A communication studies major must have either an approved Plan A minor or two approved Plan B minors. An approved individualized program of studies of 24 hours can also be used to meet the minor requirement. A departmental adviser must approve the minor.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

COMM 101 and COMM 201 must be completed before a student can enroll in any 400-level course.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

A grade of C or above is required for all courses in the major.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Availability of Pass/No Pass credit in COMM courses is at the discretion of the course director and/or instructor of the course. Although the department discourages Pass/No Pass credit for majors, up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass credit may be applied to the major requirements. Up to 6 hours Pass/No Pass credit is permitted toward the minor, subject to the approval of the department granting the major.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 21 hours must be taken in communication studies courses at or above the 300 level, excluding COMM 390 and COMM 490. Of the 21 hours, at least 9 must be at the 400 level. COMM 101 and COMM 201 must be completed before a student can enroll in any 400-level course. COMM 490 cannot be used to meet this requirement.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules

The department encourages qualified students to enroll in internship, independent study, and education abroad experiences in order to supplement classroom experiences. However, non of these is a substitute for classroom experiences. No more than 3 hours of internship, independent study, or education abroad credits may count toward the 36-hour requirement in the major.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

A communication studies major must have either an approved Plan A minor or two approved Plan B minors. An approved individualized program of study of 24 hours can also be used to meet the minor requirement. A departmental adviser must approve the minor.

Plan A. This minor consists of a minimum of 18 hours in communication studies courses with at least 9 hours at or above the 300 level. The 18-hour requirement must include the following:

1. Plan A minors must complete either COMM 101 or COMM 201.

2. Plan A minors must complete either COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 212, COMM 220, COMM 286, or COMM 295.

3. A minimum of 9 hours must be taken in communication studies classes at or above the 300 level excluding COMM 390 and COMM 490.

4. Of the 9 hours, at least 3 must be at the 400 level. COMM 101 or COMM 201 must be completed before a student can enroll in any 400-level course. COMM 490 cannot be used to meet this requirement.

5. The department encourages qualified students to enroll in internship, independent study, and study abroad experiences in order to supplement classroom experiences. However, none of these is a substitute for classroom experiences. No more than 3 hours of internship, independent study, or study abroad credits may count toward the 36-credit-hour requirement in the major. Please refer to items 4 and 5 above. .

Plan B. 12 hours of communication studies courses with at least 9 hours at or above the 200 level, excluding COMM 390 or COMM 490. A maximum of 3 hours of internship or independent study may apply to the 12-hour requirement.

Computer Engineering (Lincoln)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Computer Engineering (Lincoln)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 125

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISER: Charles Riedesel

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Steve Goddard, 256 Avery Hall

Professors: Deogun, Dwyer, Elbaum, Goddard, Jiang, Ramamurthy, Reichenbach, Revesz, Rothermel, Samal, Seth (emeritus), Sincovec (emeritus), Surkan (emeritus)

Associate Professors: Choueiry, Cohen, Costello (emeritus), Lu, Scott, Soh, Srisa-An, Variyam, Vuran, Xu

Assistant Professors: Detweiler, Sarma, Yu, Zhong

Research Associate Professor: Swanson

Assistant Professor of Practice: Riedesel

Lecturers: Bourke, Suing

Phone: 402-472-2401

FAX: 402-472-7767

Website: http://cse.unl.edu

Email: info@cse.unl.edu

The UNL Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) Department offers Nebraska’s only comprehensive program of higher education, research, and service outreach in computer science and computer engineering.

The CSE Department offers a challenging baccalaureate degree program in computer engineering that prepares graduates for professional practice in commerce, industry, and government, and for post-graduate education to enter careers in research and academia. The BS degree in computer engineering is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

The focus of the program is integrated hardware/software system design. Increasingly, diverse systems, products, and processes depend on computers for design, control, data acquisition, and other functions. The computer engineer possesses the range of expertise to have an integrated view of computer-based systems and to make global design decisions.

Consistent with this focus, the computer engineering baccalaureate program develops:

The ability to view computer systems as an integrated continuum of technologies and to engage in integrated system-level design. Studies include mathematical foundations, digital logic and technologies, programming and software design, system components and design, application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, and documentation and maintenance.
The ability to work with professionals in related fields over the spectrum of system design. Studies include natural sciences, electricity/electronics, and programming and software design.
Skills to quickly adapt to new work environments, assimilate new information, and solve new problems. Studies develop skills in the application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, documentation and maintenance, and technical communications.
The background and perspective for post-graduate education. Studies develop skills in the application of theory, experimentation, and life-long learning/professional development.
Abilities to work in conformance with societal needs and expectations. Studies include liberal arts and ethical/social issues.
Insight into the world of practicing professionals, for collaborations, mutual support, and representing the profession to government and society. Studies include teamwork and life-long learning/professional development, plus students are provided multiple opportunities for involvement in organizations such as ACM, UPE, and IEEE.

The CSE department also offers a degree of bachelor of science in computer science through the College of Arts and Sciences. All students majoring in the CSE department should see their advisers during their first semester to make sure they understand the differences in the requirements of the two programs. Majors should consult with their advisers each semester for registration advising.

Introductory Courses. Entering students may select from several introductory courses according to their interests and as indicated by the CSE Placement Examination. The Computer Science I courses (CSCE 155A, CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, and CSCE 155T) all provide a foundation in designing and programming computing solutions and prepare students for more advanced CSCE courses, including CSCE 156. These courses are designed to meet different interests. CSCE 155A is designed for students majoring in computer science. CSCE 155H is for honors students. CSCE 155E emphasizes computing for systems engineering, such as control systems, mobile computing, and embedded devices and is designed for students majoring in computer engineering. CSCE 155N focuses on numerical and graphical computation in engineering and science, such as applied physics, working with time-sequence data, and matrix applications. CSCE 155T focuses on data and information processing, such as document or database applications, online commerce, or bioinformatics. CSCE 156 is for students with a background in designing and programming computing solutions, such as is provided by Computer Science I. CSCE 101 is for students seeking a broad introduction to computer science with brief instruction in computer programming.

Graduate Programs. The CSE Department offers several graduate degree programs: master of science in computer science, master of science in computer science with computer engineering specialization, master of science in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science, doctor of philosophy in engineering with computer engineering specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, and joint doctor of philosophy in computer science and mathematics. See the Graduate Studies Bulletin for details.

ADMISSION

Other Admission Requirements

Computer Science Placement Policy

The required Computer Science and Engineering Placement Exam (CSEPE) is used to assess students’ background in problem solving, computer programming, and relevant mathematics. Students who have not taken a recognized UNL or transfer prerequisite course with a grade of C or better must take the CSEPE.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

First Semester Hours

CSCE 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus* 3

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Taking both CSCE 230 and CSCE 488 satisfies ACE outcome 8.

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CSCE 156 Computer Science II* 4

CSCE 235 Introduction to Discrete Structures* 3

CSCE 251 Unix Programming Environment 1

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 16

Third Semester Hours

CSCE 230 Computer Organization* 3

CSCE 230L Computer Organization Lab* 1

ELEC 215 Electronics & Circuits I 3

ELEC 235 Introductory Electrical Lab I 1

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

Science Requirement 4-5

Must be a course designed for science/engineering majors with a laboratory component. Choose from: CHEM 109 (4 hrs) or PHYS 213 & PHYS 223 (5 hrs, required for students electing VLSI Design as their focus area).

Total 16-17

Fourth Semester Hours

CSCE 236 Embedded Systems 3

CSCE 310 Data Structures & Algorithms* 3

ELEC 216 Electronics & Circuits II 3

ELEC 236 Introductory Electrical Lab II 1

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

Total 16

Fifth Semester Hours

CSCE 351 Operating System Kernels 3

CSCE 361 Software Engineering 3

ELEC 304 Signals & Systems I 3

ELEC 316 Electronics & Circuits III 3

Open Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Taking both CSCE 230 and CSCE 488 satisfies ACE outcome 8.

Total 18

Sixth Semester Hours

CSCE 335 Digital Logic Design 3

CSCE 462 Communication Networks 3

ELEC 305 Probability Theory & Introduction to Random Processes 3

MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra 3

Technical Elective 3

Total 15

Seventh Semester Hours

CSCE 340 Numerical Analysis I 3

CSCE 488 Computer Engineering Professional Development**&*** 2

JGEN 300 Technical Communication II 3

Technical Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Taking both CSCE 230 and CSCE 488 satisfies ACE outcome 8.

Total 14

Eighth Semester Hours

CSCE 489 Computer Engineering Senior Design Project**&*** 3

Technical Electives 9

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Taking both CSCE 230 and CSCE 488 satisfies ACE outcome 8.

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required 125

* As part of the required core courses in computer science and engineering, students in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management take RAIK 183H, RAIK 184H, RAIK 283H, RAIK 284H, and RAIK 383H instead of CSCE 155E, CSCE 156, CSCE 230, CSCE 230L, CSCE 235, CSCE 310 and CSCE 361.

** Students in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management may substitute RAIK 381H or RAIK 382H for CSCE 488, and RAIK 302H or RAIK 402H for CSCE 489 with advance approval from both the Design Studio and Computer Engineering Senior Design instructors.

*** Double majors in electrical engineering may elect to take either of the senior design course sequences (CSCE 488 then CSCE 489 or ELEC 494 then ELEC 495). Students not taking both CSCE 230 and CSCE 488 must satisfy ACE outcome 8 with another course(s).

The computer engineering degree requires 125 hours of course work. There is a set of required core courses in computer science and engineering (41 credit hours), electrical engineering (17 credit hours), mathematics (19 credit hours), and physics and chemistry (12-13 credit hours). In addition, students select 3 credit hours of open elective and 15 credit hours of technical electives with the focus areas option as described below.

A computer engineering major has the option of declaring a focus in one of the areas listed below. Students who, in addition to completing all computer engineering required courses listed above, receive a grade of C or better in each of the three technical elective courses from one focus area below, will receive a notice from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering stating that they received the degree bachelor of science in computer engineering with a focus in their chosen area(s). The focus areas are:

Embedded Systems and Robotics: CSCE 436 (required), CSCE 439 or MECH 453, CSCE 430, CSCE 438, CSCE 476, ELEC 479
VLSI Design: CSCE 434 or ELEC 470 (required), CSCE 421, CSCE 430, ELEC 416, ELEC 421, ELEC 475. Students choosing this focus area must take PHYS 213 and PHYS 223 as the science requirement.
Signal Processing and Communications: ELEC 462, ELEC 463, ELEC 464, ELEC 465, CSCE 438, CSCE 463, CSCE 472, CSCE 473.
High-Performance Computing: CSCE 430 (required), CSCE 432, CSCE 435, CSCE 437, CSCE 455, CSCE 456.

The 15 credit hours can be taken from exactly one focus area or from any combination of the focus areas courses plus 300- or 400-level CSCE, ELEC, and RAIK courses, but subject to the following restrictions:

1. At least 9 hours must be taken from CSCE and/or cross-listed courses in RAIK (namely, RAIK 384H, RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, and RAIK 402H).

2. At least 9 hours must be taken at the 400 level.

3. CSCE 390 and CSCE 490 have been pre-designated as not applying to the major and cannot count as technical electives.

4. At most, 3 hours of independent study (CSCE 399, CSCE 498, ELEC 399, ELEC 499) may apply.

5. At most, 6 hours of internship/practicum courses (CSCE 491, CSCE 493, RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, RAIK 402H) may apply.

6. ELEC 494 and ELEC 495 may not apply (however, these may be substituted for CSCE 488 and CSCE 489).

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required in their senior year to complete a written exit survey. Results of that participation will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Applicants for formal admission to computer engineering must meet the usual college requirements plus a minimum grade rule on the following core courses (or their equivalents):

Grades of C+ or higher in CSCE 155A, CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, CSCE 155T, CSCE 156, CSCE 230, CSCE 230L, CSCE 235; ELEC 215, ELEC 235; MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208; PHYS 211, PHYS 212

Computer Science

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Computer Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Charles Riedesel

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Steve Goddard, 256 Avery

Professors: Deogun, Dwyer, Elbaum, Goddard, Jiang, Ramamurthy, Reichenbach, Revesz, Rothermel, Samal, Seth (emeritus), Sincovec (emeritus), Surkan (emeritus)

Associate Professors: Choueiry, Cohen, Costello (emeritus), Lu, Scott, Soh, Srisa-an, Variyam, Vuran, Xu

Assistant Professors: Cui, Detweiler, Pierobon, Sarma, Yu, Zhong

Research Associate Professor: Swanson

Research Assistant Professors: Bockelman, Tian

Assistant Professor of Practice: Riedesel

Lecturers: Bourke, Patrick, Suing

Phone: 402-472-2401

FAX: 402-472-7767

http://cse.unl.edu

email: info@cse.unl.edu

The UNL Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) offers Nebraska's only comprehensive program of higher education, research, and service outreach in computer science and computer engineering.

The CSE department offers a challenging baccalaureate degree program in computer science that prepares graduates for professional practice as computer scientists, provides the basis for advanced studies in the field, and establishes a foundation for life-long learning and achievement. The BS degree in computer science is accredited by the Computing Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

Consistent with these goals, the computer science baccalaureate program develops:

The ability to solve a wide range of computing-related problems. Studies include mathematical foundations, computer science theory, programming and software design, system components and design, application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, and documentation and maintenance.
The ability to work with professionals in fields related to computing and/or having computing applications. Studies include natural sciences and the completion of at least one minor.
Skills to quickly adapt to new work environments, assimilate new information, and solve new problems. Studies include application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, documentation and maintenance, and technical communications.
The background and perspective necessary to pursue post-graduate education. Studies include computer science theory, application of theory, experimentation, and life-long learning/professional development.
Abilities to work in conformance with societal needs and expectations. Studies include liberal arts and ethical/social issues.
Insight into the world of practicing professionals for collaborations, mutual support, and representing the profession to government and society. Studies include teamwork and life-long learning/professional development, plus students are provided multiple opportunities for involvement in organizations such as ACM and UPE; undergraduate research; and service to the department and community.

The CSE Department also offers a degree of bachelor of science in computer engineering through the College of Engineering. All students majoring in the CSE Department should see their advisers during their first semester to make sure they understand the differences in the requirements of the two programs. Majors must consult with their advisers each semester for registration advising.

Introductory Courses. Entering students may select from several introductory courses, according to their interests and as indicated by the CSE Placement Examination. The Computer Science I courses (CSCE 155A, CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, and CSCE 155T) all provide a foundation in designing and programming computing solutions and prepare students for more advanced CSCE courses, including CSCE 156. These courses are designed to meet different interests. CSCE 155A is designed for students majoring in computer science. CSCE 155H is for honors students. CSCE 155E emphasizes computing for systems engineering, such as control systems, mobile computing, and embedded devices and is designed for students majoring in computer engineering. CSCE 155N focuses on numerical and graphical computation in engineering and science, such as applied physics, working with time-sequence data, and matrix applications. CSCE 155T focuses on data and information processing, such as document or database applications, online commerce, or bioinformatics. CSCE 156 is for students with a background in designing and programming computing solutions, such as is provided by Computer Science I. CSCE 101 is for students seeking a broad introduction to computer science with brief instruction in computer programming.

Graduate Programs. The CSE department offers several graduate degree programs: master of science in computer science, master of science in computer science with computer engineering specialization, master of science in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science, doctor of philosophy in engineering with computer engineering specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, and joint doctor of philosophy in computer science and mathematics. See the Graduate Studies Bulletin for details.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Computer Science (44 hours)

Computer Science Core (22-24 hrs)

CSCE 10, CSCE 155A (or CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, CSCE 155T), CSCE 156, CSCE 230, CSCE 235, CSCE 251, CSCE 310, CSCE 322, and CSCE 361

Or for students in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: RAIK 183H, RAIK 184H, RAIK 283H, RAIK 383H, CSCE 230, CSCE 251, CSCE 322.

Depth Courses (6 hrs)

CSCE 351 or CSCE 451, and

CSCE 423 or CSCE 428

Technical Electives (9-11 hrs)

Any CSCE/RAIK 3xx or 4xx courses except CSCE 390, CSCE 490, and RAIK courses lacking CSCE equivalents (except that RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 384H, RAIK 401H, and RAIK 402H are acceptable as technical electives).

Up to 3 hours of CSCE 491 can be used for technical electives, and an additional 3 hours can be used toward the 120 hours required for the degree.

At most, one of MATH 428, MATH 432, MATH 433, MATH 439, MATH 450, MATH 452

At least 6 credit hours of technical electives must be other than CSCE 399H, CSCE 491, CSCE 493, CSCE 498, RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, and RAIK 402H.

Senior Design Experience (6 hrs)

CSCE 486 (or RAIK 381H or RAIK 382H), and CSCE 487 (or RAIK 302H or RAIK 402H). CSCE 486 and CSCE 487 are to be taken in consecutive semesters.

Students completing the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management automatically satisfy the technical electives and senior design experience requirements and need only CSCE 251, CSCE 322, and the 6 hours of depth courses to satisfy the computer science requirements.

Mathematics (15 hours)

MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 314, and STAT 380

Science (12 hours)

Must take at least 12 credit hours of courses intended for science/engineering majors and must include at least one laboratory. The CSE department has identified the following five disciplines with their acceptable courses:

Chemistry: CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 221 (or CHEM 113, CHEM 114, CHEM 116)
Physics and Astronomy: PHYS 211, PHYS 221, PHYS 212, PHYS 222, PHYS 213, PHYS 223, ASTR 204, ASTR 224
Biological Sciences: BIOS 109, BIOS 111, BIOS 112, BIOS 112L, BIOS 205, BIOS 206, BIOS 207; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L
Earth and Atmospheric Sciences: GEOL 101, GEOL 103H, GEOL 210, GEOL 410, METR 200, METR 205, METR 370
Anthropology: ANTH 242, ANTH 242L

NOTE: Bold face type indicates a lab course or that a lab is included with the course.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required in their senior year to complete a written exit survey.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a students GPA or graduation.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Focus

A computer science major has the option of declaring a Focus in one of the areas listed below. Students who, in addition to meeting all computer science requirements listed above, receive a grade of C or better in each of three technical elective courses from one focus area below will receive a notice from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering stating that they received the degree bachelor of science in computer science with a Focus in their chosen area.

The Focus areas are as follows:

Informatics: CSCE 410, CSCE 413, CSCE 464, CSCE 470, CSCE 471, CSCE 472, CSCE 473, CSCE 474

Artificial Intelligence: CSCE 421, CSCE 475, CSCE 476, CSCE 478, CSCE 479

Computer and Networking Systems: CSCE 430, CSCE 432, CSCE 434, CSCE 435, CSCE 455, CSCE 456, CSCE 462, CSCE 465

Foundations: CSCE 440, CSCE 421, CSCE 423, CSCE 424, CSCE 428, CSCE 477

Software Engineering: CSCE 378, CSCE 425, CSCE 461, CSCE 464, CSCE 493 (CSCE 301H, CSCE 302H, CSCE 401H, CSCE 402H may be substituted for CSCE 493)

In addition, up to 3 hours of CSCE 498 Computer Problems (undergraduate research) can be used in any focus area. Some offerings of CSCE 496 Special Topics may be substituted in an appropriate area. See your adviser for more details.

A Focus is in addition to all major requirements. Thus, no course used by a student to fulfill a major requirement can also be applied to a Focus.

Customized Focus Areas are possible. The department chair, in consultation with relevant faculty members and the undergraduate adviser, may approve a customized Focus Area proposed by a student. See your adviser for more information.

To declare a Focus, see your adviser.

Minor Requirements

The Plan A minor enables students to develop expertise in an additional academic area. Completing MATH 208 (in addition to the major requirements) meets the Plan A minor requirement for mathematics. See your adviser for more information.

Students who wish to take a cohesive block of courses that crosses departmental or even college lines should consider the Individualized Program of Studies minor offered by the College or a business minor offered by the College of Business Administration.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Departmental permission to take major or minor courses for Pass/No Pass credit must be obtained. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirement

13 hours of the CSCE courses must be at the 400 level for students not completing the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

For students not enrolled in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: 18 hours of computer science courses, including one of CSCE 155A, CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, or CSCE 155T; at least one of CSCE 156 or CSCE 311; and at least 3 hours of CSCE courses at the 300 level or above, but excluding CSCE courses explicitly designated as not counting toward the minor.

For students enrolled in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: 18 hours of computer science courses, including CSCE 183H/RAIK 183H, CSCE 184H/RAIK 184H, and CSCE 283H/RAIK 283H. For the remaining 7 hours, students may count any CSCE courses (or RAIK courses cross-listed as CSCE courses) numbered 200 or above (except CSCE 235 and courses designated as not counting toward the minor) and up to 3 hours for a RAIK Design Studio course (RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, RAIK 402H).

Conflict & Conflict Resolution Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Conflict & Conflict Resolution Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 24

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Fran Kaye

DESCRIPTION

Chair and Chief Adviser: Fran Kaye

Faculty: Cahan (philosophy), Demers (anthropology and geography), Dienstbier (psychology), Hames (anthropology/geography), Leger (psychology), Maslowski (history), Potter (philosophy)

This program is concerned with violent conflict between social groups–the biological, ecological, economic, social, and political basis of such conflict and its relationship to religion, philosophy, and the arts. It examines the history of efforts to resolve or prevent violent conflicts through such means as armaments, negotiations, diplomacy, international law, and nonviolent resistance to violence.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The core course in conflict and conflict resolution (cross-listed as ANTH 261, POLS 261, PSYC 261 and SOCI 261) is required. In addition, students must take one course from six of the following seven groups:

I. Evolution, Human Biology and Warfare

ANTH 353 Anthropology of War

BIOS 203 Bioethics

BIOS 373/PSYC 373 Biopsychology

II. The Social Unit, Aggression and Violence

COMM 371 Communication in Negotiation & Conflict Resolution

HIST 303/803 United States Military History, 1607-1917

HIST 304/804 United States Military History Since 1917

PSYC 401 Psychology & Law

SOCI 201 Social Problems

SOCI 415/815 Social Change

SOCI 491/891 Political Sociology

III. International Society

HIST 347 America & the World to 1914

HIST 348 America & the World Since 1914

POLS 160 International Relations

POLS 468/868 Organizing World Order

POLS 469/869 International Law

IV. History of Warfare and its Impact on States and Within States

AERO 441 & AERO 442 National Security Affairs & Preparation for Active Duty I & II

HIST 338/838 War & Peace in Europe: 1914 to Present

NAVS 321 Evolution of Warfare

ETHN 217/SOCI 217 Nationality & Race Relations

V. Science and Technology: Arms and Arms Control

NAVS 321 Evolution of Warfare

POLS 398 Arms Racing & Arms Control

VI. Economics and Resource Economics and the Origins of Modern Aggression

AECN 346 World Food Economics

ECON 423/823 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

POLS 459/859 International Political Economy

VII. Human Cultural Responses to War and its Alternatives

ENGL 210 Themes in Literature

PHIL 220 Elements of Ethics

Substitutions in this program may be made if such substitution can be justified on vocational or intellectual grounds.

A senior seminar will complete the program of 24 hours. Courses that are part of a student’s major may be used to satisfy the requirements for a conflict resolution minor.

Construction Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Construction Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Construction Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 126

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Christine Warren

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Eddy M. Rojas

Program Coordinator: Terri Norton

Professors: Foster, Goedert, Rojas, Sires

Associate Professors: Bernstein, Bonsell, Harmon, Jensen, Morcous, Norton, Schwer, Stentz

Assistant Professors: Ahn, Esmaeili, Lau, Pedersen

Construction engineering (CONE) is a program of the Charles W. Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction. The construction engineering major integrates engineering, construction, and management courses. This program is designed for persons fulfilling the construction industry’s need for licensed professional engineers. It resembles the construction management program but provides a greater emphasis on engineering, scientific, and technical courses so that requirements for licensure are met. The courses in construction engineering focus on the application of engineering principles to solve real world construction problems.  They include instruction in civil engineering, structural principles, material testing and evaluation, project management, computer-assisted design, 3D animation, sustainability and graphic communication.

The educational objective of the construction engineering program is to produce graduates who:

Possess lifelong knowledge acquisition skills enabling them to add value to society throughout their construction careers by

applying engineering principles of analysis and design to the constructed environment

learning technical skills, innovative thought and dedication to search for ways to improve society through enhanced functionality, efficiency and decreased cost
developing communication skills to effectively share their ideas with others
adapting to the constantly changing, interdisciplinary world of design and construction by learning good team work and team building skills

using appropriate construction practices including:

business organization

estimating

scheduling

project delivery

ethics

Under the stimulus of increasing demand for its services globally, the construction industry has expanded its technological capabilities pertaining to physical and informational systems. This demand gives the construction engineering graduate an unprecedented number of opportunities for employment and for pursuing an advanced degree.

Construction engineers participate in the preparation of engineering and architectural plans and specifications which they translate into finished projects, such as buildings, bridges, highways, power plants, or other constructed facilities. These projects involve thousands of details shared by a team of owners, architects, engineers, general constructors, specialty constructors, manufacturers, material suppliers, equipment distributors, regulatory bodies and agencies, labor resources, and numerous others. The constructor assumes responsibility for delivery of the completed project at a specified time and cost and also accepts associated legal, financial, and management obligations. Because of the broad scope of the construction engineer’s project responsibility, he/she must assure the project’s ability to be constructed as well as its ability to be operated and sustained.

Construction Engineering is accredited by the EAC-ABET, Inc.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Please visit our website for the latest information on the Construction Engineering requirements for the Bachelor of Science program.

http://engineering.unl.edu/durhamschool/academics/ConstructionEngineering.shtml

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

All course work must be of “C” grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

Students are required to enroll in a predetermined set of courses specifically designed for general construction education.  Each student selects, with the approval of his/her adviser, a set of approved electives.

The CONE program follows the UNL ACE general education requirements.  Because of the specific needs of the program, several of these courses are specified in the curriculum.  Please contact Christine Warren, student services coordinator, at cwarren2@unl.edu or 402-554-3918, if you are interested in more information about this program.

Culinary Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Culinary Science

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Cameya Ramirez-Rousseau

DESCRIPTION

The Culinary Science (Culinology®) option is the emerging discipline of the culinary arts, nutrition and the science of food. Culinology® is becoming a recognized and valued discipline that will significantly impact food research and development in the global market. Culinologists are skilled chefs who are creating a new generation of exciting, high-quality food products. The food industry needs, and rewards, people who understand and can apply the principles of this specialty.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 31

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. ECON 211 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. ECON 212 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. FDST 460 (Professional Requirement) 3

Culinary Arts Concentration 22

(Select any culinary arts electives from an accredited Institution)

Professional Requirements 32

HRTM 173 and NUTR 245 1 hr ea 2

NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 344, (NUTR 372 or BIOS 312) and NUTR 449 15

NUTR 441 &/or NUTR 445 &/or FDST 448 (3 hrs ea – select two) 6

FDST 205, FDST 403 and FDST 430 (3 hrs ea) 9

Supporting Courses 17-20

MATH 101 or higher 3-5

MRKT 341 3

BIOC 321 3

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 (3 hrs) & CHEM 253 (1 hr) 4

Processing Electives 6

Select any two courses from the following: (ASCI 210, ASCI 213, ASCI 310, ASCI 410) or (FDST 363, FDST 405, FDST 412, FDST 420, FDST 429, FDST 455) or NUTR 343

Electives 9-12

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Area of Concentration

Culinary Arts electives from an accredited Culinary Arts Institution

Professional Requirements

Nutrition and Health Sciences

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

HRTM 173 Field Experience in Culinology®

NUTR 244 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation

NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation or BIOS 312 Microbiology

NUTR 441 Functional Properties of Food &/or FDST 448 Food Chemistry &/or NUTR 445 Experimental Foods

NUTR 449 Culinology® Research Experience

Food Science and Technology

FDST 205 Food Composition & Analysis

FDST 403 Food Quality Assurance

FDST 430 Sensory Evaluation

FDST 460 Food Product Development Concepts

Supporting Sciences

BIOC 321 Elements of Biochemistry

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

Supporting Courses

ECON 211 & ECON 212 Principles of Macroeconomics & Microeconomics

MATH 101 College Algebra

If a student does not place into MATH 101, they must complete the appropriate course(s) plus complete MATH 101. If a student places above MATH 101, the student will take either MATH 101 or the MATH course they placed into.

MRKT 341 Marketing

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics

Processing Electives

Select two courses from:

ASCI 210 Animal Products

ASCI 213 Meat Specifications & Procurement

ASCI 310 Fresh Meats

ASCI 410 Processed Meats

FDST 363 Heat & Mass Transfer

FDST 405 Food Microbiology

FDST 412 Cereal Technology

FDST 420 Fruit & Vegetable Technology

FDST 429 Dairy Products Technology

FDST 455 Microbiology of Fermented Foods

NUTR 343 Meat Culinology® III: Foodservice Applications (Grade of C or better required in NUTR 343)

Electives

OTHER

Meat Culinology® Certificate Program

The Meat Culinology® Certificate program at UNL concentrates on meat because it is the center of most meals and is the major portion of the food budget in the food service industry. Proper handling and preparation is paramount to the success of a meal and a food establishment. The faculty at UNL who developed this program know that food industry professionals are busy. With little time to take courses on campus, the online Meat Culinology® Certificate program allows professionals the opportunity to advance their education and career by learning more about the science and art of meat. The six-course sequence will teach you everything from harvest to consumption of livestock and poultry. The Meat Culinology® Certificate program consists of six courses. Students must successfully complete all six courses in order to earn certification. Successful completion is considered an earned grade of ‘C’ or higher.

Meat Culinology® Certificate Program

ASCI 210 Animal Products

ASCI 213/NUTR 213 Meat Specification & Procurement

ASCI 310 Fresh Meats

NUTR 343/ASCI 343 Meat Culinology® III: Foodservice Applications

ASCI 410 Processed Meats

ASCI 411 HACCP & Food Safety Systems for the Food Industry

Early Care & Education (Birth-K)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Early Care & Education (Birth-K)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Val Wiemeyer

DESCRIPTION

Students who complete this field endorsement may work with infants and toddlers as an educator and are prepared to work effectively with families and children from diverse backgrounds. The program includes an emphasis on family systems and working with infants, toddlers and families in community contexts.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the curriculum and these must be successfully completed in order to be certified in the teaching profession. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Felony and Misdemeanor Conviction” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements (or majors) are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30-34

ACE 1. ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254, JOUR 102 3

ACE 2. COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, COMM 286, ALEC 102 3

ACE 3. MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 203, MATH 208; SOCI 206; STAT 218; EDPS 459 3-5

ACE 4. ENTO 115/ENTO 116; NRES 108; METR 200; ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105 or CHEM 109; GEOG 155; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; TMFD 206; GEOL 101 or GEOL 103; PHYS 141 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. TEAC 331 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 9. TEAC 330 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 497A (Professional Education Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Education Requirements 22

LIBR 110 1

CYAF 170 & CYAF 271 (3 hrs ea) 6

CYAF 270 2

CYAF 270L & CYAF 271L (1 hr ea) 2

NUTR 100 3

SPED 201 3

TEAC 259 3

TEAC 297A 2

Endorsement Requirements 26

CYAF 374 & CYAF 210 (3 hrs ea) 6

CYAF 374L & CYAF 210L (1 hr ea) 2

CYAF 380 & CYAF 383 & CYAF 474 (3 hrs ea) 9

SLPA 251 3

SPED 303 & SPED 463 (3 hrs ea) 6

Professional Education Requirements 35

CYAF 371 & CYAF 384 (3 hrs ea) 6

CYAF 371L 1

CYAF 497A (3 hrs are met in ACE 10) 9

CYAF 497I & CYAF 497K (6 hrs ea) 12

TEAC 310 3

SPED 362 3

SPED 496Y 1

Electives 3-7

Suggested electives include: CYAF 495, CYAF 477; ANTH 473; BIOS 232; ENTO 115/ENTO 116; ENVR 201; HORT 200; NRES 220; SOCI 446; SPED 472, SPED 480

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADMISSION

All education programs have a competitive admission process. At some point-in-time, after meeting specific education requirements, all students must formally apply to their particular education program.

Pre-Education Status

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program are classified as pre-education students until admitted to a specific Teacher Education Program.

Admission to the Early Care & Education: B-K Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Students must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the Early Care and Education B-K Teacher Education Program:

1. Completion of at least 30 credit hours with a minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

2. Completion of the following courses with a grade of C+ or above: TEAC 331; CYAF 271 & CYAF 271L or CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L; SPED 201 or equivalent; TEAC 297A; approved speech class.

3. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of the Praxis I, Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

4. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program application form and documentation of practica experiences.

5. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form (PPF) as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate, are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 116 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience for an entire semester. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Admission to the Early Care and Education B-K program.

2. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

3. A minimum 2.5 GPA in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below a C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

4. All endorsement, pre-professional and professional education course work must be completed prior to student teaching. If necessary, no more than 6 hours of general education (ACE) or elective classes can be completed after the student teaching experience.

5. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester unless prior approval is obtained from the Certification Officer, the Director of Field Experiences, or the Department Chair that oversees the program.

6. Completion of a second criminal history check that will be conducted, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required). For more information, contact the Director of Field Experiences or your adviser.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Child Development

CYAF 210 Applied Methods of Social Emotional Development & Guidance

CYAF 210L Applied Methods of Social Emotional Development & Guidance Lab

CYAF 374 Curriculum Planning in Early Childhood Education

CYAF 374L Curriculum Planning in Early Childhood Education Lab

CYAF 380 Working with Families in Communities & Schools

CYAF 383 Literacy Methods for Young Children

CYAF 474 Assessment in Early Childhood

SLPA 251 Normal Language Development

SPED 303 Behavior Management

SPED 463 Medically Fragile Infants

Supporting Courses (listed in ACE)

ALEC 102, COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, or COMM 286

EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 203, MATH 208, SOCI 206, or STAT 218

Science course with lab: ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105, CHEM 109; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; GEOG 155; GEOL 101, GEOL 103; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; METR 200; NRES 108; PHYS 141; or TMFD 206

Professional Education Requirements

CYAF 371 Methods of Working with Infants in Programs & Communities

CYAF 371L Working with Infants in Programs & Communities Practicum

CYAF 384 World of Wonder: Math, Science & Nature Integrated Methods Birth to Age 5

CYAF 497A Student Teaching in Early Childhood Education: Preschool

CYAF 497I Student Teaching: Infancy

CYAF 497K Student Teaching: Kindergarten

SPED 362 Early Childhood Special Education

SPED 496Y Early Childhood Special Education Lab

TEAC 310 Educational Program for Kindergarten Children

Student Teaching

CYAF 497A Student Teaching in Early Childhood Education: Preschool

CYAF 497K Student Teaching: Kindergarten

CYAF 497I Student Teaching: Infancy

Pre-Professional Education Requirements

LIBR 110 Introduction to Library Research

CYAF 160 Human Development & the Family

CYAF 170 Introduction to Early Care & Education

CYAF 270 Development of the Preschool Child

CYAF 270L Development of the Preschool Child Lab

CYAF 271 Infancy

CYAF 271L Infancy Lab

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

SPED 201 Introduction to Special Education

TEAC 259 Instructional Technology

TEAC 297A Professional Practicum Experiences II

TEAC 330 Multicultural Education

TEAC 331 School & Society

Suggested electives include: CYAF 495, CYAF 477; ANTH 473; BIOS 232; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; ENVR 201; HORT 200; NRES 220; SOCI 446; SPED 472, SPED 480

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

OTHER

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experiences.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the College supervisor, the student will be removed from the school placement by the Director of Field Experiences. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experiences in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting. The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experiences, and to the Dean of the College.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska, Department of Education. Students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert/ and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more undergraduate degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for or is removed from student teaching. However, there are times when because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Early Childhood Education in Mobile Society

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Early Childhood Education in Mobile Society

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Valerie Wiemeyer

DESCRIPTION

Early Childhood Education in a Mobile Society (ECEMS) will prepare you to work in early childhood settings with young children whose family members are highly mobile. When you complete the program, you will be qualified to work in a variety of programs that offer early care and education for children birth to age 8 and particularly those with highly mobile populations such as military installations.

This is an online program offered as part of the Great Plains Interactive Distance Education Alliance (IDEA). The Great Plains IDEA is a consortium of universities collaborating in the delivery of programs. As a student in this program, you will enroll for all your course work through UNL and you will graduate from UNL, but your online courses will be taught by faculty at each of the participating universities. Core courses (51 credits; identified under the heading ECEMS Requirements below) in this program are subject to differential tuition at the common Great Plains IDEA rate. For 2014-2015, this rate is $370 per credit hour. The Great Plains IDEA rate does not apply to tuition and fees for any remaining credit hours needed to complete the bachelors degree (i.e., ACE requirements, minor and elective requirements).

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

ACE 1. Any ACE 1 Course (Suggested online courses: JGEN 200, JGEN 220, ENGL 151, ENGL 150)

ACE 2. Any ACE 2 Course (Suggested online course: ALEC 102)

ACE 3. Any ACE 3 Course (Suggested online courses: MATH 104, CSCE 101, ECON 215)

ACE 4. Any ACE 4 Course (Suggested online courses: AGRI 115, AGRI 485, AGRO 131)

ACE 5. Any ACE 5 Course (Suggested online courses: ENTO 115, GEOL 125, GPSP 377, ENGL 206, ENGL 215, SPAN 331)

ACE 6. Any ACE 6 Course (Suggested online courses: ANTH 110, ANTH 212, CRIM 101, ECON 211, SOCI 209, SOCI 225, CYAF 160)

ACE 7. Any ACE 7 Course

ACE 8. Any ACE 8 Course (Suggested online courses: ECON 211, WMNS 101, CYAF 150)

ACE 9. Any ACE 9 Course (Suggested online courses: CYAF 495, GPSP 377, GPSP 378, POLS 160, SOCI 200, SOCI 217, ECON 321, ENGL 215, ENGL 245N, SPAN 331, TEAC 330, WMNS 101, WMNS 385)

ACE 10. CYAF 306 ECEMS: Practicum III

ECEMS Requirements: 51 credits

*Students must be admitted into the ECEMS program to take these courses.  Admission requirements:  30 credit hours completed, 2.5 cumulative GPA.

CYAF 203 ECEMS: Child Development, Birth to 3 (3 cr)

CYAF 204 ECEMS: Child Development, 4 to 8 (3 cr)

CYAF 205 ECEMS:  Guidance and Classroom Environments (3 cr)

CYAF 206 ECEMS: Professional Development (3 cr)

CYAF 207 ECEMS: Practicum 1 (3 cr) Prereqs:  CYAF 203, 204, 205, 206

CYAF 208  ECEMS: Administration and Supervision in Early Childhood Settings (3 cr)

CYAF 209  ECEMS: Diversity in the Lives of Young Children and Families (3 cr)

CYAF 212  ECEMS: Health, Safety, and Nutrition (3 cr)

CYAF 213  ECEMS:  Technology and Young Children (3 cr)

CYAF 214  ECEMS: Working with Families (3 cr)

CYAF 301 ECEMS:  Assessing Young Children and Their Environments to Enhance Development (3 cr) Prereq: Practicum I

CYAF 302 ECEMS: Development of Curriculum for Children ages Birth to 3 (3 cr) Prereq: Practicum I

CYAF 303 ECEMS: Development of Curriculum for Children ages 4 to 8 (3 cr) Prereq:  Practicum I

CYAF 304 ECEMS: Young Children with Special Needs (3 cr) Prereq:  Practicum I

CYAF 305 ECEMS: Practicum II (3 cr) Prereq: Practicum I

CYAF 306 Practicum III (6 cr), P/NP Prereq:  Practicum II

Electives/Minor:  39 credits

Criminal History Background Check

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children.  We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with pre-school or with school age youth in pre-schools, schools or in public agency settings, must complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender prior to participating in a field experience.  The student is responsible for the cost of the criminal history review.  If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed.  Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report.  Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience.  This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student's future in the College, and one's ability to find success in their profession.  If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs.  Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program.  From the College's perspective, continued participation in school-based field experiences will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and the Nebraska Department of Education as to how their standards are applied to working with pre-school and school age youth.  If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, the student will be prohibited from participation in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting.  The individual may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgement; and evidence a disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College, may bring into question a student's ability to be successful in their profession.  Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior.  Students must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others.  Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training students who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly.  These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgement of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student's individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program.  More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum or field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter.  The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students' fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the field experience, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination.  The student's written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student's appeal.  The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal.  The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student's education records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information).  The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal.  Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final an not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Criminal History Background Check

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children.  We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with pre-school or with school age youth in pre-schools, schools or in public agency settings, must complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender prior to participating in a field experience.  The student is responsible for the cost of the criminal history review.  If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed.  Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report.  Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience.  This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student's future in the College, and one's ability to find success in their profession.  If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs.  Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program.  From the College's perspective, continued participation in school-based field experiences will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and the Nebraska Department of Education as to how their standards are applied to working with pre-school and school age youth.  If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, the student will be prohibited from participation in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting.  The individual may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgement; and evidence a disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College, may bring into question a student's ability to be successful in their profession.  Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior.  Students must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others.  Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training students who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly.  These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgement of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student's individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program.  More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum or field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter.  The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students' fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the field experience, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination.  The student's written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student's appeal.  The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal.  The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student's education records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information).  The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal.  Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final an not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Economics (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Economics (ASC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: F. Gregory Hayden

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Scott M. Fuess, Jr., 340 College of Business Administration Building

Professors: Allgood, Anderson, Cushing, Edwards, Fuess, Hayden, May, Rosenbaum, Schmidt, van den Berg, Walstad

Associate Professors: Giertz, McGarvey, Thompson

Assistant Professors: Kim

Assistant Professor of Practice: Miller

Economic analysis is useful in many decisions made by individuals, businesses, nonprofit organizations, and governments. In addition to opportunities in teaching, economists are employed in many branches of government and on the staffs of corporations in manufacturing, insurance, banking, brokerage and other financial services. Economists often serve as consultants, either individually or in consulting firms. Todays economists deal with problems ranging from monetary and fiscal policy, monopoly and competition, environmental improvement, labor relations, regional development, urban reconstruction, economic development and international business and finance. Economics is also a popular major for students planning to enter professional and graduate programs, particularly in law, foreign service, labor relations, or business administration.

The department of economics offers the opportunity for intensive study in twelve specialized economic areas:

General Economics and Theory. Develops fundamental reasoning skills and analytical tools necessary to understand and evaluate economic issues such as specialization, trade, efficiency, costs, markets, prices, resource allocation, money, labor, and government and think critically about economic theory and social provisioning.

Comparative International and Regional Development. Examines how human capital, fiscal policy, natural features, and industry clusters influence the comparative advantage, growth, and standard of living in urban and regional economies between and within countries.

Econometrics.

Economic Education.

Economic History. Examines the transformation in economic life that accompanied the rise of market capitalism in the United States and focus on the impact of this transformation on the environment, society, and individuals. Courses in this area are integrative in nature and allow students the opportunity to examine the complex nature of economic development throughout American history.

Industrial Organization and Regulation.

Institutional Economics.

International Trade and Finance. Examines the causes and effects of imports, exports, foreign investment, and migration and their implications for exchange rates, the balance of payments, and economic welfare.

Labor Economics. Focuses on how labor markets function and thus, how wages and employment are determined. The decisions of labor market participants are studied, as are employment practices and public policies related to employment issues.

Monetary Economics. Studies the role of money and banking system, and of Federal Reserves monetary policy in the determination of output, employment, interest rates, prices and business cycles in the domestic and open-economy context.

Public Finance. Survey of taxation and public expenditures in theory and practice. Understanding the logic of collective action, the theory of public goods, social welfare, redistribution and intergovernmental fiscal relations.

Quantitative Economics.

For some careers, study in related areas is advisable. If you're interested in:

Human Resource Management take additional courses in labor economics and economic history
Finance courses in money and banking, intermediate microeconomics, and macroeconomics are helpful
Marketing econometrics courses add to your resume
Accounting econometrics and public finance courses covering taxes are useful

In planning a program of studies, students should consult a faculty adviser or talk to any member of the economics faculty who would be glad to make suggestions about complementary courses.

Many economics courses also satisfy ACE requirements, (see Other.)

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

An economics major must complete 30 credit hours of economics. These 30 hours must include:

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics 3

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ECON 215 Statistics* 3

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics 3

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics 3

Economics 300- or 400-level courses 6

Economics 400-level courses 9

Total 30

*NOTE for economics majors: STAT 218 may be substituted for ECON 215 if STAT 218 was completed before declaring economics as a major; otherwise student must take ECON 215.

Track/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, students majoring in economics may choose to pursue areas of interest in the following disciplines to fulfill requirements for the major. Course options appear under each area.

General Economics and Theory

ECON 389 Current Economic Issues

ECON 413/FINA 413 Social Insurance

ECON 433 History of Economic Thought

ECON 445 Gender, Economics, & Social Provisioning

Comparative International and Regional Development

ECON 322 Introduction to Development Economics

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 340 Introduction to Urban-Regional Economics

ECON 388 Comparative Economic Systems

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 442 Regional Analysis

ECON 466 Pro-seminar in International Relations I

ECON 467 Pro-seminar in International Relations II

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

Econometrics

ECON 417 Introductory Econometrics

Economic Education

(Also see courses in Quantitative Economics)

ECON 450 Economics for Teachers

ECON 451 Economics Issues for Teachers

Economic History

ECON 375 Women & Work in United States History

ECON 457 19th Century United States Economic History

ECON 458 20th Century United States Economic History

Industrial Organization and Regulation

ECON 426 Government Intervention in Markets

ECON 435 Market Competition

Also see the following economics courses:

ECON 457/857 19th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 458/858 20th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 472/872 Efficiency in Government

ECON 487/887 Economies in Transition

ECON 900 Seminar in Economic Theory & Policy

Institutional Economics

ECON 475 Theory & Analysis of Institutional Economics

International Trade and Finance

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics

NOTE: ECON 321 is also an ACE 9 course option and can be taken to fulfill the NBR 6 ACE 9 requirement as well as a course for the major (AND it is also an IBCR).

ECON 421 International Trade

ECON 422 International Finance

For additional courses, see Comparative International & Regional Development

Labor Economics

ECON 381 Introduction to Labor Economics

ECON 481 Economics of the Labor Market

Ace 10 approved.

ECON 482 Labor in the National Economy

Ace 10 approved.

ECON 485 The Regulatory Environment for Employment & Labor

Monetary Economics

ECON 303 An Introduction to Money & Banking

ECON 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

ECON 403 Money & the Financial System

ECON 404 Current Issues in Monetary Economics

Public Finance

ECON 371 Elements of Public Finance

ECON 471 Public Finance

ECON 472 Efficiency in Government

Quantitative Economics

ECON 409 Applied Public Policy Analysis

ECON 416 Statistics for Decision Making

ECON 419 Topics in Applied Research

Also see Econometrics area for additional courses in quantitative economics.

Research and Thesis

Seminar and research courses in specific fields are listed in their respective divisions.

ECON 189H University Honors Seminar

ECON 198 Freshman Seminar

ECON 399 Independent Study

ECON 399H Honors: Independent Study

ECON 499H Honors Thesis

This department participates in the program for Global Studies. For a full description of the program, see Global Studies.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details of these programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin. Refer to the Graduate Studies Bulletin for 800/900-level courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Students are required to complete ECON 211, ECON 212, and ECON 215 before completing additional required economics course work. The completion of BSAD 150 and MATH 104 are required prior to enrollment in ECON 215. We strongly recommend students complete the intermediate theory sequence, ECON 311 and ECON 312, prior to completing elective 300 and 400 level classes.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses for the major, with the exception of ECON 399, must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass). If ECON 399 is taken as Pass/No Pass, it may only be used as an elective.

Course Level Requirement

Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before taking other 300/400-level economics courses.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A: 18 hours of economics course work

Plan B: 12 hours of economics course work

OTHER

All students are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include all requirements for enrollment in 300- or 400-level economics courses.

ECON 211 and ECON 212 Macro- and Microeconomics are ACE 6 and ACE 8 approved course work.

ECON 215 Statistics is an approved ACE 3 course and may be used to fulfill the ACE 3 requirement of the University.

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics is an approved ACE 9 course and while most students will complete ACE 9 during the freshman and sophomore year with other course work, transfer and upper-class students meeting the prerequisite, may wish to take this class.

Electrical Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Electrical Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 125

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Jerry Varner

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jerry L. Hudgins, 209N SEC

Associate Chair: Sohrab Asgarpoor

Professors: Alexander, Asgarpoor, Bahar, Balkir, Boye, Choobineh, Hoffman, Hudgins, Ianno, Lu, Otu, Pérez, Sayood, Schubert, Woollam

Associate Professors: Franke-Shubert, Qiao, Snyder, Vakilzadian, Varner

Assistant Professors: Han, Qu

Research Professor: Patterson

Research Assistant Professors: Hofmann, Psota, Zhou

Senior Lecturer: Bauer

Lecturer: McCreight

Phone: 402-472-3771

Fax: 402-472-4732

Website: http://engineering.unl.edu/academicunits/electricalengineering/

Electrical engineering is concerned with the production, transmission, and utilization of electrical energy and the transmission and processing of information. Employment opportunities for electrical engineers cover a wide spectrum of activities including design, development, research, sales, and management. These activities are carried on in industrial organizations, public and private utilities, the communications and computer industry, governmental and educational institutions, and consulting engineering firms. The objective of this major is to offer students an education to become productive electrical engineers and be active, contributing citizens of the nation and the world.

This department has over 25 faculty involved in research related to electronic materials, nanotechnology, optical systems, communications, biomedical applications, signal processing, microelectronics design, energy systems, and electromagnetics. Students are encouraged to participate in research activities, and have opportunities to travel and present their research results.

The department has extensive research facilities for all areas including state of the art computing facilities, integrated circuits and systems research facilities, communications and signal-processing laboratories, applied electromagnetics research, solid state laboratories, nanostructures research, electro-optics research and energy systems laboratories.

The curriculum is designed to provide a broad education in fundamental principles and laboratory applications, and an awareness of the socioeconomic impact of technology. Technical electives are normally selected from advanced courses in electrical engineering to provide for specialization in selected areas. However, technical electives can also be selected from courses offered by other departments of the College of Engineering or from appropriate physics, chemistry, mathematics, and biological sciences courses.

The department administers a network of high-end UNIX workstations and PCs, upgraded regularly, and used for classroom instruction as well as the individual needs of students.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Requirements for admission to the Department of Electrical Engineering will be granted if he/she has:

1. maintained a cumulative GPA of at least 2.4 and is in good standing in the College of Engineering, and,

2. completed ELEC 215 and ELEC 216 with a grade of C or better.

A transfer student will be admitted if he/she has:

1. completed courses equivalent to ELEC 215 and 216 at other institutions with acceptable transfer grades of C or better, and,

2. a GPA of 2.4 or better during their first 12 credit hours in Electrical Engineering course work at UNL.

Transfer students will be able to appeal to the advisers for admission if they fail to meet the GPA requirement for an additional semester.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree

First Semester Hours

ELEC 121 Introduction to Electrical Engineering I 3

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

Science Elective 4

Choose 4 credit hours of science elective from the following: LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; CHEM 109 or CHEM 111 or CHEM 113; and PHYS 213.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

ELEC 122 Introduction to Electrical Engineering II 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

Computer Programming Elective 3

The recommended computer programming elective is CSCE 155E.

Total 14

Third Semester Hours

ELEC 215 Electronics & Circuits I 3

ELEC 235 Introductory Electrical Lab I 1

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

PHYS 222 General Physics Lab II 1

Communications Elective 3

Choose from JGEN 200, or one of two from JGEN 300 and COMM 286 so as to meet both ACE 1 and 2.

Total 16

Fourth Semester Hours

ELEC 216 Electronics & Circuits II 3

ELEC 222 Introduction to Embedded Systems 3

ELEC 236 Introductory Electrical Lab II 1

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

Science Elective 4

Choose 4 credit hours of science elective from the following: LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; CHEM 109 or CHEM 111 or CHEM 113; and PHYS 213.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Fifth Semester Hours

ELEC 304 Signals & Systems I 3

ELEC 307 Electrical Engineering Lab I 2

ELEC 316 Electronics & Circuits III 3

ELEC 370 Digital Logic Design 3

Technical Elective 3

The department maintains an approved list of technical electives (within and outside of EE) on the department website.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Sixth Semester Hours

ELEC 305 Probability Theory & Introduction to Random Processes 3

ELEC 306 Electromagnetic Field Theory 3

ELEC 317 Electrical Engineering Lab II 2

Technical Electives 6

The department maintains an approved list of technical electives (within and outside of EE) on the department website.

Communications Elective 3

Choose from JGEN 200 or one of two from JGEN 300 and COMM 286 so as to meet both ACE 1 and 2.

Total 17

Seventh Semester Hours

ELEC 494 Electrical Engineering Senior Design I 2

Technical Electives 9

The department maintains an approved list of technical electives (within and outside of EE) on the department website.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 14

Eighth Semester Hours

ELEC 495 Electrical Engineering Senior Design II 3

Technical Electives 9

The department maintains an approved list of technical electives (within and outside of EE) on the department website.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required for Graduation 125

Each EE undergraduate student must choose one of the options listed below for the EE technical electives.

Electrical Engineering Options

1. Communications and Signal Processing

2. Electromagnetic Fields and Optics

3. Electronics and Computer Engineering

4. Energy and Power Systems

5. Materials and Devices

6. Bioengineering

Electives

There are twenty-seven (27) credit hours of technical electives required. Of these 27 credit hours, at least 12 credit hours must be taken in electrical engineering (ELEC) courses which are referred to as “EE technical electives.” Below is a list of courses in each option.

1. Communications & Signal Processing

ELEC 410, ELEC 462, ELEC 463, ELEC 464, ELEC 465

2. Electromagnetic Fields and Optics

ELEC 408, ELEC 467, ELEC 468, ELEC 480, ELEC 486

3. Electronics and Computer Engineering

ELEC 361, ELEC 469, ELEC 470, ELEC 475

4. Energy and Power Systems

ELEC 406, ELEC 428, ELEC 438, ELEC 444

5. Materials and Devices

ELEC 417, ELEC 420, ELEC 421, ELEC 422

6. Bioengineering

ELEC 452, ELEC 460, ELEC 498E, ELEC 498S

Of these 12 credit hours, 6 credit hours must be taken from one of the six EE options listed (including at least one bold course).

In addition, at least one 3 credit hour course from a different EE Option must be taken. The remaining 3 credits may be satisfied by any non-required 300 or 400 level electrical engineering courses except ELEC 399.

The remaining 15 credit hours of technical electives which are referred to as “EE or other technical electives” may be taken from any 300 or 400 level course offering (with the exception of those listed below) in the Department of Electrical Engineering or in any other engineering department within the College of Engineering at UNL, or in the Departments of Biological Sciences, Chemistry, Computer Science and Engineering, Mathematics, Statistics, or Physics and Astronomy at UNL.

Not Allowed 300 and 400 Level Technical Electives

BIOS 310 School of Biological Sciences Seminar

IMSE 305 Introduction to Engineering Management

MATH 495 Seminar

MATH 496 Seminar in Mathematics

In addition, a list of courses at the 100 and 200 level, which also will be accepted as technical elective credits, are listed below.

Allowed 100 and 200 Level Technical Electives

AGEN 225/BSEN 225 Engineering Properties of Biological Materials

ASTR 204 Introduction to Astronomy & Astrophysics

ASTR 224 Astronomy & Astrophysics Lab

BIOS 206 General Genetics

BIOS 213 Human Physiology

CHME 202 Mass & Energy Balances

CHME 331 Equilibrium Stage Operations

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 114 Fundamental Chemistry II

CHEM 2xx Any 200 level chemistry course

CSCE 156 Computer Science II

CSCE 235 Introduction to Discrete Structures

CSCE 251 Unix Programming Environment

MATL 260 Elements of Materials Science

MATL 262 Materials Lab I

MECH 223 Engineering Statics

MECH 250 Mechanics I

MECH 200 Engineering Thermodynamics

No more than a total of 3 credit hours may be taken in ELEC 399 or similar offerings from other departments.

However, students can choose a “Research Option.” The purpose of research option is to provide research experiences and offer opportunities for students to work with a faculty adviser on a specific research topic. A certificate of completion of thesis will be awarded to the students, and outstanding thesis awards will be presented at the end of semester functions. Requirements for the research option are listed below.

Research Option

1. Selection of a faculty adviser (EE department faculty), research topic, and thesis committee (at least one other faculty).

2. Registration for 6 credit hours of undergraduate research (ELEC 399) over at least two consecutive semesters on the same research topic.

3. GPA of above 3.0.

4. Write an undergraduate thesis or report and make an oral presentation to be graded by thesis committee members.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

ELEC 216 – Prereq: A grade of C or better in ELEC 215; Prereq or Parallel: MATH 221 and ELEC 236.

ELEC 304 – Prereq: A grade of C or better in ELEC 216; MATH 221

ELEC 316 – Prereq: A grade of C or better in ELEC 216

ELEC 306 – Prereq: A grade of C or better in ELEC 216; PHYS 212; MATH 221

OTHER:

EE Resource Room/Tutoring

The Department of Electrical Engineering has a resource room staffed by upper class undergraduates and graduate students. Students can get help with their homework, get answers to technical questions, etc. The room is open approximately 20 hours per week. Open hours for each semester are posted outside the room.

A list of tutors is available from the Department of Electrical Engineering, 209N, SEC. At the beginning of each semester students are invited to offer their services through these lists.

Electronics Engineering (Omaha)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Electronics Engineering (Omaha)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Electronics Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 127

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Roger Sash

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Roger Sash, PKI 201E

Professors: Chen, Sharif, Wysocki

Associate Professors: Ci, Jang, Nguyen, Peng, Qian, Sash, Yang

Senior Lecturers: Detloff, Gilmore

Phone: 402-554-2288

FAX: 402-554-2289

Website: http://ceen.unl.edu

Email: rsash1@unl.edu

The electronics engineering program is administered by the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) and the bachelor of science degree program is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

Mission

The mission of the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) at the University of Nebraska is to develop and maintain programs of excellence in teaching and research which meet the educational needs of its constituents, which will support the state of Nebraska in its development as a leading center for high-technology computer/electronics/telecommunications industry and which will support national needs for well-educated computer and electronics engineering professionals.

Program Educational Objectives

The Department’s Program Educational Objectives are a statement of what its graduates are doing or are capable of doing three to five years after graduation. The students in the electronics engineering program receive a strong foundation in engineering science and design that will enable them to pursue productive careers in not only the electronics engineering field, but can also be used as the foundation for careers in other areas such as business, management, and medicine. Typical industries in which the electronics engineering graduate would be employed could include those in communication systems, telecommunication networks, analog systems, hardware/software integration, and digital and microprocessor systems.

The Electronic Engineering program prepares our graduates for their professional career with the objectives that within five years after graduation they will be:

Employed in industry, academia or government
Successful engineers who develop innovative solutions for design and construction of electrical/electronic systems and other applications of modern engineering
Functioning on teams, exhibiting leadership, and making effective contributions to the benefit of their workplace and community
Engaging in postgraduate education or pursuing professional development for continuously renewing and expanding their knowledge base
Performing engineering practice in context that reflects awareness of the ethics of their profession, and of the impacts of their work on the profession and society at large.

These Program Educational Objectives were developed with input from the program’s educational objectives constituency consisting of employers (including CEEN Industry Advisory Board), graduates of the program, and faculty of the department.

Student Outcomes

Student outcomes are those abilities that a graduate of the electronics engineering program will have attained so that he/she can meet the educational objectives established for the program.
At the time of graduation, students in the CEEN Electronics Engineering program will have:

a.    an ability to apply knowledge of mathematics, science, and engineering

b.    an ability to design and conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data

c.    an ability to design a system, component, or process to meet desired needs within realistic constraints such as economic, environmental, social, political, ethical, health and safety, manufacturability, and sustainability

d.    an ability to function on multidisciplinary teams

e.    an ability to identify, formulate, and solve engineering problems

f.    an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility

g.    an ability to communicate effectively

h.    the broad education necessary to understand the impact of engineering solutions in a global, economic, environmental, and societal context

i.    a recognition of the need for, and an ability to engage in life-long learning

j.    a knowledge of contemporary issues

k.    an ability to use the techniques, skills, and modern engineering tools necessary for engineering practice

These program outcomes have been developed with input from the program outcomes constituency group consisting of:

•    Employers (including CEEN Industry Advisory Board)

•    Graduates of the program

•    Faculty of the department

•    Students in the program

The individual holding this degree will have advanced knowledge in his or her field of engineering interest and in addition will have a university educational background involving mathematics, the physical sciences, and the humanities and social sciences. The curriculum has a strong focus in telecommunications engineering. Completion of this program will enable the graduate to enter employment in positions involving telecommunications engineering design, analog circuit design, telecommunications network performance analysis, and technical management of telecommunications networks. The program also leads to the preparation for graduate work in electronics engineering or electrical engineering.

Concentrations

The department offers several areas of concentration so students can attain an in-depth study of a topic in computer engineering or electronics engineering. The electronics engineering concentrations are:

Bioelectronics

Electrical Engineering

Network Security

Robotics and Control

Telecommunications

Wireless Systems

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Typical Schedule

First Semester Hours

CEEN 103 Computer & Electronics Engineering Fundamentals 4

CSCE 155A Computer Science I or 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus 3

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument 3

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CEEN 106 Microprocessor Applications 3

CEEN 225 Computer & Electronics Engineering Seminar 1

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II* 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab I 1

Total 16

*Calculus II is a 5-credit course on the Omaha campus. Students taking Calculus II on the Lincoln campus will need to obtain an additional 1 credit hour of math or science.

Third Semester Hours

CEEN 213 Electrical Circuits I 4

CEEN 218 Electrical Circuits Lab 1

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra (Matrix Theory) 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 15

Fourth Semester Hours

CEEN 214 Electrical Circuits II 3

CEEN 222 Electronic Circuits I 4

JGEN 300 Technical Writing 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

ACE Elective SLO 5 3

Total 17

Fifth Semester Hours

CEEN 328 Applied Fields & Lines I 3

CEEN 352 Electronic Circuits II 4

CEEN 355 Signals & Linear Systems 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications 3

ACE Elective SLO 6 3

Total 16

Sixth Semester Hours

CEEN 313 Switching Circuit Theory 4

CEEN 325 Communications Systems 4

CEEN 361 Data & Telecommunications Transceivers 4

Conc/ENGR Elective 4

Total 16

Seventh Semester Hours

CEEN 496 Senior Thesis Proposal 1

ENGR 469 Tech, Science & Civ (UNO) 3

Conc/ENGR Elective 9

ACE Elective SLO 7 3

Total 16

Eighth Semester Hours

CEEN 499 Senior Thesis 3

Conc/ENGR Elective 6

ACE Elective SLO 8 & 9 6

Total 15

Students must complete one of the electronics engineering concentrations.

Three hours of the engineering electives can be chosen from a list of approved non-CEEN courses.

Total Credit Hours Required 127

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All course work must be of “C” grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

ADMISSION

General Requirements

Advisement

Upon entry into the curriculum, each student will be assigned a faculty academic adviser. It is required that the student meet with the adviser prior to each class registration period and that all courses to be applied toward the degree be selected with the advice and approval of the adviser. Students are expected to have their academic records reviewed and obtain approval from the department prior to application to the University registrar for award of the degree in order to insure that all curricular requirements will be satisfied by the time of intended graduation.

Curriculum

Because of the rapid developments in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering, the curricular requirements are continually reviewed and upgraded to reflect technological advances. Curricular sequence and course descriptions contained herein are intended to serve as general guidelines. Contact the department for information on any changes to the requirements that are currently in effect but not listed in this catalog. Currently enrolled students are expected to modify their programs to take advantage of such revisions. Students who do not maintain continuous progress toward the degree through enrollment in applicable course work will be considered as new students upon reentering the computer or electronics engineering curricular sequence and will be subject to the requirements of the curriculum current at the time of their reentry. Certain courses may not be valid as prerequisites or as credit toward the degree after two academic years; the student’s academic adviser should be consulted regarding applicability.

The department maintains a high standard of excellence in meeting its objective of providing the student with extensive experience in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. The development of both hardware and software and the knowledge of the interrelationship of these areas is enhanced through the extensive use of laboratory equipment. The applicable University bulletins and College academic policies must be followed to ensure that the student satisfies the campus general education requirements.

Senior Thesis

The capstone senior thesis requirement provides a unique and challenging opportunity for the undergraduate student to demonstrate his/her ability to apply the knowledge gained in the course work sequence to the planning, design, execution, testing and reporting of a significant project in the applications of engineering principles. The initiative and responsibility expected of the student executing the senior thesis parallel the expectations of the employer of the program graduate.

Electives

Computer engineering and electronic engineering courses which are described in the catalog but are not shown as requirements in the semester sequences are offered as the need arises to provide co-interest areas wherein the students may broaden their background in the applications of computer engineering or electronics engineering. In addition, appropriate specified technical electives will be selected to augment the student’s particular area of interest. The applicability of transfer course work with engineering content toward credit in the curriculum is determined on a case-by-case basis by the department.

Special Interest Areas

Opportunities are provided for the development of areas of special interest through enrollment in the Individual Study in Computer and Electronics Engineering courses which are offered at the freshman through senior level for the student who may wish to develop a topic under the guidance of a department faculty member. Enrollment is by permission after the department chair has approved a written proposal. Special Topics in Computer and Electronics Engineering classes also are offered by the department as the need arises to cover topics needing emphasis as a result of the rapidly developing fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. Academic advisers should be consulted regarding the particular topics to be covered and the necessary prerequisites for each offering of this course.

Students who expect to continue their education at the graduate level after the award of the baccalaureate degree should consult their adviser regarding course selections that would enhance that objective.

Students are encouraged to develop their professional and leadership potential through participation in student chapters of related professional organizations and in University extracurricular activities. Participation in the University Honors Program is encouraged for those who qualify.

Elementary Education (K-6) & Early Education (Age 3-Grade 3)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Elementary Education (K-6) & Early Education (Age 3-Grade 3)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 141-144

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Val Wiemeyer

DESCRIPTION

Students who complete this field endorsement may teach children in all elementary subjects in kindergarten through grade 6, in all schools. They may also teach in grades 7 and 8 in self-contained classrooms. Self-contained classrooms exist when students spend more than half the school day with one teacher who provides instruction in more than half of the academic areas of the curriculum. They will also have an emphasis in early childhood education. This program requires course work beyond a single endorsement and therefore exceeds 120 hours.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the teacher education curriculum and must be successfully completed. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Criminal History Background Check Requirement” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements (or majors) are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

ADMISSION

All education programs have a competitive admission process. At some point in time, after meeting specific education requirements, all students must formally apply to their particular education program.

Pre-Education Status

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program are classified as pre-education students until admitted to a specific Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Students must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the Teacher Education Program:

1. A minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

2. Must have earned a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit.

3. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program Application Form.

4. Completion of TEAC 331 and EDPS 251 or an approved transfer course, (must be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP) with a 2.5 cumulative average in the two classes, and no grade lower than C; TEAC 259 (must also be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP).

5. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of the Praxis I, Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST) or CORE examination which is expected to replace the PPST, fall 2014, as the basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

6. Successful completion of TEAC 297A practicum and one course in communication studies selected from COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, or ALEC 102.

7. Completion of a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

8. Specific programs may have particular learning outcomes that students must address as part of the application process.

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 116 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience for an entire semester. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a specific teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.75 on a 4.0 scale.

4. Minimum grade point average of 2.5 in the endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. All endorsement, pre-professional and professional education course work must be completed prior to student teaching. If necessary, no more than 6 hours of general education (ACE) or elective classes can be completed after the student teaching experience.

7. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester unless prior approval is obtained from the Certification Officer, the Director of Field Experience, or the Department Chair that oversees the program.

8. Completion of a second criminal history check that will be conducted, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required). For more information, contact the Director of Field Experience or your adviser.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

ACE 1. ENGL 101, ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254 3

ACE 2. COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, ALEC 102 (Pre-Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 3. MATH 203, STAT 218 3

ACE 4. ASTR 103, GEOL 106, GEOL 109, GEOL 115, METR 140, NRES 108 3

ACE 5. ENGL 230A, ENGL 231, ENGL 260, ENGL 261, ENGL 305A 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. TEAC 331 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 9. TEAC 330 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 10. TEAC 403A (Professional Education Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Education Requirements 9

TEAC 259A 2

TEAC 297A 2

TEAC 380 2

CYAF 380 3

ELED Endorsement Requirements 16

Select one course: ENGL 216, ENGL 244, ENGL 244A, ENGL 244E or ENGL 245A, ENGL 245J, ENGL 245N or ENGL 344B, ENGL 344D or ENGL 345D 3

Select one course: TEAC 213, TEAC 413A, TEAC 436, TEAC 438, TEAC 441, TEAC 446, TEAC 490, EDPS 251, ENGL 210 3

Select one course: GEOG 140, GEOG 271, GEOG 272, POLS 100 3

Select one course: HIST 100, HIST 101, HIST 110, HIST 111, HIST 171 3

Select one course: BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L, CHEM 105, CHEM 109; GEOL 101, GEOL 103, METR 200, ENTO 115 & ENTO 116, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262, PHYS 261 & PHYS 262 4

Early Childhood Requirements 20

CYAF 210 & 210L 4

CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L 3

CYAF 374 & 374L 4

TEAC 410 & CYAF 474 (3 hrs ea) 6

CYAF 383 or 384 3

Professional Education Requirements 63

TEAC 297B, TEAC 317, & TEAC 351 (2 hrs ea) 6

TEAC 259B & TEAC 297E (1 hr ea) 2

TEAC 302, TEAC 305, TEAC 307, TEAC 308, TEAC 311, TEAC 313, TEAC 315, & TEAC 397A (3 hrs ea) 24

MATH 300 & MATH 302 (3 hrs ea) 6

SPED 401A 3

SPED 415/SPED 415A 4

TEAC 497A 9

CYAF 497A 9

Electives 0

Total Hours 138

NOTE: All courses must be a C or above. All methods courses must be a C+ or above.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experience.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, or the College supervisor, the student will be removed from the school placement by the Director of Field Experience. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experience in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting. The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experience, and to the Dean of the College.

Praxis II

All students completing a program leading to a teaching certificate with an endorsement in elementary grades (grades K-6) will be required to take the EECIA-00011 version of Praxis II before graduation. Test completion will be documented through official test score results.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska, Department of Education. Students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert/ and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more undergraduate degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for teacher certification (GWC).  In order to qualify for GWC a student must have senior class standing and be within two semesters of student teaching.  In addition the student:

1. must be unable to qualify for student teaching based on grades or other performance-based issues, or

2. be removed from student teaching, or

3. because of illness or other unusual situations, decides not to complete or is unable to complete all of the professional requirements in a teacher education program.

If a student is unable to meet all of the requirements as described in the “Admission to Student Teaching” section, such as minimum course grade requirements for courses in the professional education sequence or in one’s content area, but still earns passing grades in those courses while maintaining the grade point average minimums, then the student may be eligible to GWC.

To apply for GWC, the student should contact his or her adviser, meet with the College’s Certification Officer, and then submit a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all remaining content area and professional education requirements except student teaching. The requirements include passing grades in all remaining courses while maintaining the minimum grade point averages as specified in the “Admission to Student Teaching.” If a student begins student teaching but fails to complete at least one half of the assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours. The student must still meet the ACE 10 general education requirement. Contact your adviser or the Certification Officer to make sure that this requirement is satisfied.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for pre-school or school aged youth, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. In addition, the Department of Health and Human Services has created its own set of standards that apply to all individuals working in any capacity with pre-school children who are not yet in kindergarten. To comply with these two sets of standards, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. This must be completed before one’s first field experience. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process, culminating experience, or internship. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed. Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student’s future in the College and one’s ability to find success in the profession of education. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after either background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one’s criminal history can lead to removal from the program. A student’s ability to continue to participate in any teacher education program in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and/or the Nebraska Department of Education standards as they apply to working with pre-school and school age youth.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action including possible removal from the program. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Energy Science Minor

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Energy Science Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER:

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Adam Liska, 203 Chase Hall

Professors: Fulginiti, Hay, Markwell, Perrin

Website: http://energysciences.unl.edu

The energy science minor is designed to offer an educational component to University of Nebraska students that will prepare them with the knowledge, expertise, and background to successfully compete for positions with companies that are producing or developing renewable energy sources or conventional fossil fuels sources or with organizations that manage energy use or the environmental impacts of energy use. The minor is for students who desire a broad understanding of energy-related issues and an in-depth knowledge of energy in one or more of four elective thematic areas as well as for those seeking employment in agriculture, business/industry, communication, transportation, and government.

Courses of Instruction (ENSC)

Courses suitable for automatic inclusion in one of the four elective thematic areas have been identified and can be viewed at the website http://energysciences.unl.edu/tracks. Any of the above ENSC courses can be taken independently as desired by any student.

A student in consultation with an academic adviser will submit a "College-Degree-Major-Adviser Change Form" (CDMA) declaring their intent to complete the minor before the deadline for submitting the application for graduation. The degree audit system of the University Registrar will evaluate whether the appropriate courses have been taken for completion of the minor. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation.

Courses suitable for automatic inclusion in one of the four elective thematic areas have been identified and can be viewed at the website http://energysciences.unl.edu/tracks. Any of the above ENSC courses can be taken independently as desired by any student.

A student in consultation with an academic adviser will submit a "College-Degree-Major-Adviser Change Form" (CDMA) declaring their intent to complete the minor before the deadline for submitting the application for graduation. The degree audit system of the University Registrar will evaluate whether the appropriate courses have been taken for completion of the minor. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

A minor in energy science (ENSC) will include a minimum of 18 credit hours of energy-related courses including four core courses.

Core Courses 10

ENSC 110 Energy in Perspective 3

ENSC 220 Introduction to Energy Systems 3

ENSC 230 Energy & the Environment: Economics & Policy 3

ENSC 300 Energy Science Seminar 1

The remaining energy-related courses must come from one or more of the four elective thematic tracks

Energy and Natural Resources
Plant and Animal Bioenergy
Energy Engineering
Energy Economics, Policy, and Human Dimensions

or be approved by the student’s academic adviser and the minor coordinator.

Additionally, optional courses for elective credit include:

ENSC 499H Honors Thesis (3 cr)

ENSC 496 Independent Study in Energy Science (1 cr), or

ENSC 311 Energy Science Study Tour (1 cr)

At least 6 credit hours must be at the 300 or 400 level and up to 3 hours of energy-related independent study course work or Honors thesis may be included.

Engineering Mechanics Minor

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Engineering Mechanics (Minor only)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 12

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

This minor is for engineering majors ONLY.

The College of Engineering enables its students to participate in this approved minor subject to the following conditions:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor must be approved by the adviser, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor.

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “Plan A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “Plan A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “Plan A” or “Plan B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added by approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A Minor. 12 credit hours beyond the regular undergraduate engineering mechanics sequence (MECH 223, MECH 325, MECH 373 or MECH 250, MECH 351). These may be chosen from 300- and 400-level courses offered by engineering mechanics, excluding those courses required in the student’s curriculum by the major department.

Family Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Family Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE:

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

Family Science provides a comprehensive program grounded in family science theory, research, and professional practice and application for individuals to work with children and families. This career path provides students with knowledge and intervention skills that will assist them in helping to prevent and remedy interpersonal problems experienced by individuals in their family relationships, building on the family’s strengths. In addition, Family Science will prepare students for graduate school (e.g. family science, family therapy, social work, counseling psychology, and law), or for employment in human services agencies or programs.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Program Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30-34

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. ALEC 102, COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, COMM 286 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 3. ECON 215, EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 108H, MATH 203, MATH 208, STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 4. ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 113; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; GEOG 155; GEOL 101, GEOL 103; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; METR 100; NRES 108; PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 151 & PHYS 153, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262, TMFD 206 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. CYAF 150 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 9. CYAF 495 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 497D (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

Supporting Courses 1

LIBR 110 1

CYAF Core Requirements 18-19

CYAF 222, CYAF 280, CYAF 285 or CYAF 382, CYAF 380, CYAF 488 (3 hr ea) 15

Human Development 3-4

Select one: CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L, CYAF 271 & CYAF 271L, CYAF 372; GERO 200, GERO 307, GERO 446, GERO 447; EDPS 250, EDPS 251, EDPS 450, EDPS 451; PSYC 289, PSYC 446, PSYC 489

Option Area: Choose either Option A or Option B 18-23

Option A – Human and Community Services 18

CYAF 333 (3 hrs)

CYAF 446 or CYAF 458 (3 hrs)

CYAF 471 (3 hrs)

Select one: PSYC 380, SLPA 150, SPED 201 (3 hrs)

Select one: CYAF 416, EDAD 421, EDAD 422, EDPS 362 (3 hrs)

Select one: CYAF 285, CYAF 322, CYAF 382, CYAF 446, CYAF 458, CYAF 493 (3 hrs)

Option B – Family Science Research 21-23

Students must have a 3.0 GPA for this option.

CYAF 333 (3 hrs)

CYAF 446 or CYAF 458 (3 hrs)

CYAF 471 (3 hrs)

CYAF 498 (3 hrs) Research UCARE, REU, Non-UCARE Research Experience in Child, Youth & Family Studies

Select one: PSYC 380, SLPA 150, or SPED 201 (3 hrs)

Select either: PSYC 350 & PSYC 450 or SOCI 205 & SOCI 206 (6-8 hrs)

Minor Requirements 18

Approved minors: Anthropology, communication studies, education, gerontology, global studies, leadership and communications, psychology or sociology

Electives 25-35

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All CYAF courses must be taken for a grade (not Pass/No Pass).

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for pre-school or school aged youth, are all keenly attuned to the safety of children. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. In addition, the Department of Health and Human Services has created its own set of standards that apply to all individuals working in any capacity with pre-school children who are not yet in kindergarten. To comply with these two sets of standards, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. This must be completed before one’s first field experience. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process, culminating experience, or internship. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. If more than three years elapse after the initial background check is conducted, the College reserves the right to require that one or more additional background checks be completed. Eighteen months after the initial Criminal History Background Check, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time the initial background check is conducted.

If a student has any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, the student will be contacted by the College and may be required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the charge or conviction on the student’s future in the College and one’s ability to find success in the profession of education.If any new charges or convictions are acquired after either background check, the student is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one’s criminal history can lead to removal from the program. A student’s ability to continue to participate in any teacher education program in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recentness of their occurrence, and whether or not they are in violation of the requirements of the Department of Health and Human Services and/or the Nebraska Department of Education standards as they apply to working with pre-school and school age youth.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action including possible removal from the program. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In addition to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Finance

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Finance

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (24-30 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for CBA students only

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Manferd Peterson

Professors: DeFusco, Farrell, Geppert, Karels, Peterson

Associate Professors: Dudney, Friesen, Lin, Unlu

Assistant Professors: Murray, Nikolova

Associate Professor of Practice: Vagts

Assistant Professor of Practice: Williams

The goal of any financial system is to allocate monetary resources to those individuals, companies and governmental units that have the best ideas for usage. The study of finance focuses on the organization and development of capital markets and financial institutions in achieving the optimal usage of funds. As a finance student, you might want to examine how conflict of interest affects managerial performance, how risk influences investment decisions, or how investor psychology can impact the price of stocks and bonds. The finance faculty offer strong support for the exploration of such topics and the curriculum is designed to prepare students in areas of high employment demand.

A solid understanding of the finance role is becoming ever more essential in the management of public, private, and nonprofit organizations. The basic course, FINA 361 (required of all students in the College), presents the institutional background, theory, and decision-making skills essential to an understanding of the corporate finance function. The major theoretical issues and the financial techniques that are used to analyze capital management problems are investigated.

The department also offers a course in personal finance, FINA 260, that exposes students to basic financial concepts such as personal taxes, investment opportunities, insurance issues and retirement planning. The personal finance course is open to all university students and has no prerequisites. Successful completion of FINA 260 satisfies ACE Outcome 6 in the University’s general education requirements.

The finance major offers course work in the following areas of specialization:

Banking and Financial Institutions

Risk Management and Insurance

CFA® – Investments

General Finance

Finance students must declare one of these specializations as a formal option within their major. Multiple options cannot be chosen.

The finance department faculty hold student advising sessions every semester to discuss course offerings and curriculum requirements. Students are highly encouraged to attend these sessions and to meet with their CBA advisers on a regular basis. The department chair is also available to answer questions regarding the selection of courses or other questions related to the finance curriculum.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements. However, the CFA option in the finance major does require a separate application. This can be found on the department’s Web page.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 24-30 hours of course work for the major.
All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take FINA 361 as part of the Business Core Intermediate requirements.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
Exception: FINA 97 for the CFA option which is 0 credit hours, Pass/No Pass.
Course work for the major must be selected from the approved list of courses.
FINA 399/FINA 499 may NOT be counted toward the major, options, or minor.
Required core finance courses cannot be counted as course work in the options.
ALL majors must take an International Business Course requirement and while this can be part of the major for those pursuing the General Finance Option, all other options will need to work this requirement into their ELECTIVE section of the program.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in finance will complete 12 hours of core finance courses and complete one finance option consisting of 12-18 hours to meet the requirements for Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M).

Required core finance courses (12 hours):

FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

FINA 365 Financial Institutions & Markets (ECON 365) Can double count toward ECON minor if pursuing finance major.

FINA 461 Advanced Finance

The non-core course work is organized around the following options consisting of another 12-18 hours:

Finance students must declare one of these specializations as a formal option within their major. Multiple options cannot be chosen.
Banking and Financial Institutions
Risk Management and Insurance
CFA® – Investments
General Finance

The Banking and Financial Institutions Option is designed for students wishing to prepare for a career in the financial services industry. Course work emphasizes the decisions that financial managers make. The role of both bank and non-bank institutions in economic growth and development are examined. Designated scholarships for study of this option are available and internship opportunities are supported and encouraged.

Banking and Financial Institutions Option (15 hours)

FINA 260 Personal Finance or AECN 495A Internship in Agricultural Financing & Banking

FINA 307 Principles of Individual Risk Management & Insurance or FINA 382 Real Estate Principles & Practice

FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis or ACCT 313 & ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting I & II

FINA 412 Life & Health Insurance or FINA 482 Real Estate Finance or FINA 450 International Finance

FINA 465 Bank Management

Students pursuing the Banking and Financial Institutions Option may count one of their 300/400-level requirements for the finance major toward fulfilling 3 hours of the 12 hour 300/400-level elective requirement; or may count two if AECN 495A is taken.

The Risk Management and Insurance Option focuses on the study of methods used to manage activities whose outcome cannot be forecast with certainty. Individuals and organizations utilize risk management tools to reduce the uncertainty of achieving specific goals and targets. Risk management has become a central management function applicable to every area of management specialization.

Risk Management and Insurance Option (15 hours)

FINA 307 Principles of Individual Risk Management & Insurance

FINA 438 Enterprise Risk Management

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities

Choose two additional courses from the following, one of which must be FINA 412 or FINA 413 :

FINA 412 Life & Health Insurance

FINA 413 Social Insurance

FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis

FINA 450 International Financial Management

FINA 463 Security Analysis & Warren Buffett Business Valuation Techniques

MNGT 437 Computer-Aided Analysis in Decision Making

Students pursuing the Risk Management and Insurance Option may count two of their 300/400-level requirements for the finance major toward fulfilling 6 hours of the 12 hour 300/400-level elective requirement.

The CFA® – Investments Option is a technical program designed to immerse students in the art and science of the management of financial assets. UNL’s finance department is a CFA® Program Partner and the course material covered in this option meets the requirements of the Chartered Financial Analysts Program Partnership. A year-long portfolio management course with students investing real dollar funds is a part of this curriculum. Students completing this option would be expected to sit for the Level I, CFA exam.

CFA® – Investments Option (18 hours)

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting I

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities

FINA 468 Portfolio Practicum I

FINA 469 Portfolio Practicum II

FINA 482 Real Estate Finance

FINA 97 Ethics Assessment

Students pursuing the CFA® – Investments Option may count three of their 300/400-level requirements for the finance major toward fulfilling 9 hours of the 12 hour 300/400-level elective requirement.

Students pursuing this option and selecting an accounting minor may double count their ACCT course work for the minor and finance major.

Students who only take FINA 468 may count that towards the General Finance Option.

The General Finance Option allows a student to pursue a broad range of interests in the finance field. Students can select from courses in Real Estate, International Finance, Insurance, and Investments. A solid understanding of the basic finance function is provided with this option that prepares students for entry-level positions in the management and operation of public, private, and nonprofit financial organizations.

General Finance Option (12 hours)

Select 3 hours from:

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis

6 hours of 300/400-level finance courses

3 hours of 400-level finance courses

Students pursuing the General Finance Option may count one of their 300/400-level requirements for the finance major toward fulfilling 3 hours of the 12 hour 300/400-level elective requirement.

Students pursuing this option and selecting an accounting or economics major/minor may double count their ACCT or ECON course work.

Minor Requirements

Finance majors are encouraged to minor (or double major) in accounting or economics. The finance department does not prohibit the double-counting of hours used to obtain a minor or double major. Many actuarial science majors also choose to double major with finance. Requirements appear under actuarial science. Courses that might be double counted include: ACCT 308, ACCT 313, ACCT 314, FINA 365/ECON 365, ECON 311, ECON 312, and FINA 413/ECON 413.

Electives

See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

Students considering graduate work in business are encouraged to take MATH 106 instead of MATH 104. Additional course work in mathematics is strongly encouraged.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in most upper-level finance courses usually requires completion of FINA 361 as well as other prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as the College grade rules.

If selecting ACCT 308, ACCT 313, and/or ACCT 314, prerequisites require a grade of C in previous ACCT courses:

ACCT 308 requires a grade of C in ACCT 201 and ACCT 202

ACCT 313 requires a grade of C in ACCT 201 and ACCT 202

ACCT 314 requires a grade of C in ACCT 313

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Finance Minor

The finance minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Finance course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-C) degree requirements, for another major, or any other business minor requirements.
All course work for the minor must be taken for a grade.
FINA 399/ FINA 499 may NOT be used toward the minor.
To fulfill the requirements for a finance minor, students must complete 12 hours of the following:
FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management or FINA 363 Investment Principles
FINA 365 Financial Institutions & Markets
3 hours of 300/400-level finance course work
3 hours of 400-level finance course work

Geology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Geology

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Richard Kettler

DESCRIPTION

Chair: David Watkins, 214 Bessey

Professors: Fielding, Frank, Fritz, Goble, Grew, Harwood, Holmes, Hu, Joeckel, Loope, Oglesby, Pederson, Rowe, Watkins, Zlotnik

Associate Professors: Anderson, Houston, Kettler, Rack, Wang

Assistant Professors: Arthurs, Bathke, Burberry, Gates, Head, Secord, Weber

The Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences offers a variety of courses leading to the bachelor of arts and bachelor of science degrees in geology and the bachelor of science degree in meteorology-climatology.

Graduate Work. The Department of Geosciences offers the master of sciences, and doctor of philosophy degrees. For details see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Major in Geology

The Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences offers both the bachelor of science and the bachelor of arts degrees in geology. The bachelor of science program is designed for those who expect to continue in graduate work and become professional geoscientists. Undergraduate training in geology is beneficial in many other fields such as teaching at the precollege level, urban planning, law, civil engineering, environmental studies, and museum work. Students preparing for these or similar areas are advised to take the bachelor of arts program, which is strong in fundamental geology but does not provide the ancillary requirements for admission for most graduate study in geology.

Field Trips. Many of the geology courses require field trips that often include camping and primitive conditions. The number of trips and their duration are a function of the requirements of the particular course.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Bachelor of Science

The following curriculum, leading to the bachelor of science degree, is recommended as a minimum program for the pre-professional geologist. All candidates for this degree are required to attend a field camp.

The major must include 30 hours in eight courses (GEOL 101, GEOL 103, GEOL 210, GEOL 211, GEOL 310, GEOL 340, GEOL 410, and GEOL 460). An additional 12 credit hours must be acceptable electives above the 100 level, with at least one course at the 400 level. Acceptable electives include any GEOL courses at the 200, 300 or 400 level as well as METR 200 or METR 370.

No minor is required, however the student must complete a set of ancillary science and math requirements totaling 30 credit hours. These must include MATH 106 and MATH 107, CHEM 109 or CHEM 113, and PHYS 141 and PHYS 142 or equivalents. The additional 6 required credit hours in science and math must consist of courses from the following list:

ASTR 204

BIOS 101/BIOS 101L, BIOS 109, BIOS 112 & BIOS 112L, BIOS 206, LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L

CHEM 110 or CHEM 114, CHEM 116 or CHEM 221, (CHEM 251 and CHEM 253) or (CHEM 261 and CHEM 263), CHEM 471

MATH 208, MATH 221, MATH 380

STAT 218

PHYS 311, PHYS 343

A candidate for the bachelor of science in geology should complete, by the end of the sophomore year, MATH 107; CHEM 113 (or equivalent) and GEOL 210, GEOL 211. By the end of the junior year the student should also have completed GEOL 310 and the physics requirement. GEOL 460 is to be taken between the junior and senior years.

Bachelor of Arts

The bachelor of arts program consists of the college comprehensive education requirements with at least one semester of chemistry and MATH 102 or MATH 103, plus a minimum of 30 hours in geology including GEOL 101, GEOL 103, GEOL 210, GEOL 211, GEOL 310, and GEOL 340. Remaining credits in geology may include only 4 hours at the 100 level.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required:

1. To maintain and submit a portfolio of material produced for the required Summer Field Course, GEOL 460 (for BS students), or for the required Depositional Environments course, GEOL 310 (for BA students). Course instructors will inform students of the required contents, deadlines and procedures.

2. In their final semester, to participate in an exit interview/survey. The undergraduate adviser will inform students of the scheduling and format of their assessment activity.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Professional Geologist Emphasis. Over 30 U.S. and Canadian states and provinces, including Nebraska, require geologists whose work affects public health and safety to obtain a professional license. Students wishing to pursue professional licensure should take the required core courses as well as GEOL 488. Recommended electives include GEOL 450, GEOL 470, GEOL 472, and GEOL 485.

Sedimentology Emphasis. Students pursuing this emphasis should choose four electives from the following: GEOL 414, GEOL 420, GEOL 421, GEOL 450, GEOL 485.

Paleontology and Earth Systems Emphasis. Students pursuing this emphasis should choose four electives from the following: GEOL 417, GEOL 423, GEOL 424, GEOL 430, GEOL 431, GEOL 435.

Hydrological Sciences Emphasis. Students pursuing this emphasis should choose four electives from the following: GEOL 417, GEOL 418, GEOL 450, GEOL 465, GEOL 470, GEOL 472, GEOL 488.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students majoring in geology may not take major courses for Pass/No Pass credit (possible exceptions are independent study and hours in excess of those required for the major). Majors may take up to 6 hours Pass/No Pass in their minor(s), subject to the approval of the department(s) granting the minor(s). Students minoring in geology may take up to 6 hours Pass/No Pass subject to the approval of the department granting the major. To secure the necessary approval, students may obtain request forms from the Arts & Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

22 hours with only 8 hrs at the 100 level.

Global Security Studies Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Global Security Studies (Minor only)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

chief adviser: Patrice McMahon

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Patrice McMahon (political science)

Faculty: Krone (communication studies), McMahan (political science), Minter (English), Narumalani (geography/School of Natural Resources), Thomas (history), White (political science)

The undergraduate global security studies minor (GSST) is an interdisciplinary program that provides undergraduates across campus (any department or college) with relevant knowledge of various aspects of global security and the theory and analytical skills necessary for dealing with global security studies issues. Students interested in global security issues, security-related job opportunities, or a desire to have a set of analytical skills relevant to global issues will benefit from the GSST. Students who have completed the GSST requirements will, upon graduation, receive a minor in global security studies.

The minor requires 18 credit hours of course work with a grade of B- or better, a 3 credit hour capstone course (GSST 475) and an experiential learning internship (variable 1-3 credit hours) for a total of 22-24 credit hours.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Undergraduate Global Security Studies Minor (22-24 hours)

Four principles train students to analyze systematically and coherently global security issues, develop writing and critical thinking skills, negotiate multiple and competing interests, and develop in-depth knowledge and application in substantive international policy issue(s). Certain special topics courses not listed below that have a significant global security component may also be eligible for inclusion in a student’s minor program plan. Approval of chief adviser is required to include courses not listed below.

Hours

1. CORE Courses 6

Cover the theories, processes, models, and methods of global security studies and security policy analysis.

POLS 160 International Relations 3

POLS 261 Conflict & Conflict Resolution or POLS 263 Causes of War & Peace 3

2. Writing and Analysis Courses 6

Develop writing and critical thinking/analysis skills that are relevant to the intelligence community. Choose two of the following – one course from Writing and one course from Critical Thinking/Analysis for a total of 6 hours. No more than 3 hours of courses taken to meet any degree requirement may be used to meet the Rhetoric and Analysis requirements of 6 hours for the Global Security Studies minor.

Writing 3

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument

JOUR 102 The Art of Writing

JOUR 444 Science Writing

Critical Thinking/Analysis 3

COMM 210 Communicating in Small Groups

COMM 211 Intercultural Communication

COMM 212 Debate

COMM 312 Argumentation

PHIL 220 Elements of Ethics

PHIL 221 Political Philosophy

PHIL 265 Philosophy of Religion

PSYC 350 Research Methods & Data Analysis

SOCI 205 Introduction to Social Research I

SOCI 206 Introduction to Social Research II

3. Specialization 6

Students will develop a plan of study in consultation with the global security studies minor coordinator. Courses will be selected from the areas below. (6 hours or two courses within a specialization are required. Students are responsible for checking and meeting prerequisites to some of the courses.)

Area A: Political/Economics

POLS 362 Globalization, Human Rights, & Diversity

POLS 470 International Human Rights

POLS 472 State Terror

POLS 476 Ethnic Conflict & Identity

HIST 303 US Military History, 1607-1917

POLS 363 USA Foreign Policy

POLS 463 American Foreign Policy & the Use of the Military

GEOG 447 Political Geography

POLS 462 Security in the Post-Cold War Era

HIST 479/POLS 466 Pro-seminar in International Relations I

POLS 479 Insurgency, Guerilla Warfare, & Terrorism

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics

ECON 388 Comparative Economic Systems

ECON 421 International Trade

ECON 422 International Finance

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

POLS 272 Non-Western Politics

POLS 274 Developmental Politics in East Asia

POLS 275 Post-Communist Politics & Change

POLS 277 Latin American Politics

POLS 281 Challenges to the State

HIST 326 Algeria & France

POLS 372 Russian Politics

POLS 376 Chinese Politics

Area B: Cultural

HIST 181/POLS 171 Introduction to East Asian Civilization

HIST 214 History of Islam

HIST 326 Algeria & France

HIST 429 History of Fascism in Europe

HIST 466 Early Modern China

HIST 467 History of China in the 20th Century

HIST 480 The Social & Economic History of China since the Late Ming Era

RELG 108 World Religions

RELG 181 Judaism, Christianity & Islam

RELG 208 Introduction to Islam

RELG 217 Israel: The Holy Land

RELG 318 Islam in the Modern World

RELG 418 Fundamentalism, Religion & Politics

SOCI 452 Sociology of Religion

ANTH 353 Anthropology of War

ANTH 366 Peoples & Cultures of East Asia

ANTH 420 Ethnic Identity & Ethnic Conflict

COMM 312 Argumentation

COMM 371 Communication in Negotiation & Conflict Resolution

COMM 375 Theories of Persuasion

COMM 487 Global Organizational Communication

Area C: Languages

(Students may choose courses based on fluency level and input from the GSST adviser).

Arabic

ARAB 101 Beginning Arabic I

ARAB 102 Beginning Arabic II

ARAB 201* Second-Year Arabic I

ARAB 202* Second-year Arabic II

Chinese

CHIN 101 Beginning Chinese I

CHIN 102 Beginning Chinese II

CHIN 201 Second-Year Chinese I

CHIN 202 Second-Year Chinese II

CHIN 303 Third Year Chinese

CHIN 304 Advanced Conversation & Composition Chinese

Russian

RUSS 101 Beginning Russian I

RUSS 102 Beginning Russian II

RUSS 201 Second-Year Russian I

RUSS 202 Second-Year Russian II

RUSS 203 Composition & Conversation I

RUSS 204 Composition & Conversation II

RUSS 303 Advanced Conversation & Composition: Russian Language through the Russian Press

RUSS 304 Advanced Composition, Grammar, & Conversation

Area D: Scientific/Technical

GEOG 217 Mapping Science in the 21st Century

GEOG 312 Introduction to Geospatial Information Sciences

GEOG 412 Introduction to Geographic Information Systems

GEOG 418 Introduction to Remote Sensing

GEOG 420 Digital Image Analysis of Remote Sensing Data

GEOG 444 Geo-demographics & GIS

4. Capstone Course and Experiential Learning: 6

Global Experience; study abroad, internship, fieldwork. Students will take a one-semester global securities capstone course (GSST 475) followed by one of two options: 1) a study abroad and/or internship experience; or 2) a summer study-abroad experience. The global experience occurs after completing or during the last semester of course work for the GSST. The global security studies minor coordinator will help students find an appropriate study abroad or internship experience. Academic requirements for the internship will be set by the GSST adviser and it is preferred that this experience be in the student’s area of expertise or associated with the language area of specialization (AREA C). Students must complete a report associated with their global experience.

GSST 475 Threats & Solutions to Global Security in the 21st Century

Students must meet with the GSST coordinator to set up a plan of study. For more information or to enroll in the minor program, contact Tyler White, Department of Political Science, 509 Oldfather Hall, 402-472-9443. Email: twhite4@unl.edu.

Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management (CEHS)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management (CEHS)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts in Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Cameya Ramirez-Rousseau

DESCRIPTION

This program integrates leadership, communications and financial management into a curriculum focused on managing facilities and operations that provide hospitality services to the public. As part of the program, students also complete the Leadership and Communications minor offered by the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR). The Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management Program (HRTM) prepares individuals to serve as entry level managers and directors of hospitality operations by providing an excellent foundation in hospitality, leadership, and guest services.

ADMISSION

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

ACE 1.                                                                                                            3

ACE 2.                                                                                                            3

ACE 3.                                                                                                            3

ACE 4.                                                                                                            3

ACE 5.                                                                                                            3

ACE 6.                                                                                                            3

ACE 7.                                                                                                            3

ACE 8.                                                                                                            3

ACE 9.                                                                                                            3

ACE 10.          HRTM 479                                                                               3

HRTM Core Requirements45-48

ACCT 201 or **ACCT 200                                                                           3

AGRI 103/NRES 103                                                                                                3

**ECON 200 or ECON 211 & ECON 212                                                   3-6

EDPS 209                                                                                                       3

HRTM 171 & HRTM 172 & HRTM 397 (1 hr ea)                                        3

HRTM 310 & HRTM 360 or MRKT 341 or **MRKT 300 (3 hrs ea)          6

HRTM 374, HRTM 476, HRTM 483 or **FINA 300 (3 hrs ea)                  9

Select two courses from the following:                                                            6

HRTM 274, HRTM 280, HRTM 285, HRTM 289

Select one course from the following:                                                             3

HRTM 481, **BLAW 300, BLAW 371, BLAW 372, AECN 256, AECN 357

Select one course from the following:                                                             3

HORT 200, HORT 261, TMFD 121

Select one course from the following:                                                             3

JGEN 120, JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Leadership & Communications Minor                                                       18

Select three courses from the following:                                                          9

ALEC 102, ALEC 202, ALEC 302, ALEC 305

Select three courses from the following:                                                          9

ALEC 337, ALEC 388, ALEC 407, ALEC 410, ALEC 414, ALEC 466, ALEC 477, ALEC 488, AERO 331 or AERO 332 (May be substituted for Air Force ROTC student only)

HRTM Professional Electives                                                                                  21

Select 21 hours from the following. Must fulfill prereqs; no substitutions.

AECN/EAEP 225 or AECN 376 (3 hrs)

ALEC 428/NRES 428 (3 hrs)

CRPL 400 or CRPL 420 or CRPL 480 (3 hrs)

EAEP 101 (1 hr)

EAEP 121 (3 hrs)

EAEP 288A (2 hrs)

EAEP 321 (3 hrs)

EAEP 421 (3 hrs)

EAEP 488 (3 hrs)

ENTR 322 (hrs)

ENTR 422A (3 hrs)

ENTR 291 or **FINA 300 or FINA 307 or HORT 489 (3 hrs)

HRTM 373, HRTM 472, HRTM 474, HRTM 477, HRTM 478, HRTM 484, HRTM 485, HRTM 489, or HRTM 495 (1-6 cr) (3 hrs)

HRTM 296, HRTM 396, or HRTM 496 (1-3 hrs)

HRTM 291 or HRTM 391 (1-6 hrs)

**MNGT 300, MNGT 320, MNGT 361, or MNGT 365 (3 hrs)

NUTR 343, NUTR 372, or HORT/NUTR/HRTM 471 (3 hrs)

 Electives                                                                                                                     3-6

 Total Hours                                                                                                                120

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

NOTE: Students have the option to complete the Business Minor for Non-Business students offered through the College of Business Administration. Courses that meet this requirement are identified with (**). A Change of College, Degree, Major and/or Adviser (CDMA) form will need to be filled out in order to add the minor to the student’s degree audit. The CDMA form can be filled out in the CEHS Advising Center. All business classes must be taken for grade.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The College of Education and Human Sciences offers an 19 hour minor in Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management for students in CASNR and the CEHS Departments of Child, Youth and Family; Nutrition and Health Sciences; and Textile, Merchandising and Fashion Design.

Requirements

All grades must be a C or above.

Required 1 hour:

HRTM 171 Career Exploration in Hospitality Management

Select 6 hours:

HRTM 274 Introduction to Food & Beverage Management

HRTM 280 Introduction to Tourism

HRTM 285 Introduction to the Lodging Industry

HRTM 289 Introduction to the Event Industry

Select 12 hours:

HRTM 360 Hospitality & Tourism Marketing

HRTM 373 Catering

HRTM 374 Guest Services Management

HRTM 472 Fine Food & Wine

HRTM 474 Food & Beverage Management

HRTM 477 Hospitality Facility Planning & Purchasing

HRTM 478 Tourism Resources & Development

HRTM 481 Legal Environment in Hospitality Management

HRTM 484 Human Resources in the Hospitality Industry

HRTM 485 Advanced Lodging Operations

HRTM 489 Advanced Event Operations

HRTM 495 Hospitality Management Study Tour

HRTM 471 Vines, Wine & You

Individualized Program of Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Individualized Program of Studies

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Arts & Sciences Advising Center

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall

The College of Arts and Sciences major or minor in Individualized Program of Studies allows a student to design an academic program to pursue a special interest not covered by the established majors or minors offered by the College. A proposal must be interdisciplinary, (that is, come from more than one department), and center on a clearly defined problem area, a defined body of thought, a specific area of interest, or a specific educational goal. The program is not intended to allow students to graduate without concentrating their thoughts in some clearly defined pattern. Students intending to pursue graduate work should be sure that this particular program will meet admission requirements. Students also should be sure that the University has the resources (faculty interest and expertise) to support the anticipated Individualized Program of Studies major. Each major or minor is essentially “custom-made” to meet specific individual needs. However, the following list of titles of approved programs gives an idea of some of the opportunities: biomedical illustration, adolescent studies, language studies, neuroscience and behavior, and hospital administration.

Students with interests or educational objectives that cannot be met by a traditional major or minor, span more than one of the College’s traditional departmental divisions, and whose interests and objectives can be expressed in terms of some defined problem area or topic are encouraged to consider this major or minor option. For more information, interested students should contact the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Procedure. An Individualized Program of Studies form and information sheet is available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall, along with advisers who can answer general questions about the process and program.  The student must find a faculty member from the core department in Arts and Sciences to act as the adviser. The student and the academic adviser are responsible for coordinating the program with other concerned departments. The proposal, with a title, description and justification for the topic, must be approved and signed by the student, adviser and the core department chair before being turned into the Arts and Sciences Advising Center for final review by the College Curriculum and Advising Committee. The program must be approved by the College Curriculum and Advising Committee before the student completes 90 of the 120 applicable hours toward the degree.

NOTE: Individualized Program of Studies (IPS) is a major or minor. Therefore, all other University and College degree requirements must be fulfilled in addition to the IPS.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

1. Selection of at least 48 hours of courses from at least two Arts and Sciences departments representing an integrated study of some area, topic, or problem.

2. A Core Department: At least 15 of the 48 or more hours must be in the College of Arts and Sciences department of the supporting Advisr.

3. At least half of the 48 hours (24 hours) must be from departments in the College of Arts and Sciences. Courses outside the College of Arts and Sciences may be applied to the 48 hours when they contribute directly and necessarily to the program.

4. The Program must be approved by the College Curriculum and Advising Committee before the student completes 90 of the 120 applicable hours toward the degree.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

A maximum of 6 hours of Pass/No Pass (P/N) credit is allowed in courses taken to fulfill the requirements of the major or the minor.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

1. Selection of at least 24 hours of courses from at least two Arts and Sciences departments representing an integrated study of some area, topic, or problem.

2. A Core Department: At least 9 of the 24 or more hours must be in the College of Arts and Sciences department of the supporting Adviser.

3. At least half of the 24 hours (12 hours) must be from the College of Arts and Sciences. Courses outside the College of Arts and Sciences may be applied to the 24 hours when they contribute directly and necessarily to the program.

4. The Program must be approved by the College Curriculum and Advising Committee before the student completes 90 of the 120 applicable hours toward the degree.

Pass/No Pass. A maximum of 6 hours of Pass/No Pass (P/N) credit is allowed in courses taken to fulfill the requirements of the major or the minor.

Insect Science

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Insect Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Insect Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Tiffany Heng-Moss

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Professor Tiffany Heng-Moss, 105A Entomology Hall, thengmoss2@unl.edu

Website: http://entomology.unl.edu/insect_science/index.shtml

The field of insect science encompasses the agricultural, biological, and environmental sciences related to insects and their interactions with humans. Insects and their relatives are the most abundant animals on earth, are commonly found in all habitats, and are essential in maintaining our ecosystem. Insect Science offers numerous career opportunities in both basic and applied fields.

The core curriculum provides students with a balanced education focusing on insect identification, biology, structure and function, behavior, ecology, and diversity, as well as courses in mathematics, science, and the humanities. In addition to the core, there are two options from which students can select an area of focus which meets their own interest and career objectives.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

The following basic courses are required for majors in insect science. In addition, students must select and meet the requirements of one of the options, depending on their own individual interests and career objectives.

The minimum requirements of CASNR reflect the common core of courses that apply to students pursuing degrees in the college. Students should work with an adviser to satisfy ACE outcomes 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 10 with the college requirements.

College Integrative Course 6

AGRI 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems (NRES 103) 3

ENTO 485 Current Issues in Entomology (ACE 10) 3

Departmental Requirements 8

ENTO 115 Insect Biology (BIOS 115) 3

ENTO 116 Insect Identification (BIOS 116) 1

ENTO 400 Biology & Classification of Insects 4

Experiential Learning for Career Development in Insect Science 5

Select from the following four categories: Maximum of 3 hours from any one category.

ENTO 309 Career Experience

ENTO 395A Research Experience (Arranged through adviser)

ENTO 395B Teaching Experience (Arranged through adviser)

ENTO 395E Extension Experience (Arranged through adviser)

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) (ACE 3) 5

Select from: MATH 102, MATH 103, MATH 104, MATH 106, or STAT 218

NOTE: Proficiency at the college algebra level must be demonstrated either by a placement exam or through course work. If MATH 103 is taken, only 2 cr hrs can be counted toward this requirement.

Communication 6

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 120, JGEN 200

Communications and Interpersonal Skills (ACE 2) 3

Select from: ALEC 102; COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 286, JGEN 300

Natural Sciences 12

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (ACE 4) 4

Select from: BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L or LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I 4

BIOS 206 General Genetics or AGRO 315 Genetics 4

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 15

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Total Major Requirements 57

Option Requirements 42-44

Free Electives 19-21

Total Minimum Requirements for Graduation 120

IPM and Pest Science Option

The IPM and Pest Science Option is designed for students considering careers in agriculture, agribusiness, consulting (agricultural, environmental, public health, urban), extension, state and federal government agencies (e.g., APHIS, EPA, USDA, and state departments of agriculture), horticulture, the military, food processing, and pest control. Examples of areas of focus include agronomic and horticultural pests, or urban pests. This option is also suitable as preparation for graduate studies leading to academic or research careers in applied entomology.

Departmental Courses 19-21

ENTO 300 Toxins in the Environment (BIOS 300/NRES 300) 3

ENTO 401 Insect Physiology 3

ENTO 406 Insect Ecology (BIOS 406) 3

ENTO 412 Entomology & Pest Management 3

Select three of the following courses: 7-9

ENTO 109 Beekeeping (2 cr)

ENTO 403 Management of Horticultural Crop Insects (3 cr)

ENTO 308 Management of Field Crop Insects (3 cr)

ENTO 409 Insect Control by Host-Plant Resistance (2 cr)

ENTO 415 Medical Entomology (3 cr)

Other Courses 23

AGRI 115 Biotechnology: Food, Health, & Environment (LIFE 115) 3

AGRO 153 Soil Resources (HORT 153/SOIL 153) 4

AGRO 426 Invasive Plants (HORT 426/NRES 426) 3

NRES 211 Introduction to Conservation Biology 3

NRES 220 & NRES 222 Principles of Ecology & Lab (BIOS 220 & BIOS 222) 4

PLPT 270 Biological Invaders (AGRO 270/HORT 270/NRES 270) 3

PLPT 369 Introductory Plant Pathology (BIOS 369) 3

Total Option Requirements 42-44

Science Option

The Insect Science Option is designed for students interested in careers focusing on the basic biology of insects and other arthropods. This option is suitable for students considering any career involving entomology (e.g., academia, research, medicine, forensics, environmental quality, conservation biology, or health-related fields), but is especially appropriate preparation for entry into professional programs such as veterinary and medical schools and with many graduate school disciplines. Students pursuing this option must choose LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L and BIOS 206 in meeting the entomology degree requirements in life sciences. Completion of the Insect Science Option will also fulfill requirements for a minor in biological sciences.

Departmental Courses 12

ENTO 401 Insect Physiology 3

ENTO 406 Insect Ecology (BIOS 406) 3

Entomology Elective 6

Select from any ENTO course beyond those meeting other major requirements.

Other Courses 30-31

AGRI 115 Biotechnology: Food, Health & Environment (LIFE 115) 3

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab 4

BIOS 205 Genetics, Molecular & Cellular Biology Lab 2

BIOS 207 Ecology & Evolution 4

Biological Sciences Electives 2

Select from any BIOS/LIFE course beyond those meeting other major requirements.

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab 4

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II 4

CHEM 251 Organic Chemistry I 3

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I (5 cr) or PHYS 151 Elements of Physics (4 cr) 4-5

Total Option Requirements 42-43

Students interested in graduate or professional schools in biology, medicine, or veterinary science should take:

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

An additional PHYS course and lab 5

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Insect Science Minor

A minor in insect science will consist of at least 18 credit hours of entomology including at least 6 hours at the 300 level or above. BIOS 381 Invertebrate Zoology, and up to 3 hours of ENTO 496 Independent Study in Entomology, may be counted towards the minor requirements. The course of study leading to a minor in insect science must be developed in consultation with, and be approved by, an adviser in the Department of Entomology. Advisers for the minor are assigned by the Head of the Department of Entomology.

Interdisciplinary Studies

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Interdisciplinary Studies

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

DESCRIPTION

Intended for students seeking advanced levels of scholarship, this specialized course of study leads to a bachelor of arts degree. It allows a student, with the supervision and approval of an academic adviser, to design an academic program that differs from the established majors offered by the College. The degree program must be based on a clearly defined problem area, a defined body of thought, or a specific educational goal. Courses outside the College may be used, however, all College requirements (including the ACE requirements) must be fulfilled. (See graduation and degree requirements below.)

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical & Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Library 110 1

Major Area of Study 51

Electives 32-38

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Students must be admitted as a major into one of the academic units and successfully complete one year of the home unit’s core curriculum before applying for entrance into the Interdisciplinary Studies program. A listing of the required courses is available in each academic unit’s administrative office.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Student must submit a memorandum of courses that includes a minimum of 51 credits in the proposed major. These courses should be anchored in one area of study, with at least 24 credits of the 51 coming from one department. The remaining 30 credits can come from an assortment of subjects to reach the intended goals of the student. A limit of 12 credits of independent study courses may be applied toward the major. Additionally, at least 30 credits of the proposal must be at the 300/400-level

Minor Requirements

A minor is allowed, but not required.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Students are required to complete a minimum of 45 credit hours of their proposed course work at UNL after being admitted to the program.

Grade Rules

Maximum 6 hrs of Pass/No Pass courses

Course Level Requirement

Minimum 30 hrs at the 300/400 level

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules

Maximum 12 hrs of independent study courses

Interior Design

COLLEGE: Architecture

MAJOR: Interior Design

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Design

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISERS: Betsy Gabb (pre-interior design); Assigned Faculty (interior design)

DESCRIPTION

Program Director: Betsy Gabb, 232 Architecture Hall

Professors: Gabb, Hinchman

Associate Professors: Allisma, Ellsworth-Bahe

Chief Advisers: Pre-Interior Design: Betsy Gabb (bgabb1@unl.edu); Interior Design: Assigned Faculty

The College of Architecture also administers the interior design program. The four-year interior design program consists of a one-year pre-interior design program and a subsequent three-year bachelor of science in design (BSD-Interior Design) major. After completing a one-year curriculum in pre-interior design, students apply for admission into the College of Architecture’s interior design program. This interior design program is fully accredited by the Council Interior Design Accreditation (CIDA). The interior design program also offers a post-professional MS degree through the Graduate College. The graduate degree is also available through On-line and Distance Education.

This four-year, undergraduate program is for the student interested in becoming a professional interior designer. The professional interior designer is a person qualified by education, experience, and examination to 1) identify, research, and creatively explore issues related to the quality of the interior environment; 2) perform design services in interior spaces, including programming, design analysis, space planning and aesthetics, using specialized knowledge of interior construction, building systems and components, building codes, equipment materials and furnishings; and 3) prepare drawings and documents describing the design of interior spaces in order to enhance and protect the health, safety, and welfare of the public.

Upon successful completion of one year of pre-interior design studies and admission to the interior design program, students in the interior design program may enroll in the curriculum which leads to a bachelor of science in design (BSD-Interior Design) degree.

Common First Year

The Common First Year engages and prepares students for exciting futures in all design fields within the College of Architecture.

The Common First Year curriculum offered by the College of Architecture, introduces students to design through courses in three areas: Technique (drawing and computer applications), Design Discipline (an introduction to the related design disciplines and design history), and Design Practice (design Thinking and design Making). In addition, students take University courses in math, English, communications, and a general education elective. dThink and dMake are sequential hands-on courses where students learn to work in teams to address problems and promote innovation. At the same time, they learn the foundational skills in composition, craft, presentation, and idea generation necessary for all design fields.

At the end of the Common First Year, students have gained an understanding of the broad range of design and are eligible to apply to any of the design programs in the College—Architecture, Landscape Architecture, Interior Design, and Industrial Design (pending program approval).

ADMISSION

Admission to the Bachelor of Science in Design Program–Interior Design

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the interior design program, applicants must:

1. Be enrolled in the College of Architecture

2. Be in good scholastic standing

3. Have completed the appropriate 1st year pre-architecture, pre-interior design, or pre-landscape architecture program of study

Second Year Admission Process

1. An application for admission may be completed by filling out the online application. The program receives applications once a year on March 1.

2. Applicants must submit a portfolio conforming to the defined criteria for the program applied for by the date posted at the completion of the spring semester.

3. Any applicant who has previously applied for admission and has not been accepted or who fails to enroll in the professional program in architecture or the interior design program after an acceptance must reapply in the regular manner. Students may apply for admission to the interior design program only three times.

Evaluation

The faculty of the interior design program will carefully evaluate the applications for admission. The committee considers three elements in their evaluation: cumulative grade point average, a weighted grade point average, and the portfolio of student work. The weighted grade point average gives additional value to the applicant’s achievement in the required DSGN prefix course or transfer equivalents in the pre-professional curriculum.

Selection

Admission to the interior design program will be awarded to applicants who show the greatest professional potential and have demonstrated scholastic achievement. The faculty reserves the right to not fill all available spaces in the professional program in the interior design program if determined that the remaining applicants have not performed at an acceptable level.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Pre-Interior Design Curriculum

The pre-interior design curriculum begins with a one-year design core. This core introduces students to the fundamentals of design thinking and design making. The pre-interior design program is followed by three years of interior design instruction leading to a bachelor of science in design–interior design. The interior design program is fully accredited by the Council for Interior Design Accreditation (CIDA).

The College of Architecture, and all four years of the interior design program, are located in Lincoln. However, we do offer the option to do the first year of the program at UNO. After successfully completing the prescribed pre-interior design program at UNO, students may transfer to UNL and apply for admission to the second year of study in the professional program of the Interior Design Program. For more information about courses at UNO, or transferring from UNO to UNL, please contact Dr. Betsy Gabb at 402-472-9245 (UNL) or Leslie Brehm at 402-472-4065.

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: Common First Year, First Semester

DSGN 101 Introduction to Design 2

DSGN 110 Design Thinking (ACE 7) 3

DSGN 120 Design Drawing 3

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 Composition Elective (ACE 1) 3

ACE 6 Elective 3

Total 14

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: Common First Year, Second Semester

DSGN 140 History of Design 3

DSGN 111 Design Making 4

DSGN 123 Computer Applications in Design 3

MATH 104 Calculus for Managerial & Social Sciences 3

Communication Elective: COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (ACE 2) 3

Total 16

INTERIOR DESIGN: Second Year, First Semester

ARCH 241 Architecture History & Theory II 3

IDES 210 Design Studio I 5

IDES 300 Systems I 3

IDES XXX (new course to be developed) Systems II 3

Total 14

INTERIOR DESIGN: Second Year, Second Semester

AHIS 101 Introduction to Art History & Criticism I 3

IDES 211 Design Studio II 5

IDES 334 Building Environmental Technical Systems III 3

Behavior Elective: ARCH 456 Behavioral & Social Factors in Environmental Design 3

Natural Sciences Elective (ACE 4) 4

Total 17

INTERIOR DESIGN: Third Year, First Semester

IDES 301 Material Applications 3

IDES 350 Interior Design Studio III 5

IDES 433 Interior Construction Documents 3

IDES 445 History of Interiors & Designed Objects (ACE 5 or 7) 3

Total 14

INTERIOR DESIGN: Third Year, Second Semester

IDES XXX (new course to be developed) Evidence Based Design 3

IDES 351 Interior Design Studio IV 5

Professional Elective 3

ACE 8 Elective 3

Total 17

INTERIOR DESIGN: Summer Session (Between 3rd & 4th Year)

IDES 491 Selected Topics in Interior Design: Interior Design Internship 3

INTERIOR DESIGN: Fourth Year, First Semester

IDES 318 Professional Practices for Interior Design 3

IDES 450 Interior Design Studio V 5

IDES XXX (new course to be developed) Community Engagement 2

Professional Elective 3

Total 13

INTERIOR DESIGN: Fourth Year, Second Semester

IDES 451 Interior Design Studio VI 6

Professional Elective 3

ACE 9 Elective 3

Total 12

Total for Graduation 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, DSGN, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

GPA Requirements

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The standard rises to a grade point average of 2.6 in the second year. Admission into the third year of both programs requires a cumulative grade point average of 2.6. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Third and Fourth Year, Interior Design and Landscape Architecture

Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to maintain a 2.6 cumulative grade point average to remain in good academic standing. The program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Product Design Minor

Program Director and Chief Adviser: Betsy Gabb, 232 Architecture Hall

Faculty: Allisma, Ellsworth-Bahe, Hinchman, Saroka, Day (architecture), Ford (architecture), Hardy (architecture), Hemsath (architecture), Hoistad (architecture), Kuska (architecture), D. Jones (engineering), Pinnell (art)

Product Design

The common core of courses shared by students in the College of Architecture (interior design, architecture, landscape architecture) provides students with an understanding of the design and fabrication process at a range of scales. The minor in product design provides an opportunity to explore design at a smaller, yet related scale. It allows students to develop academic strengths that will prepare them for advanced study and careers in the design of objects that people interact with on a personal level, of a size and function related to human dimensions. This includes furniture and a variety of manufactured objects.

The minor is available to students in interior design, architecture, landscape architecture, and art.

Requirements for the Minor (18 credits)

Hours

A minimum of 12 hours of course work to include the following:

GRPH 221 Building Graphic Design 3

IDES 301 Material Applications 3

IDES 417 Product Design 3

MECH 370 Manufacturing Methods & Processes 3

6 credits of additional course work to be selected from:

ARCH 418 Fabrication & Construction Team 1-6

ARCH 516 Modern Craft 3

ARCH 526 Digital Fabrication 3

IDES 482 Advanced Color Theory 3

IDES 484 Material Culture: The Social Life of Things 3

IDES 491 Selected Topics in Interior Design: Branding 3

IDES Signage & Wayfinding (course to be developed) 3

International Business

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: International Business

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (36 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes-for CBA students only

CHIEF ADVISER: D'vee Buss

DESCRIPTION

Students in international business study the business practices of other nations and learn how international trade laws affect the world economy. A background in international business will help students become a better member of the management team of any corporation. From banks to manufacturing firms, an increasing number of industries need professionals who understand the world’s business environment. Import and export firms, agricultural commodities firms, and government and non-government agencies may specifically seek international expertise. It is suggested that students begin thinking about where they want to study abroad and their language and culture courses during the freshman year. Upper-level course work and education abroad experience will be done sometime in the junior or senior year.

Because the nature of the major requires studying abroad and careful selection of course work to complement and count for appropriate requirements, students are strongly encouraged to consult with their adviser or a staff member in the Undergraduate Programs Office.

In order for students to be successful in international business after graduation, they should plan to do the following as part of their university experience:

Internships related to international business
Involvement with international student groups
Language study
Courses that will provide them with greater awareness and knowledge of global issues
Education abroad experiences

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 36 hours of course work for the major.
Course work for the major must be selected from the approved list of courses.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
No course work for this major may be double counted with any other business major or minor.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in international business will complete 36 hours of course work in three components consisting of:

(1) General Business Requirements (24 hours)

Students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in International Business are to complete 24 hours of 300/400-level business course work for the Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M) to be selected from course work offered by:

Accounting
Economics
Finance
Management or Supply Chain Management
Marketing

As part of the 24 hour requirement:

Course work must be from the 300/400-level with the 300-level course work selected from the following approved list.
A MINIMUM of 3 hours from each of five departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 6 hours from each of three departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 9 hours must be taken at the 400 level.
Departmental 399/499s (unless an honors thesis) may NOT be used toward the major.

Accounting:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II

Any 400-level accounting course work

Economics:

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics

Any 400-level economics course work

Finance:

FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

FINA 365/ECON 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

Any 400-level finance or actuarial science course work

Management:

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communication, & Teams

MNGT 321/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations

MNGT 361 Human Resource Management

SCMS 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models

Any 400-level management or supply chain management course work

Marketing:

MRKT 346/SCMS 346 Marketing Channels Management

MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy

MRKT 345 Market Research

MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems

MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics

Any 400-level marketing course work

Additional Restrictions:

Students who earn BSAD 491 (6 hrs) from the Senshu (Japan) study abroad program may substitute 6 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in two of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA China study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA CIMBA (Italy) study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

(2) International Business course work (12 hours)

In addition to the 24 hours identified above, students will complete 12 hours of international business course work. These 12 hours must come from at least two departments. All courses for the 12 hours must be from the Approved International Business Course List found in this Bulletin.

The 12 hours of ‘international business course work’ are SEPARATE from the 24 hours of 300/400-level general business course work (listed above) and these hours cannot be ‘double counted’ between both components. However, there can be double counting between the NBR 6/ACE 9 requirement where, if taken, MNGT 414 or ECON 321 may be used both in the ACE requirement and for the major.

Approved International Business Course List (12 hours):

BSAD 491 International Studies in Business & Economics (1-15 hrs) (This is a credit option for students studying abroad for course work with no direct business equivalency. Pre-approval for credit required.)

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for ACE 9.)

ECON 421 International Trade (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 421 and AECN 420)

ECON 422 International Finance

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 466 & ECON 467 Pro-Seminar in International Relations I & II (Credit option for students participating in the Nebraska at Oxford Program.)

FINA 450 International Financial Management

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for ACE 9.)

MNGT 459/SCMS 459 Global Information Systems

MRKT 453 International Marketing (prerequisite requires completion of 6 hours of MRKT course work)

SCMS 439 Global Sourcing & Distribution

Although the following courses may also be used to fulfill requirements in the international business major/minor/IBCR, students should be aware that they are not necessarily offered on a consistent basis. (None of these courses were offered in the 2011-12 AY.)

ECON 322 Intro to Development Economics (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 322 and AECN 367)

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 388 Comparative Economic Systems

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

(3) Education Abroad

In addition to completing course work required for the major, students majoring in International Business are also required to participate in a UNL sponsored education abroad experience.

This must be completed while in college.
A MINIMUM of 3 hours of UNL sponsored or approved education abroad credit must be achieved as part of the education abroad experience. If approved, these hours may fit towards the major, minors or other degree requirements.
International students must study in a country other than the U.S. or their home country.

(4) Additional Studies (optional)

While not required, students majoring in international business who wish to seek opportunities for employment abroad should develop a plan early to potentially include the following:

a. Develop a plan of study beginning the freshman year to include Global Studies/International course work as part of the ACE (Achievement Center Education) requirements and other degree program requirements where appropriate;

b. Develop fluency in a minimum of one language other than their native language;

c. International-related internships, international-related volunteer experiences; language partner relationships;

d. Additional education abroad experiences;

e. Conduct research and develop connections with internationally-focused businesses.

Minor Requirements

While not required, students should consider a minor in language and/or consider options in other departments related to the country of interest (i.e., history, political science, global studies, Asian studies, ethnic or European studies, Latin American studies, etc.)

Refer to Arts and Science minors for options and requirements which may compliment the geographical area and/or language of interest.
Those interested in pursuing a language minor may be able to double count NBR 4–Ace 5. Students will need to compare the requirements for their minor with the ACE course list to determine applicability.
In any of these instances, credit hours count only ONCE; student still needs 120 hours for the degree.
Be sure to distinguish differences between Plan A & Plan B minors (as Plan A requires completion of only ONE minor, while Plan B requires completion of an additional minor).

Electives

See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in most upper-level business courses usually requires completion of an introductory course in that major area as well as other prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions EARLY in the program to plan for completion of specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

Enrollment in language courses above the 101 level requires appropriate placement on the Modern Language Placement exam.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

International Business Minor

The international business minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M, BCA-A) degree requirements, for another major, nor any other business minor requirements.
ECON 321 and MNGT 414 can count for minor AND NBR 6–ACE 9 “IF” not being used for another major.
All course work for the minor must be taken for a grade.
Departmental 399/499’s may NOT be used toward the minor.
To fulfill the requirements for an international business minor, students must complete 12 hours from those courses listed under the Approved Business Courses.
In addition to completing course work required for the minor, students are required to participate in a UNL sponsored study abroad experience or a study abroad experience resulting in UNL transfer credit.

Approved International Business Course List (12 hours):

BSAD 491 International Studies in Business & Economics (1-15 hrs) (This is a credit option for students studying abroad for course work with no direct business equivalency. Pre-approval for credit required.)

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for ACE 9.)

ECON 421 International Trade (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 421 and AECN 420)

ECON 422 International Finance

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 466 & ECON 467 Pro-Seminar in International Relations I & II (Credit option for students participating in the Nebraska at Oxford Program.)

FINA 450 International Financial Management

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for the major and ACE 9.)

MNGT 459/SCMS 459 Global Information Systems

SCMS 439 Global Sourcing & Distribution

MRKT 453 International Marketing (prerequisite requires completion of 6 hours of MRKT course work)

Although the following courses may also be used to fulfill requirements in the international business major/minor/IBCR, students should be aware that they are not necessarily offered on a consistent basis.

ECON 322 Introduction to Development Economics (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 322 and AECN 367)

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 388 Comparative Economics Systems

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

Management

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (21 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for CBA students only

CHIEF ADVISER: Gwendolyn M. Combs

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Gwendolyn M. Combs

Professors: Duchon, Luthans, Olson, Plowman, Schniederjans, Uhl-Bien, Welbourne

Associate Professors: Combs, Sebora, Swenseth, Trimi

Assistant Professors: Batur, Chakrabarty, Harms, Pieper, Thornton, Titus, Tuggle, Yu

Associate Professor of Practice: Jones

Assistant Professor of Practice: Nelson, Ibrayeva

A major in management at the University of Nebraska equips students with the essential skills to effectively manage people and resources in today’s business systems and organizational structures. Our management curriculum prepares students for careers in leadership and supervision of employees in the workplace, starting up and managing a business, and utilizing the critical role of information in strategy and operations of the business world.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take the following courses as part of the Business Core Intermediate Requirements:
MNGT 331 Operations & Supply Chain Management
MNGT 350 Intro to Management Information Systems
MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations

and for the Business Core Advanced Capstone requirement:

MNGT 475 Business Policies & Strategies
NONE of these courses may be used to count toward the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
MNGT 398, MNGT 399 may not count toward the major or minor in management.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the management major. Students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in management will complete 9 hours of core management courses and one management Option consisting of four courses (12 credit hours) to meet the requirements for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M).

Required Management Courses (9 hours):

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications, & Teams

MNGT 321/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations

MNGT 361 Human Resource Management

The management major offers course work in the following Options of specialization:

Human Resource Management
Entrepreneurship and Innovation
Leadership in Organizations
General Management

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Management majors must declare one of these specializations as a formal Option within their major. Multiple options may not be chosen.

OPTION: Human Resource Management

Required Courses:

MNGT 461 Strategic Human Resource Management

MNGT 463 Compensation Administration

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

MNGT 466 The Regulatory Environment for Employment & Labor

Students pursuing the Human Resource Management Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context

ECON 481 Economics of the Labor Market

OPTION: Entrepreneurship and Innovation

Required Courses:

MNGT 421/ENTR 421 Initiating & Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

MNGT 422/ENTR 422 Managing Rapid Growth & Change in Organizations

MNGT 423/ENTR 423 Business Plan Development & Decision Making

One course from the following list:

MNGT/ENTR 322 Family Business

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MRKT 345 Market Research

Students pursuing the Entrepreneurship and Innovation Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

MRKT 345 Market Research

OPTION: Leadership in Organizations

Required Courses:

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 413 Building Ethical & Sustainable Organizations

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context

Students pursuing the Leadership in Organizations Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 421/ENTR 421 Initiating & Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

MNGT 422 Managing Rapid Growth & Change in Organizations

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

SCMS 436 Project Management

OPTION: General Management

This Option is open to students who do not wish to specialize in one of the specified Options of the management major. In addition to the three core courses for the management Option, students must take 12 additional hours (four courses): three of these courses must be selected from the management options (Human Resource Management, Leadership, and Entrepreneurship, and one elective from the management or supply chain management systems course offerings.

Required Courses - 12 hours (four courses)

Select one course from each Option:

Human Resource Management

Entrepreneurship and Innovation

Leadership in Organizations

Select one elective from the management or supply chain management systems course offerings.

(NOTE: SCMS courses that are cross-listed with MRKT are not allowed in this requirement.)

Students pursuing the General Management Option may select from the course bulletin to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

Additional restrictions beyond those noted per individual courses above include:

NBR 6–ACE 9 – MNGT 365 or MNGT 414 can be double counted to fulfill NBR 6–ACE 9 AND course work for the major.
MNGT 414 may also be counted for the IBCR.
In any option where double counting is permitted, only 3 hours of credit are used; students must still meet the 120 hour requirement for the degree.
In any option where double counting is permitted for NBR requirements and the major, course work cannot, in turn, be used for any minor.
MNGT 121/ENTR 121, MNGT 331, MNGT 350/SCMS 350, MNGT 360, MNGT 398, MNGT 399 (Independent Study), and MNGT 475 may NOT be counted toward the major.
BSAD 491 may count for a maximum of 3 hours credit, only for those students who take it as part of the Nebraska at China Education Abroad Program or the Senshu University Program, or for a transfer course from an international institution for which ‘management-related’ course work was done, evaluated, and approved for credit toward the major.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College Grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

MNGT 475 Business Policies and Strategies is the capstone requirement for ALL business students and is to be taken the final semester in the program. Refer to the course description for other specific course prerequisites. This course may NOT be used toward the major (BCA-M).

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR THE MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The management minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Management course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-C) degree requirements, for another major, or any other business minor requirements.
All course work for the management minor must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).
MNGT 399, MNGT 499, may NOT be used toward the minor.
To fulfill the requirements for a management minor, students must complete 12 graded hours of 300/400-level management course work.

Electives

As noted in the Options area, students may choose to take elective course work required for the degree in the suggested course options as listed under the areas of Options. See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

Marketing

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Marketing

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (21 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes-for CBA students only

CHIEF ADVISER:

DESCRIPTION

Chair: A. Dwayne Ball

Professors: Carlson, Gentry, Sohi

Associate Professors: Ball, Saini

Assistant Professors: Eilert, Friend, Kumar, Zhao

Associate Professor of Practice: Simon

Assistant Professor of Practice: Welton

The field of marketing includes many different career opportunities such as advertising, distribution, marketing research, customer relationship management, merchandising, marketing communication, retailing, product management, professional selling, and sales management. The management of activities related to the flow of both goods and services from producer to consumer has become increasingly important in this age of consumer-oriented production. This importance has increased the demand for well-qualified persons, both as specialists in technical aspects of marketing and as general marketing managers. New developments are appearing in quantitative analysis of marketing problems, use of social media, in studies of consumer behavior, in international marketing, and in the social responsibilities of marketing. These developments hold exciting promise for the future.

Academic preparation for some careers is best achieved by combining marketing courses with courses in other departments of the University. For this reason it is important for the student to consult with a faculty member in the Department of Marketing before deciding on a particular course of study. Courses within the department include those from the following disciplines: Marketing, Marketing Communication, Distribution Channels, Retailing, Sales Management, Marketing Research, Professional Selling, Marketing Information Systems, Digital Marketing, Consumer Behavior, and International Marketing. Outside the College, courses in psychology, sociology, journalism, mathematics, communication studies, art, and geography may be helpful.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take MRKT 341 Marketing as part of the Business Core Intermediate requirements.

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
MRKT 399/ MRKT 499 may not count toward the major or minor in marketing.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in marketing will complete 21 hours of marketing course work (plus MRKT 341 for the Business Core Intermediate requirement) for the Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M):

6 required hours selected from:

MRKT 345 Market Research or MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems (if not taken in Business Core Intermediate) or MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics

MRKT 442 Marketing Management (capstone requirement for the marketing major taken during the final semester in the program. Refer to course description for other specific course prerequisites.)

15 additional hours of marketing to be selected from the following courses:

MRKT 225/AECN 225/EAEP 225 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship in Food Products Marketing

MRKT 257 Sales Communication

MRKT 325/AECN 325 Marketing of Agricultural Commodities

MRKT 345 Market Research (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 350 or MRKT 355)

MRKT 346/SCMS 346 Marketing Channels Management

MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy

MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 345 or MRKT 355, or used in lieu of MNGT 350 for BCI)

MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 345 or MRKT 350)

MRKT 357 Advanced Professional Selling

MRKT 425 Retailing Management

MRKT 426 Services Marketing

MRKT 428 Sports Marketing

MRKT 441 Digital Marketing & Electronic Commerce

MRKT 443 Consumer Behavior: Marketing Aspects

MRKT 444/SCMS 444 Supply Chain Logistics Management

MRKT 446 Quantitative Analysis in Marketing

MRKT 449 Marketing Communication Campaigns

MRKT 453 International Marketing

MRKT 457 Customer Relationship Management

MRKT 458 Sales Force Management

MRKT 460 Key Account Selling

MRKT 490 Special Topics in Marketing

MRKT 399 may not be used toward the major
As part of the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirements, marketing majors may substitute MRKT 350 for the MNGT 350 requirement.
Note that although only one of MRKT 345 or MRKT 350 or MRKT 355 is required, a student may elect to take all, one as required and the other two as part of the 15 hours of marketing electives.
The marketing curriculum specifies that MRKT 442 cannot be taken until MRKT 341, MRKT 345, MRKT 350, or MRKT 355 and 6 hours of marketing electives have been completed. This is the capstone requirement for the marketing major and should be taken during the final semester in the program.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, students majoring in marketing may choose to pursue three different options and have these minors declared to pursue the course options. Course work will count toward the ELECTIVES in the College.

Advertising Emphasis requirements (12 hours):

9 hours from:

JOMC 160 Visual Production: Photography & Videography or JOMC 161 (recommended) Visual Design Fundamentals: Graphic Design & Web (3 cr)

ADPR 251 Introduction to Advertising & Public Relations (3 cr)

ADPR 283 Strategy Development for Advertising & Public Relations (3 cr)

3 hours – One course from ADPR (300 or 400 level)

JOMC 160, JOMC 161 (recommended) and ADPR 251 have no prerequisites. ADPR 251 should be completed before ADPR 283. Prerequisites are waived for JOMC 160 and JOMC 161.
ADPR 283 must be completed before taking any of the 300 or 400-level courses.
Marketing majors must have the prerequisites for courses in ADPR and JOMC.

Marketing majors may minor in textiles, merchandising and fashion design by choosing either a Merchandising Track or a Merchandising/Design Track.

Minor in Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design: Merchandising Track requirements (15 hours)

Required:

TMFD 206 Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry (3 cr)

TMFD 313 Merchandising II: Merchandise Buying & Control (3 cr)

Also select two courses from the following:

TMFD 405 Advanced Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 407 History of Costume (3 cr)

TMFD 408 History of Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 413 Merchandising III: Textiles & Apparel Merchandise Development & Retail Strategies (3 cr)

TMFD 422 International Textile & Apparel Sourcing (3 cr)

Minor in Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design: Merchandising/Design Track requirements (24 hours)

Required:

TMFD 144 Introduction to Design Theory & Criticism (3 cr)

TMFD 145 Color Studio: Theory & Practice (3 cr)

TMFD 146 Visualization Studio (3 cr)

TMFD 206 Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry (3 cr)

TMFD 313 Merchandising II: Merchandise Buying & Control (3 cr)

TMFD 314 Textiles & Apparel Merchandising & Promotion (3 cr)

TMFD 413 Merchandising III: Textiles & Apparel Merchandise Development & Retail Strategies (3 cr)

Minor Requirements

Refer to: Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in upper-level marketing courses requires completion of MRKT 341 as well as other prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

MRKT 442 Marketing Management is the capstone requirement for the marketing major taken during the final semester in the program. Refer to course description for other specific course prerequisites.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Marketing Minor

The marketing minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Marketing course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-A) degree requirements, for another major, nor any other business minor requirements.
To fulfill the requirements for a marketing minor, students must complete:
Twelve (12) graded hours of 300/400-level marketing course work.
All course work for the minor must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).
MRKT 399 may not be used toward the minor (or major).

OTHER

The marketing department requires and enforces that specific prerequisite requirements be completed by the first class meeting. Concurrent registration in a class that is a prerequisite for another class is not allowed. Transfer credit assumes that the prerequisites have been transferred to UNL and appear on the transcripts.

The marketing department reserves the right to administratively drop students who do not attend the first class meeting and/or who do not have the appropriate prerequisites for any marketing class.

Mathematics

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Mathematics

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Lori Mueller

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Judy Walker, 206 Avery Hall

Vice Chair: Alan Donsig

Professors: Avalos, Avramov, Deng, Dunbar, Harbourne, Hermiller, Iyengar, Lewis, Logan, Manderscheid, Marley, Meakin, Orr, Peterson, Pitts, Radcliffe, Rammaha, Rebarber, J. Walker, M. Walker, Woodward

Associate Professors: Brittenham, Cohn, Donsig, Foss, Hartke, Ledder, Radu, Tenhumberg

Assistant Professors: Curto, Itskov, Jin, Kelley, Toundykov, Zhang

Associate Professor of Practice: Hines

A strong mathematics background is essential to an increasing variety of careers. The Department of Mathematics encourages students to select a coherent body of courses in mathematics and in other disciplines that are consistent with their academic and career goals.

The Department of Mathematics offers four options for the major in mathematics. Each student majoring in mathematics should select an option that meets their academic and career needs by completing a Program Declaration form in consultation with the Department’s Chief Undergraduate Adviser. Ideally, this should be done prior to completing two mathematics courses beyond the calculus sequence. As appropriate, students can change their Program Declaration to select a different option or modify the program of study subject to the approval of the Chief Undergraduate Adviser.

NOTE: Students with previous credit in any calculus course may not register for or earn credit in MATH 100A, MATH 101, MATH 102, MATH 103, or MATH 104, without first receiving special written permission from the Chief Undergraduate Adviser.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts, master of science, master of arts (or science) for teachers, and doctor of philosophy are offered by the Department of Mathematics. For details of these programs, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Bachelor of Arts

The BA degree is ideal for the student who wants to combine a mathematics major with another major or several minors in the humanities or the social sciences or for the student dual matriculating with another college.

Core Requirements

1. A complete calculus sequence: MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208 or MATH 108H, MATH 109H, or equivalent;

2. Twenty-one hours (seven courses) selected from the Advanced Mathematics Course List.

Specific Major Requirements for the BA

The seven mathematics courses must be distributed as follows:

MATH 221 or MATH 380/STAT 380

MATH 314, MATH 310, and MATH 325

At least two advanced mathematics courses at the 400-level

One more advanced mathematics course

NOTE: Students may substitute a more advanced course in the same area for a required mathematics course. Interested students should visit with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser for more information about this option.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating its programs, all majors should plan to participate in an exit interview during their last semester before graduation. Please make arrangements with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser.

Bachelor of Science

Core Requirements

1. A complete calculus sequence: MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208 or MATH 108H, MATH 109H, or equivalent;

2. Twenty-four hours (eight courses) selected from the Advanced Mathematics Course List;

3. An approved Option Declaration form.

Specific Major Requirements for the BS

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating its programs, all majors should plan to participate in an exit interview during their last semester before graduation. Please make arrangements with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Option C (Concentration)

This option is ideal for students wishing to combine a strong mathematics education with a coherent body of course work in another discipline. Specific requirements above calculus are as follows:

The 8 required mathematics courses must be distributed as follows:

MATH 314

Either MATH 221 or MATH 380/STAT 380

MATH 310 and MATH 325

At least two more advanced mathematics courses at the 400 level

Two additional advanced mathematics courses

Any Plan A minor or an approved 18-hour concentration outside of mathematics.

NOTE: One 400-level course in the area of the concentration may be substituted for one of the required two additional advanced mathematics courses, provided the course makes significant use of advanced mathematics. The Chief Undergraduate Adviser must approve the substitution.

Option E (Education)

This option is ideal for students interested in teaching mathematics at the secondary level. Specific requirements above calculus are as follows:

MATH 310, MATH 314, MATH 325, MATH 350, MATH 380/STAT 380, MATH 405, MATH 407, MATH 408

One additional advanced mathematics course

An education minor or an approved 18-hour concentration in education

Option R (Research Experience)

This option is recommended for students interested in independent work and for students planning to pursue graduate work in mathematics. Specific requirements above calculus are as follows:

The eight required mathematics courses must be distributed as follows:

MATH 221, MATH 310, MATH 314, and MATH 325

At least three advanced mathematics courses at the 400 level

One more advanced mathematics course

An approved undergraduate research experience. A variety of options exist for meeting this requirement. They include 1) research experiences such as an REU or UCARE that leads to a project paper, 2) a senior honors thesis or a thesis approved for graduation with distinction, or 3) a grade of P in MATH 496, Undergraduate Research Seminar (this course would be in addition to the advanced mathematics courses requirement above). To satisfy this requirement, students must file with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser a) a “Research Experience” contract that is approved by the Chief Undergraduate Adviser and b) the thesis, research papers, or projects as required by the contract. Visit with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser for more information.

Option S (Statistics)

This option is recommended for students interested in a mathematics major and a strong body of course work in statistics. Specific requirements above calculus are as follows:

The eight required mathematics courses must be distributed as follows:

MATH 314 and MATH 380/STAT 380

MATH 310 and MATH 325

At least two advanced mathematics courses at the 400 level.

Two more advanced mathematics courses

Nine hours of statistics numbered 300 or above in addition to MATH 380/STAT 380

NOTE: For this option, one 400-level statistics course may be substituted for one of the required two additional advanced mathematics courses.

NOTE: Under any option, students may substitute a more advanced course in the same area for a required mathematics course. Interested students should visit with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser for more information about this option.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

The prerequisites listed for a course may be replaced by equivalent preparation. One prerequisite for all Advanced Mathematics courses is successful completion of MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208 (or MATH 108H, MATH 109H) or equivalent. Additional specific prerequisites, if any, are listed with the course. Two courses past calculus are required prerequisites for all 400-level mathematics courses. All topics, independent study, reading courses and seminars require permission of the instructor before registering; and these courses do not count toward the major requirements unless approved by the Chief Undergraduate Adviser.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

For majors or minors, no calculus course can be taken Pass/No Pass. (Students in violation of this should consult with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser for possible alternative requirements.) For majors or minors, at most 3 hours of the advanced courses may be taken as Pass/No Pass.

GPA Requirements

A minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5 in those courses used to satisfy the Advanced Mathematics course requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. A complete calculus sequence plus two advanced mathematics courses.

Plan B. A complete calculus sequence.

Pass/No Pass. For majors or minors, no calculus course can be taken Pass/No Pass. (Students in violation of this should consult with the Chief Undergraduate Adviser for possible alternative requirements.) For majors or minors, at most 3 hours of the advanced courses may be taken as Pass/No Pass.

Mechanical Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Mechanical Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 128

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Jeffrey Shield

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jeffrey E. Shield

Associate Chair for Research and Graduate Studies: Mehrdad Negahban

Professors: Barton, Bishu, Bobaru, Cole, Dzenis, Farritor, Feng, Gogos, Hallbeck, Nastasi, Negahban, Rajurkar, Reid, Shield, To, Turner, Wei, Yang

Professor of Practice: Stelling

Associate Professors: Baesu, Gu, Nelson, Szydlowski, Tan, Williams, Zhang

Assistant Professors: Huang, Lim, Ndao, Ryu, Terry

Lecturers: Coen-Brown, Dick, Lehman

Mechanical engineering is a broad field of study that significantly impacts many technologies, including those that expand our energy resources and improve medical care. Mechanical engineers are concerned with all forms of energy conversion and transmission; the flow of fluids and heat; the development, design, manufacturing, and operation of machinery and equipment; material structure and properties; solid and applied mechanics; and transportation processes. The course of study is designed to give the student fundamental preparation to enter the fields of research, design, operation, production, sales, or management.

The mechanical engineering curriculum is structured so that students are well prepared in the fundamental areas of solid mechanics, thermal-fluid sciences, systems and design engineering, and materials engineering. Students can develop an emphasis area of study by concentrating elective courses in specific interdisciplinary areas such as aerospace engineering, automotive engineering, robotics, biomedical engineering, computational methods, manufacturing, nanotechnology and others depending upon the technical courses available and the interest of the student.

Mission and Objectives

Mission Statement

The mission of the Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering at the University of Nebraska is to impact society locally and globally through our educational programs, research, and service, developing knowledge and sharing our expertise in the best traditions of land-grant universities. We strive for excellence in teaching and learning at both the undergraduate and graduate levels, seek to develop novel educational opportunities, grow our public and private support for research and education, and expand our scholarship, outreach and service.

Program Educational Objectives

Within a few years of graduation, our mechanical engineering graduates are expected to:

1. have started successful careers based on their education or have completed a professional degree or a graduate degree in engineering or related field;

2. have begun life-long learning and development in order to remain current in their knowledge and skills and to advance in their careers; and

3. have established a record of professionalism, leadership, respect and integrity in working to serve humanity and to use resources responsibly.

Student Outcomes

The educational program leading to the BS in mechanical engineering ensures that students attain the following outcomes:

an ability to apply knowledge of mathematics, science, and engineering;
an ability to design and conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data;
an ability to design a system, component, or process to meet desired needs within realistic constraints such as economic, environmental, social, political, ethical, health and safety, manufacturability, and sustainability;
an ability to function on multidisciplinary teams;
an ability to identify, formulate, and solve engineering problems;
an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility;
an ability to communicate effectively;
the broad education necessary to understand the impact of engineering solutions in a global, economic, environmental, and societal context;
a recognition of the need for, and an ability to engage in, life-long learning;
a knowledge of contemporary issues;
an ability to use the techniques, skills, and modern engineering tools necessary for engineering practice.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln campus)

First Semester Hours

CHEM 111 Chemistry for Engineering & Technology 4

CHEM 109 and 110 may be substituted for CHEM 111. Only 4 credits count toward graduation.

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

ACE Electives 6

Choose courses from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering and Science Focus 3

MATH 107 Calculus II 4

MECH 130 Introduction to CAD 3

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab I 1

Or, instead, PHYS 222 General Physics Lab II (1 cr) may be taken in the Third Semester

Total 15

Third Semester Hours

BSEN 206/CONE 206 Engineering Economics 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 208 Calculus III 4

MECH 223 Engineering Statics 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MATL 360 Elements of Materials Science 4

MECH 200 Engineering Thermodynamics 3

MECH 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

MECH 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

Total 16

Fifth Semester Hours

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering I 3

ELEC 231 Electrical Engineering Lab 1

MATH 314 Linear Algebra 3

MECH 300 Thermal Systems & Design 3

MECH 342 Kinematics & Dynamics of Machinery 3

Communication Studies Elective 3

Choose one course from the following: COMM 210, COMM 283, or COMM 286 (ACE 2).

Total 16

Sixth Semester Hours

IMSE 321 Engineering Statistics & Data Analysis or STAT 380/MATH 380 Statistics & Applications 3

MECH 310 Fluid Mechanics 3

MECH 343 Elements of Machine Design 3

MECH 350 Introduction to Dynamics & Control of Engineering Systems 3

MECH 380 Mechanical Engineering Measurements 3

Total 15

Seventh Semester Hours

MECH 370 Manufacturing Methods & Processes 3

MECH 420 Heat Transfer 3

MECH 446 Mechanical Engineering Design I 3

The capstone design sequence must be taken in the order shown in the curriculum and should be taken in the last two semesters of the program (MECH 446 and MECH 447).

MECH 488 Kinematics & Machine Design Lab 2

Mechanical Engineering Technical Elective 3

Design and technical electives must be chosen from a list of approved 400-level mechanical engineering elective courses. Consult adviser for suggested choices.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Eighth Semester Hours

ENGR 400 Professional Ethics & Social Responsibilities 1

MECH 447 Mechanical Engineering Design II 2

MECH 487 Thermal Fluids Lab 2

Mechanical Engineering Design Elective 3

Design and technical electives must be chosen from a list of approved 400-level mechanical engineering elective courses. Consult adviser for suggested choices.

Senior Elective 3

Senior electives may be either another mechanical engineering technical elective, another mechanical engineering design elective, or, with prior written approval of your adviser, a 300 or higher level engineering, science, or math course.

ACE Electives 6

Choose courses from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Total Credit Hours Required 128

OTHER

Admittance to Degree Program

Students are expected to meet minimum college entrance requirements. After being admitted to the college as pre-mechanical engineering students, students wishing to pursue a degree in mechanical engineering must further be admitted to the degree program. Students who have completed 43 credit hours applicable to their mechanical engineering degree are considered for formal admission to the mechanical engineering degree program. Typically, this occurs the semester the student is enrolled in MECH 200 or MATL 360. Those exceeding 61 credit hours must receive formal admission to the mechanical engineering degree program if they are to continue to take mechanical engineering courses. Transfer students must have at least 12 credit hours of course work from the University of Nebraska–Lincoln on record before an application will be considered.

The requirements for admission to the degree program are a major GPA of 2.7 (that is, not counting elective courses), no more than four withdrawals and no more than three repeated courses. Those who are not admitted to the degree program the first time are advised of the outcome and are automatically reviewed again at the end of that semester. If after two reviews a student is not admitted to the degree program, the student is advised of other majors, in engineering or elsewhere, in which they may be likely to find success.

Hands-on Opportunities

One major focus of the Department is to provide students with many hands-on opportunities both within the curriculum (through formal laboratory courses) and through extracurricular activities. Brief descriptions of some of the laboratories in the department are given below.

The Materials Laboratory is designed to study the development of microstructures during processing, and to correlate the properties of materials with the observed structures. Undergraduates utilize arc melting facilities for solidification processing and alloy formation, rolling mills for deformation processing, and a variety of furnaces for thermal treatments. Characterization facilities include x-ray diffractometry and optical microscopy, while property measurements are completed using hardness testing (including microhardness), tensile testing, and impact testing facilities. Other facilities associated with the materials laboratory include rapid solidification processing facilities and electron microscopy facilities.

The Measurements Laboratory is associated with the required MECH 380 Mechanical Engineering Measurements course which includes two hours of lecture and two hours of laboratory work each week. The course covers the fundamentals of mechanical engineering measurements including data analysis (statistics, graphing, spectral analysis), signal conditioning, data readout, and the measurement of length/displacement, rate of rotation, stress/strain, temperature, pressure, fluid velocity, fluid flow rate, vibration/acceleration, and sound. The MECH 380 Lab has four workbenches. Each workbench has set of basic measurement equipment including a digital oscilloscope, an electronic counter, a digital multimeter, a DC power supply, a function generator, and a computer-based data acquisition system consisting of a personal computer with data acquisition software and interfaced analog-to-digital converter and digital counter cards. In addition, on a week-to-week basis, specialized equipment is brought out of the cabinets and set up for each of the nine (some one week, some two week) labs.

The Kinematics and Machine Design Laboratory is a teaching laboratory for undergraduate students. The laboratory consists of equipment and instruments for conducting experiments in kinematics and machine design. One piece of major equipment is the rapid prototyping machine, which accepts design specifications from a computer and forms a prototype of the design using plastic injection. This machine provides the student with experience in design integration from concept to product. We have also recently upgraded the rapid prototyping laboratory with the acquisition of the MakerBot Thing-O-Matic 3-D printer kit. This 3D printer uses ABS plastic to create rapid prototyped objects with better than 1 mm feature resolution; it accepts standard CAD models converted to g-code and is a low-cost alternative to high-end rapid prototyping services or equipment. Accessories in this laboratory include desktop computers, a wide-carriage printer, and other instruments. Kawasaki also donated a retired robot that is now utilized in this laboratory.

The Thermal Fluids Laboratory involves design, execution and evaluation of physical experiments in the areas of thermodynamics, fluid mechanics, and heat transfer. There are three major, heavily-instrumented experiments: 1) a two stage air-compressor with intercooling, 2) a versatile air conditioning unit, and 3) a Ford gasoline engine with a Superflow water brake dynamometer, supported with a data acquisition system. The course involves design, execution and evaluation of physical experiments in the areas of thermodynamics, fluid mechanics, and heat transfer. In addition, the facilities include “table top” instrumentation for viscosity measurement, measurement of pressure distribution on an airfoil, flow visualization and head loss across a valve on which students conduct experiments.

The Mechatronics Laboratory is well-equipped for teaching courses in mechatronics, robotics, and controls. It is used primarily for MECH 457 and MECH 450, but is also used for other courses, and by both undergraduate and graduate students working on research projects. The laboratory contains desktop computers, modular robots, digital oscilloscopes, function generators, computer controllers, soldering systems, and many other accessories.

The Department also has computational facilities available to students. The computer lab has a suite of personal computers with a full complement of computing resources available to students.

Research Laboratories. These laboratories, extensions of those described above, are equipped for research in the fields of fluid mechanics, heat transfer, thermodynamics, turbulence, flow visualization, fluid mechanics, measurements, turbomachinery and engine research, combustion, materials, mechanical design, dynamics, computational, solid and applied mechanics, biomedical engineering, and controls. Many of our undergraduate students gain valuable experience working on research projects under the guidance of professors. These are funded by research grants or the University’s UCARE program.

Some of the extracurricular opportunities for students to gain hands-on engineering experience include SAE Baja, SAE Formula (both through Husker Motorsports), NASA microgravity, AIAA competitions, and others.

Modern Languages-French, German & Russian Minor (ENGR)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Modern Languages-French, German & Russian Minor (ENGR)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: Plan A–12 hrs; Plan B–9 hrs

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER:

DESCRIPTION

This minor is for engineering majors ONLY.

The College of Engineering enables its students to participate in this approved minor subject to the following conditions:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor must be approved by the adviser, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor.

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “Plan A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “Plan A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “Plan A” or “Plan B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added by approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A Minor. 12 hours at the 203 level and above, including 6 hours at the 300 level.

Plan B Minor. 9 hours at the 203 level and above, including 3 hours at the 300 level.

Music Education

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Music Education

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Music Education

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Robert Woody

DESCRIPTION

Director: John W. Richmond, 120 Westbrook Music Building

Professor: Nierman

Associate Professors: Fuelberth, Moore, Woody

Assistant Professor of Practice: Bazan

Students wanting to teach music in K-12 schools should pursue a bachelor of music education degree. This degree leads to an endorsement (certification) in vocal and instrumental music.

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

ACE Outcome 6 must be MUED 244

ACE Outcome 7 must be MUSC 160

ACE Outcome 9 must be MUSC 280

ACE Outcome 10 must be MUED 403

Library 110 1

Academic Electives 3

Any 3-credit course that is not from music or education.

Music Core 27

Professional and Music Education Requirements 41

Music K-12 Endorsement Requirements 27

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

A three-year sequence of courses called the Music Core Curriculum is at the heart of the School of Music instructional program. Music Core Curriculum courses may not be taken for a Pass/No Pass grade.

The first year of study provides, within a comprehensive framework, a foundation for the successful study of music in an academic environment. Courses include an historical overview and concentrate on music fundamentals, keyboard and aural skills, and conducting. Courses are taken concurrently in each of two semesters beginning with the fall semester.

BME Music Education

Core Curriculum 27

MUSC 64 Senior Assessment in Music 0

MUSC 131 Keyboard Skills I 1

MUSC 132 Keyboard Skills II 1

MUSC 160 Music as Art, Discipline, & Profession 3

MUSC 165 Musicianship I 2

MUSC 165A Musicianship I Lab 1

MUSC 166 Musicianship II 3

MUSC 166A Musicianship II Lab 1

MUSC 265 Musicianship III 3

MUSC 265A Musicianship III Lab 1

MUSC 266 Musicianship IV 3

MUSC 266A Musicianship IV Lab 1

MUSC 274 Beginning Conducting 1

MUSC 365 Music History and Literature I 3

MUSC 366 Music History and Literature II 3

MUSR 68 Recital Attendance (7 semesters) 0

Specific Major Requirements

NOTE: Students preparing for teaching careers will enroll in the following professional courses. Careful planning for the sequencing of these courses is of utmost importance. Students must consult their adviser regularly to be sure their programs are properly scheduled.

See below for additional teacher certification information.

Professional and Music Education Requirements 41

MUED 201 Introduction to Music Education 2

MUED 244 Music Learning & Development 3

MUED 297 Professional Practicum Experience 1

Admission to the Music Teacher Education Endorsement Program is required prior to the following:

MUED 343 Music Composition Methods 2

MUED 344 General Music Methods 3

MUED 345 Instrumental Music Methods 3

MUED 346 Choral Music Methods 3

MUED 374 Advanced Conducting 3

MUED 397A Practicum Experience: General Music 1

MUED 397B or MUED 397D Practicum Experience: Instrumental/Choral 1

MUED 401 Advanced Methods in Music Education 3

MUED 403 Student Teaching Seminar 3

MUED 470 Music & Special Education 3

MUED 497D or MUED 497T Student Teaching: Elementary/Secondary 9

MUED 497D or MUED 497T Student Teaching: Elementary/Secondary 1

Music K-12 Endorsement Requirements 27

MUAP Applied Area (2 credits each semester) 12

Diction and Literature (voice emphasis) Select two from: 0

MUSC 25 English & Italian Diction & Literature (0 hr)

MUSC 26 German Diction & Literature

MUSC 27 French Diction & Literature

MUAP 231 & MUAP 232 Keyboard Skills III & IV or demonstrated proficiency 2

MUAP 235, MUAP 236, MUAP 237, MUAP 238, MUAP 239, MUAP 240 Instrumental Skills Classes 6

MUDC Ensembles (see School of Music Handbook) 7

MUSR 90 Sophomore or Junior Recital in Applied Music 0

(Music education students cannot present student recitals during student teaching.)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for Continuing Study Toward a Music Degree

Music education majors are required to demonstrate adequate skills in applied music, functional keyboard, theory and sight singing before they may continue toward the completion of a degree. The following prerequisites are in place to secure this requirement.

Applied Music–Upper Divisional Qualifying Jury

Music majors must pass the Upper Divisional Qualifying Jury (UDQJ) to be admitted into 300-level applied music. The UDQJ is usually taken in the fourth semester of applied study.

Part I – Basic Skills

Faculty evaluate the student’s minimal capabilities, including the ability to sight read and perform scales and arpeggios, to determine if the student may continue as a music major.

Part II - Musicianship

Faculty evaluate the student’s performance to determine if the student may continue as a music major.

Evaluation

The UDQJ is judged Pass/No Pass, with pass meaning that the student’s basic musical skills and musicianship are judged to be at least minimal for his/her instrument. The jury members in each area will use a general consensus approach in determining Pass/No Pass. A no pass on the UDQJ will indicate an interpretation by the faculty that the student has not completed the requirements for the Upper Divisional Qualifying Jury, resulting in a formal grade of incomplete. The student then has two additional juries to remove the incomplete. The student may continue to register for applied study at the 200 level for a maximum of two semesters until the incomplete is removed. After one year, the incomplete will expire, causing the grade to revert to a D or F. If the student passes the re-take before the beginning of the 2nd week of classes, he/she will be permitted to register for 300-level applied music courses for that semester.

NOTE: A re-examination will be scheduled only during the first week of classes following a semester in which the UDQJ was failed or during regular scheduled jury times at the end of a semester.

The status of music major is provisional, pending a satisfactory completion of the UDQJ. The result of the UDQJ is validated on the UDQJ JURY form with faculty signatures, and filed in the music office.

Grade Rules

All courses taken to fulfill music major or minor requirements must be taken for a grade (except those only offered as Pass/No Pass).
Students must earn grades of C or better in these courses. Any course in which a student earns a grade of C- or below must be repeated in order to count toward the requirement.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit used in Major Requirements

The following will be used by advisers as guidelines for the evaluation of transfer credits that are less than five years old:

If a transfer student has successfully completed (grade C or above) approved transfer credits that are equivalent to NU area requirements in terms of number of credit hours and scope of content, that area will be considered completed at the discretion of the chief degree program adviser.
For approved transfer credits which are lacking equivalency in either number of credit hours, scope of content, or grade received to NU area requirements in applied music, music theory, sight singing/aural skills, and keyboard skills, the number of transfer credits accepted and placement in the NU area will be determined by audition/proficiency tests administered by designated area faculty.
For approved transfer credits that are lacking equivalency in other music areas (history and ensembles) the number of transfer credits accepted will be determined by the chief degree program adviser.

All music course work that is more than five years old must be validated by an audition or competency examination given by designated area faculty.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

A performance audition is required for acceptance as music education major. Auditions are generally held in January and February. The Glenn Korff School of Music should be contacted for audition dates and other details.

OTHER

Ensembles

MUDC/MUCO

Music Ensembles for Degree Credit (MUDC) are exclusively for music majors and minors to fulfill major and minor degree requirements. Music Ensembles for Elective Credit Only (MUCO) are for all other students, and music majors and minors who register for more than one ensemble per semester. All students (full-time music majors, music minors, students registered for applied music, and students with majors or minor outside music) participating in an ensemble in a given semester must register for a minimum of 1 MUDC or MUCO credit. Students participating in more than one ensemble during the same semester may register for zero credit for the additional ensemble(s) using a MUCO ensemble number. All students who do not take applied lessons for credit in a given semester and are in an ensemble must register for the ensemble MUDC or MUCO for credit. No zero credit enrollment will be allowed for such students. Ensemble registrations may be repeated for credit. Ensembles taken in excess of degree requirements will only count as electives.

First Year/First Semester Student Ensemble Registration Policy

All string majors must register for Symphony Orchestra (MUDC 247).
All wind and percussion majors must register for Symphonic Band (MUDC 248B or MUCO 248B) or UNL Jazz Orchestra (MUDC 253A or MUCO 253A).
All voice majors and all piano, organ, guitar, harp, harpsichord, and composition majors must register for Varsity Choir (MUDC 243) or University Chorale (MUDC 246).
All music minors (any applied emphasis) registered for applied music must register for an applied related ensemble (Group I, IA, or II) selected from the List of Approved Ensembles.

Requirements for Majors

Every full-time music major (12 credit hours or more) enrolled in applied music lessons must perform in an ensemble from the List of Approved Ensembles (BA/BM keyboard and guitar players may also use MUDC 440A, MUDC 440B, or MUDC 352) each semester. Students who have not fulfilled ensemble degree requirements should register for one (and only one) MUDC ensemble per semester. The ensembles listed under the MUDC listing are the only ensembles that will fulfill the degree requirements. Only 1 credit under the MUDC listing may be taken per semester. Students may register for additional ensembles using the MUCO listing. Students in the music education degree program are exempt from ensemble participation during the semester in which they student teach. After the student has completed the minimum ensemble requirement for a degree, the student may participate in any ensembles listed below in the List of Approved Ensembles (plus MUDC 440A, MUDC 440B, or MUDC 352 for keyboard, composition, or guitar students).

Bachelor of Music Education

(See following List of Approved Ensembles)

Vocal Emphasis

1 credit Varsity Chorus (MUDC 243) or University Chorale (MUDC 246)

4 credits from Vocal Group I or IA

1 credit from Instrumental Group II and 1 credit from Instrumental or Vocal Group II

Instrumental Emphasis (winds, strings, percussion)

1 credit Varsity Chorus (MUDC 243) or University Chorale (MUDC 246)

4 credits from Instrumental Group I or IA (wind and percussion majors: min 3 cr in Wind Ensemble, Symphonic Band, or Symphony Orchestra; string majors: min 3 cr in Symphony Orchestra)

2 credits from Vocal or Instrumental Group II

Piano, Organ, Guitar, Harp, Harpsichord, Composition Emphasis

1 credit Varsity Chorus (MUDC 243) or University Chorale (MUDC 246)

4 credits from Vocal or Instrumental Group I or IA

1 credit from Vocal Group II and 1 credit from Instrumental Group II

List of Approved Ensembles

Instrumental (MUDC)

Group I: Symphony Orchestra (MUDC 247 or MUDC 447), Wind Ensemble (MUDC 248A or MUDC 448A), UNL Jazz Orchestra (MUDC 253A or MUDC 453A)

Group IA: Symphonic Band (MUDC 248B or MUDC 448B), UNL Big Band (MUDC 253B or MUDC 453B)

Group II: Symphony Orchestra (MUDC 247 or MUDC 447) (vocal emphasis only), Symphonic Band (MUDC 248B or MUDC 448B) (string and vocal emphasis only), Campus Band (MUDC 248D or MUDC 448D) (secondary area only), Marching Band (MUDC 248E or MUDC 448E) (max 1 cr), UNL Big Band (MUDC 253B or MUDC 453B)

Vocal (MUDC)

Group I: University Singers (MUDC 245 or MUDC 445)

Group IA: Concert Choir (MUDC 242), All Collegiate Choir (MUDC 241 or MUDC 441), Chamber Singers (MUDC 249 or MUDC 449), Varsity Chorus (MUDC 243; max 1 cr), University Chorale (MUDC 246; max 1 cr)

Group II: Concert Choir (MUDC 242) (instrumental emphasis only), Varsity Chorus (MUDC 243 or MUDC 443), University Chorale (MUDC 246 or MUDC 446), Jazz Vocal Ensemble (MUDC 253D or MUDC 453D-vocal section only), Big Red Singers (MUDC 251 or MUDC 451; max 2 cr)

NOTE: Students registering to fulfill Group I degree ensemble requirements must audition for and participate in a Group I ensemble. If it is not possible to accommodate the student in a Group I ensemble, the student must audition and participate in a Group IA ensemble to fulfill the Group IA requirement.

Admission to Music Teacher Education Program

Admission to the Music Teacher Education Program is a prerequisite for a music education major to enroll in any 300- or 400-level music education courses. Admission is competitive and enrollment is limited. Admission requires meeting all of the following criteria:

1. Completion of at least 42 credit hours with a minimum 2.5 GPA.

2. Completion of MUED 201 and MUED 244 with a minimum grade of “C” and MUED 297 with a Pass.

3. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

4. Passing the Applied Music–Upper Divisional Qualifying Jury.

5. Completion of MUSC 266, MUSC 266A, and MUAP 232 (or piano proficiency).

6. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form and formal criminal history background check (fee required). (Undertaken during MUED 201 and MUED 297.)

7. Successful completion of a screening interview and digital portfolio review with music education faculty. (Undertaken during MUED 244.)

Interview and Portfolio Review Process

Through course work taken during the freshman and sophomore years, each student will compile a digital portfolio to give evidence of his or her potential as a music teacher. This portfolio will include an autobiographical essay, an educational philosophy statement, a professional resume, and sample lesson plans. The music education faculty will review the digital portfolio prior to conducting a screening interview. During the interview students will demonstrate their suitability to a career in music education by responding to questions posed by the faculty. Feedback will be provided to each student detailing the results of the faculty’s assessment.

Students will be admitted into the Music Teacher Education Program during the spring semester. If a student fails to meet any of the above criteria, they will meet with the music education faculty to determine a course of remediation if applicable. If a student wishes to contest the decision of the music education faculty, they may appeal to the director of the School of Music.

Admission to Student Teaching

Student teaching is required for all students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate. Students who plan to student teach during the fall semester must apply to the coordinator of Music Field Experiences by the preceding March 1. Students who plan to student teach during the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1.

During their student teaching semester, students are to be enrolled exclusively in courses that comprise the student teaching experience (MUED 403 and MUED 497D or MUED 497T). Students wishing to enroll in a degree requirement course while student teaching (in order to graduate at the end of the semester) may do so only with the permission of the director of the School of Music. Students cannot enroll in classes that are not required for their degree.

The removal of an incomplete in student recitals (MUSR 90, MUSR 91, or MUSR 490) during student teaching must have prior approval from the director of the School of Music.

The basic requirements for admission to student teaching are:

1. Matriculation in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts and another college.

2. Admission to the Music Teacher Education Program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative 2.5 GPA.

4. Completion of all 300- and 400-level MUED courses: MUED 343, MUED 344, MUED 345, MUED 346, MUED 374, and MUED 470, with a minimum GPA of 2.5 and no grade below C+ (2.33).

5. Completion of all 300- and 400-level practica: MUED 397A, MUED 397B/D, and MUED 497D/T, each with a grade of Pass.

6. Completion of a criminal history check that will be conducted by an independent party (fee required).

The basic program for student teaching in music provides for a full-day experience on a semester basis.

Student Teaching Placement

Student teachers are placed in many school districts in Lincoln and surrounding areas. Out of state student teaching is also possible. Students should be aware that they may be assigned to a school outside the Lincoln area for student teaching. While student preferences for location will be considered, not all personal preferences can be met.

Criminal History/Background Check

All students will be required to have a criminal history/background check completed no earlier than 90 days prior to the first day of their student teaching experience. This will be at the expense of the student. The applications for acceptance into the music teacher education program and into student teaching also require completion of a self-disclosure form.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. If such a problem occurs, the student in question will be removed by the coordinator of Music Field Experiences at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the university supervisor. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Certification Officer for the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the director of the School of Music within 30 days of the removal. The director will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the coordinator of Music Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the appeals meeting. The decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the coordinator of Music Field Experiences, the director of Field Experiences for the College of Education and Human Sciences, and to the dean of the College.

Moral Character and Safety Concerns

Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Therefore, the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts is interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

With this in mind, should the College discover behavior, which in its reasonable judgment, establishes on the part of the candidate a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss anyone from any program which leads to certification. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching, or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children and young people present in the classroom, schools, and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts programs.

Nebraska State Department of Education Policy Pertaining to Students with Felony or Misdemeanor Convictions

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with felony convictions or misdemeanor convictions involving abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval by the Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts will require each student to affirm under oath that he or she does not have any convictions in the above named areas prior to each field placement. If a student does have any felony or misdemeanor convictions, he/she is required to meet with Dr. Tom Wandzilak, Certification Officer, Student Services Center, 104 Henzlik Hall, 402-472-8626, as soon as possible. Students with questions pertaining to convictions should contact Dr. Wandzilak.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska. Undergraduate students apply for the teaching certificate at the same time they apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building. Post-baccalaureate students completing teacher certification apply to the Chief Adviser for Music Education, Westbrook Music Building.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for, or is removed from, student teaching. However, there are times when, because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the coordinator of Music Field Experiences to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, he or she must first appeal for readmission to the music teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

National Security Studies Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: National Security Studies Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 21

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Tyler R. White

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Kevin Smith (political science)

The undergraduate national security studies minor (NSST) is an interdisciplinary program that provides undergraduates across campus (any department or college) with relevant knowledge of various aspects of global security and the theory and analytical skills necessary for dealing with global security studies issues. Students interested in national security issues, security-related job opportunities, or a desire to have a set of analytical skills relevant to global issues will benefit from the NSST. Students who have completed the NSST requirements will, upon graduation, receive a minor in national security studies.

The minor requires 21 credit hours of course work with a grade of B- or better, including a 3 credit hour capstone course (NSST 475).

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Undergraduate National Security Studies Minor (21 Hours)

Four principles train students to systematically and coherently analyze national security issues, develop writing and critical thinking skills, negotiate multiple and competing interests, and develop in-depth knowledge and application in substantive international policy issue(s). Certain special topics courses not listed below that have a significant nationall security component may also be eligible for inclusion in a students minor program plan. Approval of chief adviser is required to include courses not listed below.

1. CORE Courses (3 credits)

Cover the theories, processes, models, and methods of national security studies and security policy analysis. Choose from:

POLS 160 International Relations

NSST 175 Introduction to National Security

2. Writing and Analysis Courses (6 credits)

Develop writing and critical thinking/analysis skills that are relevant to the national security establishment. Choose two of the following one course from Writing and one course from Critical Thinking/Analysis for a total of 6 hours. No more than 3 hours of courses taken to meet any degree requirement may be used to meet the Rhetoric and Analysis requirements of 6 hours for the National Security Studies minor.

Writing (3 credits). Choose from:

NSST 375 Writing & Briefing for the National Security Enterprise

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument

JOUR 102 The Art of Writing

Critical Thinking/Analysis (3 credits). Choose from:

NSST 376 Analysis for the National Security Establishment

COMM 312 Argumentation

PSYC 350 Research Methods & Data Analysis

SOCI 205 Introduction to Social Research I

SOCI 206 Introduction to Social Research II

3. Topics in Security (9 credits)

Students will develop a plan of study in consultation with the national security studies minor coordinator. Courses will be selected from the list below. (3 hours of 300 level and above and an additional 3 hours of 400 level and above credit required). Choose from:

ANTH 353 Anthropology of War

GEOG 217 Mapping Science in the 21st Century

GEOG 312 Introduction to Geospatial Information Sciences

GEOG 412 Introduction to Geographic Information Systems

GEOG 418 Introduction to Remote Sensing

GEOG 420 Digital Image Analysis of Remote Sensing Data

GEOG 444 Geo-demographic & GIS

HIST 304 U.S. Military History since 1917

HIST 326 Algeria & France

HIST 368 History of Terrorism in the Modern World

HIST 425 History of Radical Islam

POLS 261 Conflict & Conflict Resolution

POLS 263 Causes of War & Peace

POLS 362 Globalization, Human Rights, & Diversity

POLS 363 U.S.A. Foreign Policy

POLS 375 Conflict & Development in Africa

POLS 398 Transnational Criminal Network

POLS 470 International Human Rights

POLS 472 State Terror

POLS 476 Ethnic Conflict & Identity

POLS 463 American Foreign Policy & the Use of the Military

POLS 462 Security in the Post-Cold War Era

POLS 479 Insurgency, Guerilla Warfare, & Terrorism

PSYC 498 Psychology of Terrorism

RELG 318 Islam in the Modern World

RELG 418 Fundamentalism, Religion & Politics

4. Capstone Course (3 credits)

Students will take a one-semester national securities capstone course.

NSST 475 Threats & Solutions to National Security in the 21st Century

Students must meet with the NSST coordinator to set up a plan of study. For more information or to enroll in the minor program, contact Tyler R. White, Department of Political Science, 514 Oldfather Hall, 402-472-9443. Email: twhite4@unl.edu.

Nutrition & Dietetics

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Nutrition & Dietetics

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The Nutrition and Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics) option is designed for students who wish to become registered dietitians and practitioners in clinical, community, food industry, and foodservice areas of nutrition and may be employed by hospitals, community agencies, and various government or private organizations. The University of Nebraska–Lincoln Didactic Program in Dietetics is currently granted accreditation status by the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 120 South Riverside Plaza, Suite 2000, Chicago, IL 60606-6995, 312-899-0040, ext. 5400.

The process to become a registered dietitian involves three steps: completion of a bachelors degree with attainment of the Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics; admission into and the completion of an accredited dietetic internship program; and successfully passing the registration exam to earn the Registered Dietitian (RD) credential.

Meeting requirements for the bachelors degree Nutrition and Dietetics option does not automatically result in the student being awarded a Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics. Requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement are listed on the dietetics program website. The Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics is required for admission into an accredited dietetic internship program.

Acceptance into an accredited dietetic internship program is competitive. Currently, there is a significant shortage of available internship positions for the number of students applying for acceptance into an internship program. Acceptance into an internship program cannot be guaranteed.

All required accreditation information and requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement can be found at http://cehs.unl.edu/nhs/undergrad/dietetics.shtml.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 33

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. NUTR 452 & NUTR 452L (Professional Requirement) 4

Professional Requirements (A grade of C or above is required) 40

NUTR 100, NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 251, NUTR 344, NUTR 356, NUTR 370, NUTR 402, NUTR 450, NUTR 453, NUTR 455, NUTR 473 (3 hrs ea) 36

NUTR 150, NUTR 245, NUTR 371, NUTR 490 (1 hr ea) 4

Supporting Courses 29-33

MATH 101 or higher 2-5

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L 4

BIOS 111 (4 hrs) or BIOS 312 (3 hrs) & BIOS 314 (1 hr) or NUTR 372 (3 hrs) 3-4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 4

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L 4

Electives 14-18

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

* These (*) courses, required in your major, will also meet ACE Requirements.

Professional Requirements

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

NUTR 150 Foundations in Nutrition & Health Promotion

NUTR 244 & NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation & Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle

*NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 356 Nutrition Education in the Community

NUTR 370 Food Production Management

NUTR 371 Applied Food Production Lab

NUTR 402 Health Information: Science, Media, and the Consumer

NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I

*NUTR 452 Medical Nutrition Therapy II

*NUTR 452L Medical Nutrition Therapy II Lab

NUTR 453 Nutrition & Fitness Communication Strategies

NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition

NUTR 473 Organization & Administration of Foodservice

NUTR 490 Professional Preparation for Careers in Dietetics

Supporting Courses

*EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or *STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics

*PSYC 181 Introduction to Psychology

MATH 101 College Algebra or higher, trigonometry or calculus

BIOS 111 The Biology of Microoganisms or BIOS 312 & BIOS 314 Microbiology & Lab or NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation (3-4 hrs)

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades Earned at UNL, UNO, UNK

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Policy for Pass/No Pass Courses

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed for students who want to study elective areas or topics when they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Free electives may be taken P/N. Students can earn no more than 12 hours of pass credit excluding courses offered on Pass/No Pass only basis. Not all classes can be taken under the Pass/No Pass option. All courses, specified by course and number, must be taken for a grade. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed by the appropriate department.

Nutrition Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Nutrition Science

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Vicki Fisher

DESCRIPTION

The Nutrition Science option is designed for students who wish to combine an emphasis in nutrition with a strong science background. This major provides an appropriate vehicle for premedical, predental, nursing, physical therapy, and laboratory technology majors who may be able to obtain a degree in nutrition and simultaneously meet entrance requirements for a professional program. It is also a suitable avenue for students interested in nutrition research and graduate study since it provides an opportunity to emphasize the basic sciences.

ADMISSION

The admission requirements for pre-professional programs vary and may change from year to year. Admission to professional programs is competitive. Students need to be aware of not only specific course requirements but also entrance exams, admission deadlines, research and volunteer opportunities, and other activities that enhance the application. In order to receive the most timely information on requirements and preparation, students should visit the Explore Center, 33 Canfield Administration Building, 402-472-3605.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 32

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 or COMM 211 or SOCI 200 or SOCI 217 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 10. NUTR 455 (Professional Requirement) 3

Professional Requirements (A grade of C or above is required) 15

NUTR 250, NUTR 401, NUTR 402, NUTR 450, NUTR 452 (3 hrs ea) 15

Supporting Courses 54-62

MATH 101 or higher 2-5

BIOC 431 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 312 6

BIOS 213L & BIOS 314 2

BIOS 214 5

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 & CHEM 252 & CHEM 253 7

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L 4

PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 (5 hrs ea) or PHYS 211 & PHYS 212 (4 hrs ea) 8-10

Select any from the following: 8-11

BIOC 432; any course 200 or above in BIOS, PHYS, CHEM; CHEM 254; any FDST 400 or above; MATH 102 or higher; NUTR 484; PHIL 213; PSYC 380; or any VBMS 300 or above

Electives 11-19

Total Hours 120

MAJOR/PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

*These (*) courses required in your major, will also meet ACE Requirements.

Professional Requirements

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 401 Health Behavior or NUTR 403 Physiological Foundations of Health & Disease

NUTR 402 Facts & Fiction in Fitness & Food

NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I

NUTR 452 Medical Nutrition Therapy II

*NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition

Supporting Courses

*EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics

*NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition or SOCI 200 Women in Contemporary Society or SOCI 217 Nationality & Race Relations or COMM 211 Intercultural Communication

*PSYC 181 Introduction to Psychology

MATH 101 College Algebra or higher

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab

BIOS 214 Human Anatomy

BIOS 312 & BIOS 314 Microbiology & Lab

*CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab

PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 Elementary General Physics I & II or PHYS 211 & PHYS 212 General Physics I & II

Select from any of the following:

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication

BIOS (any course 200 or above)

CHEM (any course 200 or above)

CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II Lab

FDST (any course 400 or above)

MATH 102 Trigonometry (or higher)

NUTR 484 Physiology of Exercise

PHIL 213 Medical Ethics

PHYS (any course 200 or above)

PSYC 380 Abnormal Psychology

VBMS (any course 300 or above)

Electives

Nutrition, Exercise & Health Sciences

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Nutrition, Exercise & Health Sciences

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Ben Bannon, Eric Einspahr

DESCRIPTION

The Nutrition, Exercise and Health Science option is designed for those students interested in planning, conducting and managing health-related fitness and wellness programs in a variety of settings. Graduates are prepared to enter a variety of health/fitness/recreation-related positions such as: fitness/wellness programs provided by corporations for their employees; fitness, health assessment, and cardiac rehabilitation programs provided by hospitals or medical clinics; programs provided by YMCA’s, private health clubs and commercial fitness clubs; government or private agencies which provide health or fitness assessment or lifestyle behavior modification programs for employees or other groups of individuals; and community recreation centers and other health, fitness or lifestyle-related endeavors. The nutrition, exercise and health science option provides an appropriate vehicle for premedical, predental, prechiropractic and prephysical therapy majors who may be able to obtain a degree in nutrition and simultaneously meet entrance requirements for a professional program.

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 32

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 330 or EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. NUTR 488 (Professional Requirement) 3

Professional Requirements (A grade of C or above is required) 38

NUTR 100, NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 344, NUTR 384, NUTR 401, NUTR 402, NUTR 453, NUTR 455, NUTR 484 (3 hrs ea) 30

NUTR 150 1

NUTR 486 4

FITN 180 1

FITN 222 2

Supporting Courses 31-34

MATH 102 or MATH 103 or MATH 106 2-5

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

BIOS 214 (A grade of C or above is required) 5

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 4

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L 4

Electives 16-19

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

BIOS 214 (grade of C or higher is required)

Pre-Health

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Pre-Health

DEGREE OFFERED:

HOURS REQUIRED:

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE:

CHIEF ADVISER:

DESCRIPTION

Pre-health areas of study are not majors at UNL but rather advising categories. Students interested in pursuing health care careers but who have not yet decided on a major start their program of studies in the College of Arts and Sciences. Some students declare an academic major while working toward their professional school requirements and earn a degree from UNL before entering professional school. Some professional programs allow students to enter after completing school requirements without earning an undergraduate degree. In either case, students may choose a course of study in any of the following Pre-Health Categories while they are preparing for professional school and/or deciding on a major and degree. Students pursuing these categories while earning degrees from any undergraduate college at UNL can receive guidance and advice from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center (Explore Center) by declaring their pre-health category with their college advising office. Students who do not know which career path they might pursue are encouraged to explore the many options available by using ExploreHealthCareers.org website in addition to Career Services and the Explore Center website and resources.

Pre-Chiropractic

Chiropractic is a branch of health care that focuses on manipulation as the best mode of care and treatment of many injuries and illnesses. It emphasizes the inter-relatedness of the body parts as a whole set, but especially as they relate to the function of the nervous system. Since the majority of the bodys organs are innervated by nerves which enter or leave the spine, a major emphasis is on the correct structure and function of the spine and the body joints.

Pre-Clinical Laboratory Science

Clinical Lab Science (formally Medical Technology) is the allied health profession concerned with performing laboratory tests that are used in the diagnosis, treatment, and prognosis of disease and in the maintenance of health. The clinical lab scientist performs a full range of laboratory tests, from simple pre-marital blood tests to more complex tests to uncover diseases, such as AIDS, diabetes, and cancer. The clinical lab scientist is also responsible for confirming the accuracy of test results and reporting laboratory findings to the pathologist and other doctors.

Pre-Clinical Perfusion Science

Perfusionists are skilled allied health professionals, qualified by academic and clinical education, who deal with all phases of regulating and controlling blood flow outside the body, called extracorporeal circulation. The perfusionist operates extracorporeal equipment during any medical situation where it is necessary to support, or temporarily replace, the patients circulatory or respiratory function. The perfusionist has diverse responsibilities which include the mechanical support of a patients circulation and pulmonary function during open heart surgery and is an integral member of the cardiovascular surgery team involved in infant and adult cardiac surgery.

Pre-Cytotechnology

Cytotechnology is an allied health specialty which offers exciting possibilities for those who want a career in science and a significant role in health care. Working with a microscope, cytotechnologists study specimens from all body sites. Using subtle clues in the cells themselves, cytotechnologists can solve the mystery of disease by diagnosing cancer, precancerous lesions, benign tumors, infectious agents, and inflammatory processes. Cytotechnologists help save lives by discovering certain diseases early when treatment is most effective.

Pre-Dental Hygiene

A dental hygienist is a preventive oral health professional licensed in dental hygiene to provide educational, clinical and therapeutic services supporting total health through the promotion of optimal oral health. The dental hygienist is responsible for providing treatment that helps to prevent oral diseases such as dental caries (cavities) and periodontal disease (gum disease) and for educating the patient to maintain optimal oral health.

Pre-Dentistry

Dentistry is devoted to maintaining the health of teeth and gums, as well as other hard and soft tissues of the mouth. Early detection of oral cancer and systemic conditions that manifest themselves through the mouth are necessary for the maintenance of general health. The dentist is, in fact, a person dedicated to the highest standards of health throughout the prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of all oral diseases and conditions.

Pre-Medicine

The medical profession (allopathic, osteopathic, or podiatric) offers a wide variety of career options that are exciting, challenging, and rewarding. Although the environment in which medical services are provided has been changing rapidly and will continue to change, the physicians role as diagnostician, healer, and patient advocate remains central to the provision of health care in our country. Although most physicians provide direct patient care, some medical degree recipients concentrate on basic or applied research, become teachers or administrators, or combine various elements of these activities.

Pre-Mortuary Science

Completion of a professional program in mortuary science leads to licensure as a funeral director/embalmer. Morticians deal with funeral planning, death registration, embalming, and the grief and bereavement issues of families and friends of the deceased.

Pre-Nursing

The nursing profession offers a wide variety of career opportunities for men and women. Career choices range from highly technical positions in research or intensive care to high touch specialties such as hospice care or the newborn nursery. Nursing training programs range from associates to bachelors educational levels. Students who earn the BSN are prepared to assume staff nurse level positions in areas such as public health, gerontology, pediatrics, industrial settings, emergency medicine, psychiatric and mental health facilities, and acute care agencies. Students who desire advanced nursing degrees will find graduate programs leading to the masters and doctor of philosophy degrees in a variety of specialty areas. UNL offers prerequisite courses required for admission to clinical nursing programs, which grant the nursing degree.

Pre-Occupational Therapy

Occupational therapy is a health care profession using purposeful activity (occupation) as a means of preventing, reducing, or overcoming physical, social, and emotional challenges in people of all ages. An occupational therapist works with individuals whose participation in daily activities has been impaired by physical injury/illness, developmental/learning disabilities, psychological/emotional problems or the aging process. The occupational therapist carefully evaluates each person to determine physical and/or mental strengths and weaknesses, and, in conjunction with other health professionals, develops a program using purposeful activities and adaptive equipment to encourage the patients involvement in meaningful daily living.

Pre-Optometry

Optometry is the primary health profession dedicated to caring for vision. Through academic and clinical training, optometrists acquire the knowledge and skills needed to diagnose, treat, and prevent problems of the visual system. Providing health education, managing curative or preventive regimes, and supplying vision care to special groups of patients are all parts of an optometrists work.

Pre-Pharmacy

Pharmacists are responsible for drug therapy and drug distribution and must possess the scientific and technical knowledge necessary to evaluate drug therapy for each individual patient. They must develop skill in personal relations with patients and other health professionals. Above all, they must be able to make good use of acquired knowledge and experience in arriving at sound judgments and policy decisions.

Pre-Physical Therapy

As an important member of the health care team, physical therapists assess and treat disabilities and promote wellness to individuals of all ages. Their primary objective is to promote optimum human health and function. The physical therapist conducts physical evaluations to determine the patients potential for rehabilitation and life style changes indicated, as well as educates the patient and family.

Students can declare Pre-Physical Therapy through the College of Arts and Sciences or the College of Education and Human Sciences. The Pre-Physical Therapy category does not vary based on the UNL undergraduate college. Students who see themselves pursuing an undergraduate major in the College of Arts and Sciences should choose that college for their degree program, while students interested in an academic major offered through the College of Education and Human Sciences should declare that college for completing their degree. The academic advisers in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center will assist students from any college with their pre-physical therapy requirements.

Pre-Physician Assistant

The physician assistant (PA) practices medicine with the supervision of a physician. As a result of extensive medical training, the PA can assume many tasks traditionally performed only by a medical doctor, thereby helping the physician to be more efficient. Each supervising physician utilizes the services of a PA based on his/her own practice needs. Typically the PA obtains the patients medical history, performs a comprehensive physical examination, and orders appropriate laboratory and x-ray studies. The PA diagnoses and treats a wide range of common medical problems, and assists the physician in the management of complex chronic illnesses. Many PAs make hospital and nursing home rounds and assist in surgery. A very important part of the PAs role is to educate the patient and the community about illness, family planning, social services, health hazards, baby and child care, and other aspects of health promotion and disease prevention.

Pre-Radiation Science Technology

Radiation science technology comprises several disciplines that utilize radiation for diagnosis or treatment, including but not limited to radiography, nuclear medicine, diagnostic medical sonography, or radiation therapy technology. Students should explore options in radiation science to see which field best fits their skills and interests. The career options available to students interested in radiation sciences continually expands as technology develops.

HIGH SCHOOL PREPARATION

Students planning to pursue advanced work in any of the Pre-Health programs should begin with a strong college preparatory course program in high school. In addition to meeting the University entrance requirements, it is recommended that pre-health students finish four years of the same foreign language in high school. Pre-health students are also encouraged to take as many years of mathematics and science as possible while paying close attention to the use of pre-university earned credit options such as Advanced Placement, International Baccalaureate, and Dual Enrollment/Dual Credit options. Some health professional schools will not accept or will limit acceptance and applicability of prerequisite credit earned by examination (AP/IB) or prior to high school graduation. Students should consult with an academic adviser in the Explore Center or their high school guidance counselor when choosing to earn college credit prior to graduating from high school.

ADMISSION TO PROFESSIONAL PROGRAMS

The admission requirements for health professional programs vary and may change from year to year. Admission to professional programs is competitive. Therefore, students need to be aware of not only specific course requirements but also entrance exams, admission deadlines, research and volunteer opportunities, and other activities that enhance the application. In order to receive the timeliest information on requirements and preparation, students should visit or contact the Explore Center, 127 Love Library South, 402-472-3605, explorecenter@unl.edu. Information is also available on the website http://explorecenter.unl.edu/.

ADMISSION TO PRE-HEALTH

Pre-health is not a major at UNL but rather an advising category. Students may follow pre-health areas of study while pursing any degree/major at UNL. Students who are unsure of which college/major they would like to pursue, may initially apply to the College of Arts and Sciences as a Pre-Health student. Please review the entrance requirements for the College of Arts and Sciences in the colleges section of the bulletin at http://bulletin.unl.edu/undergraduate/college/Arts+%26+Sciences.

ADVISING FOR PRE-HEALTH

Students are advised in pre-health areas of study by professional academic advisers in the Explore Center. Advisers are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 127 Love Library South and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu.

COLLEGE REQUIREMENTS FOR PRE-HEALTH

Students should check the section of the bulletin outlining the requirements for their specific college of admittance. Those students undecided on a major who were admitted as Pre-Health students to the College of Arts and Sciences should review the college requirements outlined in the colleges section of the bulletin at http://bulletin.unl.edu/undergraduate/college/Arts+%26+Sciences.

Pre-Law (EC)

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Pre-Law (EC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking

HOURS REQUIRED: N/A

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: N/A

MINOR AVAILABLE: N/A

CHIEF ADVISER: Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center

DESCRIPTION

The pre-law area of study is an advising category used to identify students advancing toward a law-related career goal. Students cannot declare a major or earn a degree in the pre-law area. Most students use their undergraduate academic program to develop the desired skill set for entry into law school and the legal profession. Students may select any UNL academic major while pursuing a pre-law area of study, and can temporarily select a major of “Pre-Law” though the College of Arts and Sciences while they are exploring and determining which academic major they would like to declare.

Students pursuing a pre-law area of study can receive guidance and advice from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center (Explore Center) by declaring the pre-law category with their college advising office.

Pre-Law

Law is the system we use to ensure order and justice for individuals and communities within our society. The broad nature of the legal field allows people to work with the law in a number of ways. Litigation (trial practice), representative practice, legal planning, education, and adjudication (becoming a judge) are traditional ways in which people work directly with the law. However, a legal education is useful and may be applied to a variety of other fields such as business, insurance, government, writing, resource management, or publishing.

High School Preparation

Students planning to pursue advanced work in the pre-law program should begin with a strong college preparatory course program in high school. In addition to meeting the University entrance requirements, it is recommended that pre-law students finish four years of the same foreign language in high school.

Advising

Students are advised in the pre-law area of study by professional academic advisers in the Explore Center. Advisers are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 127 Love (Library) South and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu.  Academic advising appointments can also be scheduled through the MyPLAN tab in Blackboard.

In addition to the Explore Center advisers, students with a declared UNL major should work with their assigned major adviser and should check the section of the bulletin outlining the requirements for their specific college of admittance. Those students undecided on a major who were admitted as “Pre-Law” majors to the College of Arts and Sciences should review the college requirements outlined in the Arts and Sciences section of the bulletin.

Application and Admission to Law Professional Programs

The admission requirements for law professional programs vary and may change from year to year. Admission to professional programs is competitive. Therefore, students should to be aware of academic recommendations, entrance exams, admission deadlines, research and volunteer opportunities, and other activities that enhance the application. In order to receive the timeliest information on requirements and preparation, students should visit or contact the Explore Center at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu. Information is also available on the Explore Center website http://explorecenter.unl.edu/.

Pre-Veterinary Medicine

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Veterinary Medicine

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

HOURS REQUIRED:

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Laura Hardin

DESCRIPTION

Interim Director: Professor Don Beerman, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, 120C Vet Basic Sciences

Head: Professor Larry Berger, Department of Animal Science, C203 Animal Sciences

Individuals wishing to enter the four-year professional curriculum leading to the degree Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (DVM) degree, must first complete two or more years of pre-veterinary general education. Courses taken during pre-veterinary education must satisfy the entrance prerequisites for the college of veterinary medicine of the person’s choice. At the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, it usually requires a minimum of three years to complete the pre-professional requirements. Certain options in the veterinary science and veterinary technology degree programs meet the pre-veterinary requirements of colleges of veterinary medicine. The student should discuss special variations and other colleges of interest with their academic adviser at the earliest possible date.

The Pre-Veterinary Program IS NOT a degree-granting program. Completion of the pre-veterinary program alone in fulfilling the prerequisites for admission to a college or school of veterinary medicine does not result in the awarding of a degree from the University of Nebraska. Students are encouraged to consider courses of study with a degree-granting program in veterinary science (biomedical science, microbiology options, or veterinary medicine options), veterinary technology, animal science, food science and technology, biochemistry or other fields compatible with the pre-veterinary program. Students can also complete pre-veterinary prerequisites with a degree program in wildlife or environmental studies, leading to a bachelor of science degree. It is also possible to pursue these pre-veterinary requirements in degree-granting programs outside the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, such as the College of Arts and Sciences.

The program utilizes an “Advising Plus” model which involves faculty from the School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences and the Department of Animal Science.  Pre-veterinary  advising will guide students toward successful completeion of requirements and application to veterinary school.  Advisors will also expose students to opportunities in animal health and assist them in identifying an appropriate degree program as they progress in their studies.

Students interested in veterinary medicine are encouraged to participate in the Pre-veterinary Club to learn about the exciting advancement and developments within the profession.

It is not recommended that pre-veterinary students take any courses on a Pass/No Pass basis (unless this is the only grading option for a given course, e.g. VBMS 101) because courses taken Pass/No Pass may not be accepted for pre-professional prerequisites. Letter grades are required to evaluate credentials of applicants for veterinary college admission.

See individual degree programs for specializations in those areas.

Russian (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Russian (ASC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Radha Balasubramanian

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Evelyn Jacobson, 1111 Oldfather Hall

Vice Chair: Radha Balasubramanian

Professors: Carr, Hayden-Roy, E. Jacobson, Pereira, Stump

Associate Professors: Balasubramanian, Brantner, González, González-Allende, Guevara, Kalisa, Lorenzo, Mejias-Bikandi, Saskova-Pierce, Shirer

Assistant Professors: Amano, Enkin, Hasan, Kingsbury-Brunetto, Peterson, Velázquez

Emeriti Professors: Fouletier-Smith, M. Jacobson, Martinez, Nickel, Turner, Wilhelmsen

The Department of Modern Languages and Literatures offers courses in Arabic, German, Japanese, the Romance Language group (French, Spanish), and the Slavic group (Czech, Russian). Whenever possible, the courses are conducted in the language that is studied. The aim of instruction is reading, writing, aural and oral proficiency, and an understanding of the life, literature, and culture of the country. Lectures and films in the language studied are offered during the school year for the benefit of the students in the department. Language laboratories supplement class work.

Placement

Incoming students who wish to enter the University’s language program in French, Spanish, and German are required to take the Computer Assisted Placement Examination (CAPE). The results of the placement exam, together with training in a secondary school university, or other prior second language environments, will assist students in finding the level at which they will have the greatest opportunity for success. The examination results will be used in combination with advising to determine appropriate placement in the sequence of courses offered within the department’s curriculum. CAPE is administered in the language laboratory (302 Burnett Hall). Those students exempted from this requirement are expected to enroll in a first semester elementary course (101). Students qualifying for this exemption are defined as follows:

1. Students with no previous second language exposure whatsoever.

2. Students whose second language exposure amounts to one year or less at the U.S. high school level.

3. Students who wish to begin study of a new language other than those previously studied.

For other languages, placement is generally determined by the following criteria for students who come to the University with:

1. 1 semester of a language in high school should take 101 (same language or a new one);

2. 2 or 3 semesters in high school should take 102 (same language);

3. 4 or 5 semesters in high school should take 201;

4. 6 semesters in high school should take 202;

5. 8 semesters or more in high school should take 203.

The department participates in the following interdisciplinary study programs: Institute for Ethnic Studies, Global Studies, Jewish Studies, Latin American Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Women’s and Gender Studies.

Students may receive full credit at the University of Nebraska for education abroad programs in many countries, among these are Costa Rica, France, Germany, Spain, Russia, Japan, and the Czech Republic. See http://educationabroad.unl.edu for a guide to these programs.

Auditing. Audits are allowed in 101 in French, German and Spanish only upon recommendation of the Modern Language Placement Advisers. Otherwise no audits are allowed in 100- and 200-level classes.

Literature in Translation

The Department offers the following literature in translation courses for which no knowledge of a foreign language is necessary. Check the Schedule of Classes to determine which are being taught in any given semester: MODL 234D Major Themes in World Literature; MODL 298, MODL 398 Special Topics; FREN 282 and GERM 282 Literature in Translation; SPAN 264 and SPAN 265 Spanish-American Literature in Translation I & II; MODL/GERM 442/842 Survey of Medieval German Literature in Translation; JAPN 331 Introduction to Japanese Film; JAPN 483 Japanese Literature in Translation; and RUSS 482 and RUSS 483 Russian Literature in Translation I & II.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered in French, German, and Spanish. For details, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

21 hours of courses numbered 300 or above, including RUSS 303 and RUSS 304 and 6 hours at the 400 level.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to assemble and maintain a portfolio. In their junior year, majors will be assigned a faculty adviser who will inform students of the required contents of the portfolio, deadlines and procedures. During their last semester, French and Russian majors will be required to provide oral and written assessment for their portfolios.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. 12 hours in one language at the 300 level or 400 level, including at least 6 hours from 301, 302, 303, 304, and 3 hours at the 400 level.

Plan B. 6 hours in one language, in courses numbered above 300, including at least 3 hours from 301, 302, 303, 304.

Pass/No Pass. No courses in the department may be taken by students majoring or minoring in modern languages for Pass/No Pass credit.

Sociology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Sociology

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Lisa Kort-Butler

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Julia McQuillan, 711 Oldfather Hall

Vice-Chair: Philip Schwadel

Professors: Deegan, Hoyt, McQuillan, Moore, Tyler, Werum, Whitbeck

Associate Professors: Cheadle, Dance, Dombrowski, Falci, Goosby, Olson, Schwadel, Smyth

Assistant Professors: Kazyak, Kort-Butler, Smith, D. Warner, T. Warner

A major in sociology within the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) is a valuable and flexible program. The sociology curriculum provides students with vital skills, including analytical thinking, creative problem solving, effective written and oral communication, making meaning out of data through analyses, and greater understanding of social and cultural differences among people. Course choices may be made with respect to a students interests and educational objectives. Students may pursue broad training in sociology or may pursue one of our five focus areas. Focus areas include: crime/deviance, family, health, social inequality, and social research. Students are encouraged to complete an internship to apply the perspectives gained in their coursework to the real world and acquire experience in a career path.

Current majors and students considering a major in sociology should consult with a department adviser when registering for classes. This is particularly important because the subjects that lay the foundation for later training in sociology, plus the courses for a minor in another department, should be carefully selected. The adviser can also discuss focus areas, internships, and research opportunities.

This department participates in the programs of Global Studies, Ethnic Studies, Environmental Studies, the Center for Great Plains Studies, the Womens and Gender Studies Program, and the Center for Civic Engagement.

One course in rural sociology, AECN 276, may count toward a major in sociology. Students in the College of Agriculture who have taken AECN 276 may substitute the course for SOCI 101 if they plan to take other courses in the Department of Sociology.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details of these programs, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin and the departmental bulletin, Sociology Graduate Program Guidelines, available at 711 Oldfather Hall.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

30 hours, including SOCI 101, SOCI 205, SOCI 206, SOCI 355, and a significant research experience.

The research experience requirement may be met in any of the following ways: 1) SOCI 310A and SOCI 310B; 2) SOCI 495; 3) SOCI 399H; or 4) SOCI 396.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to complete an exit survey during the course of the senior seminar. The instructor will inform the students of the scheduling and format of the survey.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will not affect a students GPA or graduation in any way.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students majoring in sociology may not take courses in the major for Pass/No Pass credit with the possible exceptions of independent study, 3 credit hours of field work in sociology, and hours in excess of those required for the major. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirement

At least 12 hours must be taken at the 300 or 400 level.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules

No more than 6 hours total from internship and independent study courses, SOCI 397 and SOCI 399, may be counted toward the major requirements in sociology.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours including SOCI 101. No more than 3 hours total from internship and independent study courses, SOCI 397 and SOCI 399, may be counted toward the minor requirements in sociology.

Spanish (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Spanish (ASC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Lola Lorenzo

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Evelyn Jacobson, 1111 Oldfather Hall

Vice Chair: Radha Balasubramanian

Professors: Carr, Hayden-Roy, E. Jacobson, Pereira, Stump

Associate Professors: Balasubramanian, Brantner, Gonzlez, Gonzlez-Allende, Guevara, Kalisa, Lorenzo, Mejias-Bikandi, Saskova-Pierce, Shirer

Assistant Professors: Amano, Enkin, Hasan, Kingsbury-Brunetto, Peterson, Velzquez

Emeriti Professors: Fouletier-Smith, M. Jacobson, Martinez, Nickel, Turner, Wilhelmsen

The Department of Modern Languages and Literatures offers courses in Arabic, German, Japanese, the Romance Language group (French, Spanish), and the Slavic group (Czech, Russian). Whenever possible, the courses are conducted in the language that is studied. The aim of instruction is reading, writing, aural and oral proficiency, and an understanding of the life, literature, and culture of the country. Lectures and films in the language studied are offered during the school year for the benefit of the students in the department. Language laboratories supplement class work.

Placement

Incoming students who wish to enter the Universitys language program in French, Spanish, and German are required to take the Computer Assisted Placement Examination (CAPE). The results of the placement exam, together with training in a secondary school university, or other prior second language environments, will assist students in finding the level at which they will have the greatest opportunity for success. The examination results will be used in combination with advising to determine appropriate placement in the sequence of courses offered within the departments curriculum. CAPE is administered in the language laboratory (302 Burnett Hall). Those students exempted from this requirement are expected to enroll in a first semester elementary course (101). Students qualifying for this exemption are defined as follows:

1. Students with no previous second language exposure whatsoever.

2. Students whose second language exposure amounts to one year or less at the U.S. high school level.

3. Students who wish to begin study of a new language other than those previously studied.

Foreign language placement guidelines are generally determined by the following criteria for students who come to the University with:

1. 1 semester of a language in high school should take 101 (same language or a new one);

2. 2 or 3 semesters in high school should take 102 (same language);

3. 4 or 5 semesters in high school should take 201;

4. 6 semesters in high school should take 202;

5. 8 semesters or more in high school should take 203.

The department participates in the following interdisciplinary study programs: Institute for Ethnic Studies, Global Studies, Jewish Studies, Latin American Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Womens and Gender Studies.

Students may receive full credit at the University of Nebraska for education abroad programs in many countries, among these are Costa Rica, France, Germany, Spain, Russia, Japan, and the Czech Republic. See http://educationabroad.unl.edu for a guide to these programs.

Auditing. Audits are allowed in 101 in French, German and Spanish only upon recommendation of the Modern Language Placement Advisers. Otherwise no audits are allowed in 100- and 200-level classes.

Literature in Translation

The Department offers the following literature in translation courses for which no knowledge of a foreign language is necessary. Check the Schedule of Classes to determine which are being taught in any given semester: MODL 234D Major Themes in World Literature; MODL 298, MODL 398 Special Topics; FREN 282 and GERM 282 Literature in Translation; SPAN 264 and SPAN 265 Spanish-American Literature in Translation I & II; MODL/GERM 442/842 Survey of Medieval German Literature in Translation; JAPN 331 Introduction to Japanese Film; JAPN 483 Japanese Literature in Translation; and RUSS 482 and RUSS 483 Russian Literature in Translation I & II.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered in French, German, and Spanish. For details, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to assemble a portfolio. A faculty adviser will inform students of the required contents of the portfolio, deadlines and procedures. During their last semester, Spanish majors will be required to provide oral and written materials for their portfolios.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a students GPA or graduation.

27 hours of courses

• 6 hours of SPAN 305 and SPAN 317

• 3 hours from SPAN 321 or SPAN 331

• 6 additional elective hours of SPAN courses at the 300 level (above SPAN 305)

• 9 elective hours of SPAN courses at the 400 level

• 3 additional elective hours of courses at the 300 or 400 level. These additional 3 hours may be:

            - from a SPAN course above SPAN 305

            - from one of the following courses:

                        AHIS 456 Pre-Columbian Art

                        AHIS 457 Colonial Art of Latin America

                       ANTH 350 Peoples and Cultures of Native Latin America

                       ANTH 436 The Ancient Maya

                        HIST 357 Mexican-American History

                        HIST 370 Colonial Mexico

                        HIST 371 Modern Mexico

                        HIST 372 Revolutions in 20th century Latin America

                        HIST 373 Latin America and Global Relations

                        HIST 470 Digital History Seminar

                        HIST 476A Gender and Sexuality in Latin America

PHIL 305 Introduction to the Philosophy of Language

                        POLS 365 The United States and Latin America

                        PSYC 360 Psychology of Language

                        THEA 368 Digital Media Productions

A minor is required and may be taken in any area.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

No courses in the department may be taken by students majoring or minoring in modern languages for Pass/No Pass credit.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. 12 hours of courses numbered at 305 or above. In addition to 305 (which is compulsory for Plan A), 6 hours from 311, 312, 314, or 315; and 3 hours from 317, 319, 321, or 331.

Speech-Language Pathology & Audiology (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Speech-Language Pathology & Audiology

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Cameya Ramirez

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Sherri Jones, 301 Barkley Memorial Center

The program in Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology is housed in the Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders in the College of Education and Human Sciences. The program offers both a bachelor of arts degree and a bachelor of science degree through the College of Arts and Sciences and a bachelor of science degree through the College of Education and Human Sciences. Both degrees provide the preprofessional courses required for graduate study in either speech-language pathology or audiology. The entry level for practice as a speech-language pathologist requires a masters degree. A doctorate of audiology (AuD) is required to practice audiology. For information on programs leading to degrees and for a detailed description of courses required, please see the College of Education and Human Sciences section of this bulletin.

Teacher certification in speech-language pathology requires a masters degree with specialization in speech-language pathology, passing scores on the Pre-Professional Skills Test, satisfactory completion of EDPS 250, EDPS 251, or CYAF 160, EDPS 362 and SLPA 488 or TEAC 330 or the graduate-level equivalents. Completion of a masters degree with specialization in speech-language pathology and a passing score on the speech-language pathology Praxis national certification exam is required for state licensure and/or public school certification in speech-language pathology. A doctor of audiology degree (AuD) and a passing score on the audiology Praxis national certification exam is required for state licensure in audiology.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

55 to 56 hours: SLPA 150, SLPA 250, SLPA 251, SLPA 271, SLPA 397A (1 hr); SLPA 421, SLPA 441, SLPA 452, SLPA 455, SLPA 456, SLPA 461, SLPA 461L, SLPA 464, SLPA 472; STAT 218, SPED 400 and SLPA 454; biological sciences anatomy (5 hr) or human physiology (4 hr) and a physical science (3 hr min)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Six or less Pass/No Pass credit hours may be accepted in major area course work.

GPA Requirements

Need overall minimum major GPA of B/3.0.

Speech-Language Pathology (CEHS)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Speech-Language Pathology (CEHS)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Cameya Ramirez-Rousseau

DESCRIPTION

In addition to this pre-professional program, students must also complete a masters degree in speech-language pathology before they can obtain their licensure and/or certification. Upon completion of the speech-language pathology endorsement, a person may serve as a speech-language pathologist and/or resource person.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the curriculum and these must be successfully completed in order to be certified in the teaching profession. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Felony and Misdemeanor Conviction” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30-32

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. COMM 109 or COMM 209 or COMM 210 or ALEC 102 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 or EDPS 459 (Professional SLPA Requirement) 3

ACE 4. Any PHYS or CHEM course 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. EDPS 250 or EDPS 251 or CYAF 160 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. SLPA 488 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 10. SLPA 421 (Professional SLPA Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Education Requirements 9

*EDPS 362 3

TEAC 259 3

*TEAC 331 or TEAC 430 or TEAC 431 or TEAC 434 or TEAC 437 3

Speech-Language Pathology Pre-Professional Requirements 16-17

SLPA 150 3

SLPA 250 3

SLPA 251 3

SLPA 271 3

*BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L or BIOS 214 4-5

Speech-Language Pathology Professional Requirements 29-32

SLPA 397A 1

SLPA 441 (Optional for students continuing in Audiology) 3

SLPA 452 3

SLPA 454 3

SLPA 455 4

SLPA 456 4

SLPA 461 & SLPA 461L 4

SLPA 464 4

SLPA 472 3

SPED 400 3

Electives 30-36

Total Hours 120

* These courses are also approved ACE courses and together with the 30 hours of ACE Required Courses meet the additional ACE/General Education requirements for secondary education students.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADMISSION

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission into the undergraduate pre-professional training program in SLPA does not guarantee admission into graduate school for SLPA. Although a student initially takes four pre-professional SLPA courses, the Speech-Language Pathology program has competitive admission requirements into the advanced professional phases of the program. Students must apply by September 15th for a spring admission or by February 1st for a fall admission and must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the program:

1. Must have earned a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit with a minimum 3.2 cumulative GPA.

2. Completion of the pre-professional SLPA classes (SLPA 150, SLPA 250, SLPA 251, and SLPA 271) by the end of the semester in which you apply and with a minimum average 3.2 GPA.

3. Completion of BIOS 213 and 213L or BIOS 214.

4. Completion of TEAC 331, COMM 109, and EDPS 250 or 251 or approved substitutes with no grade lower than a C.

5. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of the Praxis I, Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

6. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form (PPF) as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

MAJOR/PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS

Pre-Professional SLPA Requirements

Complete the following course work by the end of the semester in which you apply to the Professional Program. A minimum GPA of 3.2 in the four pre-professional SLPA courses and a cumulative GPA of 3.2 or higher is necessary to apply to the program. All grades must be C or above.

SLPA 150, SLPA 250, SLPA 251, SLPA 271, BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L or BIOS 214 (Must be completed before application.)

NOTE: SLPA students who complete sufficient course work in education will receive a minor in education along with the major degree.

OTHER

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Statistics Minor (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Statistics (Minor only)

DEGREES OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 14-15

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISERS: Erin Blankenship, Steve Kachman

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Steve Kachman, 340 Hardin

Professors: Bilder, Blankenship, Eskridge, Kachman, Ladunga, Marx, McCutcheon, Parkhurst, Stroup, Zhang

Associate Professors: Soulakova, Wang

Assistant Professor: Hanford

Statistics is the science of data collection, classification, analysis and interpretation. It has evolved into a core discipline for a well-rounded liberal arts education, and is of central importance to nearly all of the biological, physical and social sciences. The Department of Statistics offers introductory courses to acquaint students from all disciplines with the essential elements of statistical thinking.

The department offers a minor in statistics. The minor is a useful complement for many majors. In addition, the minor provides background beneficial for graduate study in statistics. Career opportunities for statisticians with masters and doctoral degrees abound in industry, government and education. Employers include pharmaceutical, health and medical organizations, quality improvement in manufacturing and service, marketing and opinion research, credit and security risk analysis, agribusiness, various governmental agencies including Environmental Protection, Food and Drug Administration, Departments of Census, Energy, Agriculture, and Homeland Security, and emerging fields ranging from bioinformatics to statistical applications in sports.

Graduate Work. The following advanced degrees are offered: master of science and doctor of philosophy in statistics. For details, see the Graduate Bulletin.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Track A: STAT 462 and STAT 463, and at least 6 hours from the following: STAT 318, STAT 380, STAT 412, STAT 414, STAT 450, STAT 494 or STAT 496

Track B: STAT 218 and STAT 318, and at least 9 hours from the following: STAT 412, STAT 414, STAT 450, STAT 462, STAT 463, STAT 494 or STAT 496

Alternative classes may be substituted if approved by the Department of Statistics curriculum committee.

Classes taken for a minor in statistics may not be taken Pass/No Pass.

If a student receives a grade lower than C in a course, the course may not be used to satisfy the statistics minor requirements.

Textile & Apparel Design

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Textile & Apparel Design

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

Textile and apparel design emphasizes creative problem solving and the development of technical skills related to apparel and textile design and theory, apparel pattern making, computer-aided design, and printing and dyeing techniques. Professional support is provided in business and in art and art history, theatre arts and dance, or history. The program is planned for students with professional interest in textile and apparel design, product development, and fiber arts.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 31-32

ACE 1. ENGL 101 or ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 3

ACE 2. TMFD 144 (Introductory Courses) 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 or EDPS 459 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 105 or CHEM 109 or CHEM 113 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. TMFD 407 (Common Completion Course) 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 or SOCI 101 (Supporting Courses) 3-4

ACE 7. AHIS 101 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 8. ECON 200 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 9. TMFD 123 (Introductory Course) 3

ACE 10. TMFD 412 (Common Completion Course) 3

Introductory & Common Completion Courses 34

TMFD 101 1

TMFD 206, TMFD 212, TMFD 213, TMFD 216, TMFD 225 (3 hrs ea) 15

TMFD 104, TMFD 145, TMFD 146 7

TMFD 405, TMFD 406, TMFD 422 (3 hrs ea) 9

TMFD 498 or TMFD 492 2

Supporting Courses 22-24

ACCT 200 3

AHIS 102 3

LIBR 110 1

MATH 101 or MATH 104 or MATH 106 3-5

Select one course from the following: 3

JGEN 120 or JGEN 200 or JGEN 220 or COMM 286

Select three courses from the following: 9

Art, art history, dance, theatre arts or photo journalism or JGEN 184, JOUR 404, ENTR 321 or ENTR 422, MNGT 321 or MNGT 422, appropriate advanced MATH & STAT courses (see adviser)

Professional Textile and Apparel Design Courses 22

TMFD 112 1

TMFD 312, TMFD 313, TMFD 403, TMFD 408, TMFD 416, TMFD 471 (3 hrs ea) 18

Select 3 hrs from the following: 3

TMFD 325, TMFD 410 or TMFD 425 or TMFD 472

Electives 8-11

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Minor Options

Students may receive a minor in hospitality, restaurant and tourism management (19 hrs) or a business minor (18 hrs). See adviser.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Textile and apparel design majors must take the following classes in sequence:

TMFD 212 Product Development II: Apparel Analysis & Development

TMFD 312 Product Development III: Fashion Analysis & Presentation

TMFD 412 Product Development IV: Trend Analysis & Product Conceptualization

TMFD 216 Apparel Design by Flat Pattern

TMFD 403 Apparel Design by Draping

TMFD 416 Apparel Design for Industry

Pass/No Pass Option

No required course work in the textiles, merchandising and fashion design department can be taken Pass/No Pass by textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed.

Substitution and Wavier Forms

Substitution and waiver forms must be processed prior to the semester of graduation and must be processed prior to enrolling in the substituted course. All course prerequisites must be met prior to enrollment.

Internship or Study Tour Requirement

All students are required to participate in either an internship or study tour experience, or both, during their program. Internships are qualified by a minimum GPA requirement. Textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors have the opportunity to study abroad at institutions such as the American Intercontinental University in London, for both the summer and semester education abroad programs.

Textile Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Textile Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The textile science option emphasizes textiles and biofibers, textile production, and issues concerning the global textile industry. Professional support in related sciences and business is required. The program is planned for students interested in sales, research, or management in the textile industry. It is also recommended for students who plan to go on to graduate school in either textiles or related sciences. Students are eligible to receive a minor in chemistry from the UNL College of Arts and Sciences.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 31-32

ACE 1. ENGL 101 or ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 3

ACE 2. TMFD 144 (Introductory  Course) 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 or EDPS 459 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 or CHEM 113 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 5. TMFD 407 (Common Completion Course) 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 or SOCI 101 (Supporting Course) 3-4

ACE 7. AHIS 101 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 8. ECON 200 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 9. TMFD 123 (Introductory Course) 3

ACE 10. TMFD 412 (Common Completion Course) 3

Introductory & Common Completion Courses 29

TMFD 101 1

TMFD 112 1

TMFD 104, TMFD 145, TMFD 146 7

TMFD 206, TMFD 212, TMFD 213 9

TMFD 405, TMFD 422, TMFD 410 9

TMFD 498 or TMFD 492 2

Supporting Courses 41-44

AHIS 102 3

CHEM 110 (4 hrs) or CHEM 114 (3 hrs) 3-4

CHEM 221 4

CHEM 251 (3 hrs) & CHEM 253 (1 hr) or CHEM 255 (3 hrs) & CHEM 257 (1 hr) 4

CHEM 252 (3 hrs) & CHEM 254 (1 hr) 4

CHEM 261 (3 hrs) & CHEM 263 (2 hrs) 5

CHEM 262 (3 hrs) & CHEM 264 (2 hrs) 5

LIBR 110 1

MATH 101 or MATH 104 or MATH 106 3-5

Select one course from the following: 3

JGEN 120, JGEN 200, JGEN 220, COMM 286

Select 6 hrs from any of the following areas: 6

ACCT, BLAW, CHEM, CSCE, ECON, ENTR, FINA, MATH, MNGT, MRKT, PHYS

Professional Textile Courses 15

TMFD 406, TMFD 428, TMFD 499 9

Select 6 hrs from the following: 6

TMFD 216, TMFD 225, TMFD 313, TMFD 325, TMFD 408, TMFD 425, TMFD 492, TMFD 498

Electives 0-4

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Minor Requirements

Students may receive a minor in Chemistry (27 hrs), Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management (19 hrs) or a Business minor (18 hrs). Minors may also be taken in Global Studies or in Women’s and Gender Studies. The student should see their adviser for more information.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Please note the following department specific requirements:

1. No required course work in the textiles, merchandising and fashion design department can be taken Pass/No Pass by textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed.

2. Substitution and waiver forms must be processed prior to the semester of graduation and must be processed prior to enrolling in the substituted course. All course prerequisites must be met prior to enrollment.

3. All students are required to participate in either an internship or study tour experience, or both, during their program. Internships are qualified by a minimum GPA requirement. Textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors have the opportunity to study abroad at institutions such as the American Intercontinental University in London, for both the summer and semestereducation abroadprograms.

Textiles, Merchandising & Fashion Design/Communications

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Textiles, Merchandising & Fashion Design/Communications

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

This specialization is a joint program between the Department of Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design and the College of Journalism and Mass Communications. The student combines a background in textiles including course work in textile science, textile and apparel design and merchandising, with the advertising area of journalism.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 31-32

ACE 1. ADPR 283 (Professional Course) 3

ACE 2. TMFD 144 (Introductory Courses) 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 or EDPS 459 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 105 or CHEM 109 or CHEM 113 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. TMFD 407 (Common Completion Course) 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 or SOCI 101 (Supporting Courses) 3-4

ACE 7. AHIS 101 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 8. ECON 200 (Supporting Course) 3

ACE 9. TMFD 123 (Introductory Course) 3

ACE 10. TMFD 412 (Common Completion Course) 3

Introductory & Common Completion Courses 29

TMFD 101 1

TMFD 112 1

TMFD 206, TMFD 212, TMFD 213, TMFD 405, TMFD 406, TMFD 422 18

TMFD 104, TMFD 145, TMFD 146 7

TMFD 498 or TMFD 492 2

Supporting Courses 7-9

AHIS 102 3

LIBR 110 1

MATH 101 or MATH 104 or MATH 106 3-5

Professional TMFD/Communications Courses 45

TMFD 312, TMFD 314, TMFD 408 9

Select 3 hrs from the following: 3

TMFD 216, TMFD 225, TMFD 313, TMFD 325, TMFD 410, TMFD 425, TMFD 428, TMFD 492, TMFD 498

ADPR 251 & ADPR 489 6

JOMC 101, JOMC 486, JOMC 487 9

JOMC 160, JOMC 161 6

Select any 12 hours from journalism courses 12

Electives 5-8

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass

No course in the Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design Minor can be taken Pass/No Pass.

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Please note the following department specific requirements:

1. No required course work in the textiles, merchandising and fashion design department can be taken Pass/No Pass by textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed.

2. Substitution and waiver forms must be processed prior to the semester of graduation and must be processed prior to enrolling in the substituted course. All course prerequisites must be met prior to enrollment.

3. All students are required to participate in either an internship or study tour experience, or both, during their program. Internships are qualified by a minimum GPA requirement. Textiles, merchandising and fashion design majors have the opportunity to study abroad at institutions such as the American Intercontinental University in London, for both the summer and semester education abroad programs.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design Minor – 15 hours

(This minor is not an option for marketing majors.)

TMFD 123 Clothing & Human Behavior (3 cr)

TMFD 121 Design Essentials (3 cr)

TMFD 206 Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry (3 cr)

Select 3 hours from the following:

TMFD 144 Introduction to Design Theory and Criticism (3 cr)

TMFD 405 Advanced Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 407 History of Costume (3 cr)

TMFD 408 History of Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 422 International Textile & Apparel Sourcing (3 cr)

Theatre-Performance

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Theatre-Performance

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Harris Smith

DESCRIPTION

Director: Paul Steger, 215 Temple Building

Professors: Grange, O'Connor, V. Smith, Steger

Associate Professors: Brown, Endacott, H. Smith, Stauffer, Teo-Gooding

Assistant Professors: Borden, Kolbe, Shoemaker, Veneziano

Assistant Professor of Practice: Patterson

This program offers comprehensive actor training through a core of eight different acting courses, which move from basic process work to detailed exploration of specific technical and stylistic demands. The emphasis also offers up to four semesters each of voice and speech training and movement training.

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical and Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Library 110 1

Theatre Core Requirements 39

Performance Emphasis Requirements 22

Electives 22-28

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

BA Core Requirements 39

THEA 112G Introduction to Theatre 3

THEA 114 Basic Acting Techniques I 3

THEA 115 Basic Acting Techniques II 3

THEA 201 Technical Theatre Practice 3

THEA 202 Play Direction I 3

THEA 204 Stage Makeup 3

THEA 223 Intermediate Acting I 3

THEA 234 Scripts in Performance 3

THEA 253 Voice Production for the Stage 3

THEA 255 Stage Movement I 3

THEA 335 History of Theatre I 3

THEA 336 History of Theatre II 3

THEA 472 Theatre Perspectives 3

Emphasis Requirements

Performance Emphasis Requirements 22

THEA 224 Intermediate Acting II 3

THEA 254 Stage Diction & Dialects 3

THEA 256 Stage Movement II 3

THEA 401 Advanced Acting 9

THEA 408 Advanced Projects in Acting &/or Directing 1

Select one course from: 3

THEA 120 Principles of Design for Theatre & Film (3 cr)

THEA 210 Stage Lighting I (3 cr)

THEA 412 Scene Design I (3 cr)

THEA 418 Costume Design I (3 cr)

THEA 450 Sound Design I (3 cr)

Minor Requirements

Minors are allowed, but not required, with the theatre–performance emphasis.

Theatre majors may elect to specialize in musical theatre through the minor in musical theatre. This option is open only to students with a major in theatre or music. To qualify for the required voice lessons, students must audition for the Glenn Korff School of Music voice faculty for acceptance as a musical theatre minor.

Plan A minor in Musical Theatre (theatre majors) – 25 credits

MUSC 131 Keyboard Skills I 1

MUSC 132 Keyboard Skills II 1

MUSC 160 Music as Art, Discipline, & Profession 3

MUSC 165 Musicianship I 2

MUSC 165A Musicianship I Lab 1

MUOP 455 Musical Theatre Techniques 3

Applied voice lessons (MUAP 101, MUAP 201) 5

Choral Ensembles 2

Productions 2

Dance (movement) courses 5

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Advancement in Major

Review and screening for continuation in this emphasis are done when students are enrolled in THEA 223 Intermediate Acting I (typically their third semester as theatre majors). The review includes an interview, an audition, and an analysis of the overall academic and artistic record; all of which are used to determine potential for success throughout the course of study. Approved students are permitted to enroll in THEA 224 Intermediate Acting II and in subsequent required performance emphasis courses.

Students in the Theatre-Performance emphasis are expected to maintain a 2.5 cumulative GPA throughout their career. Transcripts will be reviewed periodically to ensure satisfactory progress. Failure to maintain a 2.5 GPA may result in dismissal from the program.

Grade Rules

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Both new and transfer students wishing to complete the performance emphasis must audition for the program.